<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[BREAD PHENO: Development and Field Testing of Paper-based Biosensors to Increase Productivity of Smallholder Agriculture in Developing Countries]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dokamuro@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924508</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Yams (Dioscorea species) are among the primary agricultural commodities and major staple crop in Africa, India, South East Asia, South America and the Caribbean. However, the crop is laden with serious production problems arising from factors such as anthracnose disease, pests, and declines in soil fertility. This project seeks to revolutionize yam production in developing countries through the development and field-testing of low-cost genotyping/phenotyping biosensors that contain an integrated paper-based biobattery.  These proof-of-concept devices will provide self-sustainable, field-tested sensing systems that can be used to detect the presence of disease causing pathogens by smallholder farmers in the developing world. The project will provide international interdisciplinary research training for students and postdoctoral researchers. All project outcomes will be available for use by the scientific community. DNA sequences will be available through GenBank.  Information about biosensors will be provided through multiple mechanisms that include peer-reviewed publications as well as organized field-testing by smallholder farmers using standard protocols and handouts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will address some of the fundamental research and constraint issues associated with decreased yam production in developing countries. This project aims to develop and characterize the next generation of low-cost biosensors that can be used to assess differences in virulence and inter- and/or intraspecific genetic diversity in fungal isolates that cause anthracnose diseases in Dioscorea alata and Dioscorea cayanensis, two species of yams. Specific objectives are to (i) conduct molecular and biochemical characterization of healthy and fungal-infected yam varieties to identify DNA markers associated with up to 150-180 field-collected fungal isolates; ii) use markers as the basis for designing a multiplex SNP paper-based bioassay to detect the presence of fungal pathogens; iii) attach biosensor that is powered by a novel microbial-based bio-battery to the back of a smartphone; sensor signals could be read visually or via custom-based applications (apps) to be developed for smartphones; and, iv) develop standardized protocols for screening yams for anthracnose resistance using the new biosensing tools as a first step to deploying the technology in the field.  It is anticipated that the proposed devices can serve as a model for transforming low-cost tools into precision agriculture to promote increased food production in developing countries in developing countries. In addition, the project can potentially shift the paradigm for flexible and stackable paper-based batteries by enabling, through their architecture and design, exceptional electrical characteristics and functionalities.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044563</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Omowunmi</FirstName>
<LastName>Sadik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Omowunmi A Sadik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sadik@njit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000426798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>323 DR MARTIN LUTHER KING JR BLV</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SGBMHQ7VXNH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW JERSEY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>SGBMHQ7VXNH5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Jersey Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7681</Code>
<Text>ENG NNI Special Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8288</Code>
<Text>BM Gates Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7577</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH RESOURCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8288</Code>
<Text>BMGF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>40XX</Code>
<Name>NSF TRUST FUND</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>048960</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Products</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Peer-reviewed Publications</span></p> <ol> <li>Francis J. Osonga, Ali Akgul, Idris Yazgan, Ayfer Akgul, Gaddi B. Eshun, Laura Sakhaee,&nbsp; and Omowunmi A. Sadik*, <strong>Size and shape-dependent antimicrobial activities of silver and gold nanoparticles: A model study as potential fungicides, <em>Molecules</em></strong>, <strong>2020</strong>, 25(11), 2682.</li> <li><em>Francis J. Osonga,<sup> 1</sup> Gaddi B. Eshun,<sup> 1</sup> Sanjay Kalra,<sup> 2</sup> </em><em>Idris Yazgan,</em><em><sup> 2&Dagger;</sup></em><em> Laura Sakhaee,<sup> 2</sup>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Renata Ontman, <sup>2 </sup></em><em>Shaojie Jiang, <sup>2</sup> &amp; Omowunmi A. Sadik<sup>1</sup>*</em><strong> Greener Synthesis and Characterization of Copper Nanocubes and its antifungal activities against the crop pathogen <em>Penicillium italicum. </em></strong>Submitted to <em>ACS Agricultural Science &amp; Technology</em> (2021) - in peer review.</li> </ol> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Presentations</span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span>3. Francis J.&nbsp; Osonga<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">,</span></strong> Ali Akgul, Idris Yazgan, Ayfer Akgul, Gaddi B. Eshun, Laura Sakhaee, and Omowunmi A. Sadik, Size and shape-dependent antimicrobial activities of silver and gold nanoparticles: A model study as potential fungicides:<strong> </strong>(<strong>Oral presentation</strong><strong>) </strong><strong>ACS Spring 2021 Virtual Conference April 14, 2021</strong></p> <p><strong></strong>4. Francis J.&nbsp; Osonga, Gaddi B. Eshun, Sanjay D. Kalra, Idris Yazgan, Laura Sakhaee,&nbsp; and&nbsp; Omowunmi A. Sadik Greener synthesis, characterization and antimicrobial studies of copper nanocubes using quercetin macromolecules: (<strong>Oral presentation</strong><strong>) </strong><strong>ACS Spring 2021 Virtual Conference April 14, 2021</strong></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Patent Awarded</span></p> <p><a style="font-size: 0.75em;" href="https://patents.justia.com/patent/11091597">Packaging material and methods of using the same</a>, Patent number:&nbsp;11091597</p> <p>Abstract:&nbsp;The present disclosure is directed to films. The films can include polyamic acid (PAA). Methods of making and using the film for food product coverings is also included.</p> <p>Type:&nbsp;Grant</p> <p>Filed:&nbsp;May 23, 2018</p> <p>Date of Patent:&nbsp;August 17, 2021</p> <p>Assignee:&nbsp;The Research Foundation for The State University of New York</p> <p>Inventors:&nbsp;Omowunmi A. Sadik, Idris Yazgan</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2021<br>      Modified by: Omowunmi&nbsp;A&nbsp;Sadik</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Products  Peer-reviewed Publications  Francis J. Osonga, Ali Akgul, Idris Yazgan, Ayfer Akgul, Gaddi B. Eshun, Laura Sakhaee,  and Omowunmi A. Sadik*, Size and shape-dependent antimicrobial activities of silver and gold nanoparticles: A model study as potential fungicides, Molecules, 2020, 25(11), 2682. Francis J. Osonga, 1 Gaddi B. Eshun, 1 Sanjay Kalra, 2 Idris Yazgan, 2&Dagger; Laura Sakhaee, 2    Renata Ontman, 2 Shaojie Jiang, 2 &amp; Omowunmi A. Sadik1* Greener Synthesis and Characterization of Copper Nanocubes and its antifungal activities against the crop pathogen Penicillium italicum. Submitted to ACS Agricultural Science &amp; Technology (2021) - in peer review.   Conference Presentations   3. Francis J.  Osonga, Ali Akgul, Idris Yazgan, Ayfer Akgul, Gaddi B. Eshun, Laura Sakhaee, and Omowunmi A. Sadik, Size and shape-dependent antimicrobial activities of silver and gold nanoparticles: A model study as potential fungicides: (Oral presentation) ACS Spring 2021 Virtual Conference April 14, 2021  4. Francis J.  Osonga, Gaddi B. Eshun, Sanjay D. Kalra, Idris Yazgan, Laura Sakhaee,  and  Omowunmi A. Sadik Greener synthesis, characterization and antimicrobial studies of copper nanocubes using quercetin macromolecules: (Oral presentation) ACS Spring 2021 Virtual Conference April 14, 2021  Patent Awarded  Packaging material and methods of using the same, Patent number: 11091597  Abstract: The present disclosure is directed to films. The films can include polyamic acid (PAA). Methods of making and using the film for food product coverings is also included.  Type: Grant  Filed: May 23, 2018  Date of Patent: August 17, 2021  Assignee: The Research Foundation for The State University of New York  Inventors: Omowunmi A. Sadik, Idris Yazgan          Last Modified: 09/02/2021       Submitted by: Omowunmi A Sadik]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
