<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: A tourism decision support system for Western gateway and natural amenity region communities]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49954.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49954</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandip Roy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Gateway and natural amenity regions (GNAR) throughout the Western U.S. are facing a number of unprecedented challenges that threaten their economies, the wellbeing of their residents, and the health of tourists who flock to these areas for recreation and rejuvenation. Most recently, the COVID-19 pandemic has led to virulent concerns amongst gateway community leaders about tourists spreading the virus, harming local residents, and overwhelming these communities’ limited healthcare resources. With local economies that depend on the flow of outdoor recreationists and tourists, the disruption of those flows can have immediate and disastrous consequences for communities in GNARs. This project's research team brings together expertise from the social and spatial sciences capable of transforming the way GNAR communities across the Western U.S. plan for and respond to interruptions in the flow of tourists brought about by natural disasters and crisis events like the COVID-19 pandemic. The vision is to develop predictive models of tourism flows and a respective decision support system that GNAR communities can use to explore and inform local policy decisions. This project will be integrating publicly available mobility data into an interactive tourism planning and management tool, rapidly accelerating the ability of these data to be used by GNAR communities in their efforts to plan for and manage tourism during natural disasters and crisis events. By leveraging an established research team with demonstrated experience integrating disparate datasets to quantify the volume and spatial distribution of tourism flows across large geographic scales, this project's data and models are ready to be piloted with willing GNAR communities throughout San Juan County, Utah – home to Navajo tribal lands and over a dozen small communities which are heavily reliant on tourism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By utilizing an inclusive engagement approach to develop a web-based decision support system, this project will bring new insights into the efficacy of co-producing knowledge and understanding through smart and connected technologies. The project will also advance our understanding of effective data visualization using free and open source web mapping approaches; and provide new knowledge on resilience indicators for GNARs throughout the Western U.S. These insights can be used to improve approaches to civic engagement in the context of complex feedbacks from natural hazards and other crisis events on local economies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044061</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Derek</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Berkel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Derek Van Berkel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dbvanber@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827116</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jordan</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jordan W Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[green.olympia@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000634439</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>LOGAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 OLD MAIN HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPE2YDWHDYU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Utah State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49954</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Gateway and natural amenity regions (GNAR) throughout the Western U.S. are facing a number of unprecedented challenges that threaten their economies, the wellbeing of their residents, and the health of tourists who flock to these areas for recreation and rejuvenation. Extreme heat events in the summer months have driven outdoor recreationists and tourists indoors. Smoke plumes from an increasing number of wildfires are affecting human health as well as regional economic activity. And most recently, the COVID-19 pandemic has led to virulent concerns amongst gateway community leaders about tourists spreading the virus, harming local residents, and overwhelming these communities? limited healthcare resources. With local economies that depend on the flow of outdoor recreationists and tourists, the disruption of those flows can have immediate and disastrous consequences for communities in GNARs. Our research team brings together expertise from the social and spatial sciences capable of transforming the way GNAR communities across the Western U.S. plan for and respond to interruptions in the flow of tourists brought about by natural disasters and crisis events like the COVID-19 pandemic. Through funding provided by the NSF Civic Innovation Challenge Planning Grant, <strong>we developed a decision support system that GNAR communities can use to explore and inform local policy decisions.</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The activities supported through our planning grant were organized into three phases: 1) Identification of civic needs and applicable scientific capacities; 2) Data curation and decision support system development; and 3) Tool evaluation and refinement (Figure 1).</p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>Identification of civic needs and applicable scientific capacities.</em></strong> We hosted a series of initial project kick-off workshops with stakeholders in GNAR communities throughout San Juan County, Utah in late January 2021. These stakeholders, which included municipal and county government officials, state and federal land management agencies, local business owners, and tribal representatives were identified by our civic partners, the San Juan County Tourism and Economic Development office. These initial discussions reveled a general sense of enthusiasm amongst our stakeholders. For example, a federal land manager noted ?this could be helpful to better prepare us for sudden changes in tourism, for example, does news about the region cause an increase in visitation. And what impact has the designation of Bears Ears National Monument had?? Another federal land manager noted, ?we can see if the peak tourism season has changed because of COVID.? The discussions also revealed some key insights for us to consider as we began to develop the tool.</p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>Data curation and decision support system development. </em></strong>In conjunction with the initial stakeholder engagement workshops, we developed the protocols and code to systematically identify all roadways entering and exiting municipalities and public land units in San Juan County. We established geofences at these locations and acquired mobile location data for all of these points using our data providers? API. These data characterize the mean hourly and mean monthly volume of non-local trips through a municipality or public land unit since January 2016 (Figure 2).</p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>We hosted the beta version of the App on our personal shinyapps.io cloud account, created a video describing the basic functions of the tool, and shared the video with stakeholders who were able to attend as well as those who could not make it. We held subsequent tool development workshops virtually with stakeholders in late February and early April. These two workshops also used structured collaborative design processes to help enable efficiency, inclusion, and transparency in the rapid prototyping of the tool. After each workshop, we refined the App making changes requested by the stakeholders.&nbsp;<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>Tool evaluation and refinement. </em></strong>The planning grant concluded with an evaluation workshop where stakeholders critically reviewed the utility of the App to inform their planning efforts and the development of local tourism and economic development policies. Our evaluation plan is grounded in Diffusion of Innovation Theory, which posits that individuals are more likely to adopt a new technology or tool if that technology or tool: 1) provides a relative advantage over existing tools; 2) is compatible with pre-existing systems; 3) is not complex or difficult to learn; 4) if it is easy to trial or test out; and 5) it yields observable results. We delivered an evaluation survey to all of the stakeholders who participated in our evaluation workshop, with the data revealing strong agreement with questions designed to gauge each of the five criteria likely to influence technological adoption (Figure 3).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In sum, the planning grant allowed us to generate a prototype decision support system with a limited set of functionalities. While these functionalities are limited, there was a strong and consistent sentiment of support from the stakeholders in San Juan County, Utah.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/19/2022<br>      Modified by: Jordan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642609500867_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642609500867_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Three phase diagram"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642609500867_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Three phase diagram"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The community-driven processes for designing the GNAR Compass App involved: 1) Identification of civic needs and scientific capabilities; 2) Data curation and decision support system development; 3) Tool evaluation and refinement.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jordan W. Smith</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jordan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Smith</div> <div class="imageTitle">Three phase diagram</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642609845029_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642609845029_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Horizontal bar chart of evaluation scores"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642609845029_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Horizontal bar chart of evaluation scores"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Evaluation scores from stakeholders who participated in our planning grant's evaluation workshop. Responses were measured on a 5-point Likert scale. (n = 12).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jordan W. Smith</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jordan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Smith</div> <div class="imageTitle">Horizontal bar chart of evaluation scores</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642610061891_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642610061891_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bar charts from online decision-support tool"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044061/2044061_10714816_1642610061891_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bar charts from online decision-support tool"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The beta version of the GNAR Compass App displays mean hourly and mean monthly local trips through a municipality. This example shows Bears Ears National Monument and the cities of Blanding and Bluff.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jordan W. Smith</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jordan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Smith</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bar charts from online decision-support tool</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Gateway and natural amenity regions (GNAR) throughout the Western U.S. are facing a number of unprecedented challenges that threaten their economies, the wellbeing of their residents, and the health of tourists who flock to these areas for recreation and rejuvenation. Extreme heat events in the summer months have driven outdoor recreationists and tourists indoors. Smoke plumes from an increasing number of wildfires are affecting human health as well as regional economic activity. And most recently, the COVID-19 pandemic has led to virulent concerns amongst gateway community leaders about tourists spreading the virus, harming local residents, and overwhelming these communities? limited healthcare resources. With local economies that depend on the flow of outdoor recreationists and tourists, the disruption of those flows can have immediate and disastrous consequences for communities in GNARs. Our research team brings together expertise from the social and spatial sciences capable of transforming the way GNAR communities across the Western U.S. plan for and respond to interruptions in the flow of tourists brought about by natural disasters and crisis events like the COVID-19 pandemic. Through funding provided by the NSF Civic Innovation Challenge Planning Grant, we developed a decision support system that GNAR communities can use to explore and inform local policy decisions.     The activities supported through our planning grant were organized into three phases: 1) Identification of civic needs and applicable scientific capacities; 2) Data curation and decision support system development; and 3) Tool evaluation and refinement (Figure 1).     Identification of civic needs and applicable scientific capacities. We hosted a series of initial project kick-off workshops with stakeholders in GNAR communities throughout San Juan County, Utah in late January 2021. These stakeholders, which included municipal and county government officials, state and federal land management agencies, local business owners, and tribal representatives were identified by our civic partners, the San Juan County Tourism and Economic Development office. These initial discussions reveled a general sense of enthusiasm amongst our stakeholders. For example, a federal land manager noted ?this could be helpful to better prepare us for sudden changes in tourism, for example, does news about the region cause an increase in visitation. And what impact has the designation of Bears Ears National Monument had?? Another federal land manager noted, ?we can see if the peak tourism season has changed because of COVID.? The discussions also revealed some key insights for us to consider as we began to develop the tool.     Data curation and decision support system development. In conjunction with the initial stakeholder engagement workshops, we developed the protocols and code to systematically identify all roadways entering and exiting municipalities and public land units in San Juan County. We established geofences at these locations and acquired mobile location data for all of these points using our data providers? API. These data characterize the mean hourly and mean monthly volume of non-local trips through a municipality or public land unit since January 2016 (Figure 2).     We hosted the beta version of the App on our personal shinyapps.io cloud account, created a video describing the basic functions of the tool, and shared the video with stakeholders who were able to attend as well as those who could not make it. We held subsequent tool development workshops virtually with stakeholders in late February and early April. These two workshops also used structured collaborative design processes to help enable efficiency, inclusion, and transparency in the rapid prototyping of the tool. After each workshop, we refined the App making changes requested by the stakeholders.       Tool evaluation and refinement. The planning grant concluded with an evaluation workshop where stakeholders critically reviewed the utility of the App to inform their planning efforts and the development of local tourism and economic development policies. Our evaluation plan is grounded in Diffusion of Innovation Theory, which posits that individuals are more likely to adopt a new technology or tool if that technology or tool: 1) provides a relative advantage over existing tools; 2) is compatible with pre-existing systems; 3) is not complex or difficult to learn; 4) if it is easy to trial or test out; and 5) it yields observable results. We delivered an evaluation survey to all of the stakeholders who participated in our evaluation workshop, with the data revealing strong agreement with questions designed to gauge each of the five criteria likely to influence technological adoption (Figure 3).     In sum, the planning grant allowed us to generate a prototype decision support system with a limited set of functionalities. While these functionalities are limited, there was a strong and consistent sentiment of support from the stakeholders in San Juan County, Utah.          Last Modified: 01/19/2022       Submitted by: Jordan W Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
