<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Genome Editing in Loblolly Pine for Sustainable Fiber Production in the Southern United States]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) project is to support the domestic lumber industry, specifically for loblolly pine, through biological research. The proposed project brings forestry within the scope of the emerging science of genome editing with powerful impacts. Enhanced traits allow commercial entities in pulp and paper manufacturing to save energy and chemical costs; a pulp and paper facility can potentially reduce costs by up to 6%, exceptional for an industry that provides everyday items, such as hygienic tissue and cardboard for deliveries, at thin profit margins. Furthermore, trees play an important role in carbon sequestration, but they need to survive the temperature changes and potential infestations. With the advance of the proposed technology, editing forests could eventually gain acceptance as a significant avenue to bioresource sustainability and carbon sequestration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project combines the insights of tree genetics with the power of genome editing to generate enhanced genotypes with functional attributes that improve tree growth, processing and sustainability. Based on an integrated predictive model of genes responsible for phenotypes of commercial interest in relevant species, it is possible to select combinations of genome editing targets responsible for enhanced phenotypes, such as lignin content and syringyl/guaiacyl ratio, to modulate the composition of trees as to increase their propensity for processing, their environmental resilience, or valuable commercial features. Using CRISPR-based genome editing technologies, the project will multiplex target these genetic sequences concurrently to generate the intended genetic alteration combinations, using expertise in delivery to commercially relevant elite germplasm. Conventional breeding in forestry is slow and cumbersome because the long generation time of trees requires decades per breeding cycle. No alternative technology is currently feasible for accelerated genetic improvement of forest trees. With the proposed technology, annual crops can be efficiently bred on biannual or annual cycles with the same or improved properties as their conventionally-bred counterparts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044721</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rodolphe</FirstName>
<LastName>Barrangou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rodolphe Barrangou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rodolphe@Tree-co.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826985</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TREECO, INC.</Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>276950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199461222</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>840 MAIN CAMPUS DR PARTNERS II B</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 2513]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLYJJC8B6RT4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TREECO INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TREECO, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Loblolly pine (<em>Pinus taeda</em>) is the most widely distributed and commercially important tree species in the Southeastern US, constituting 71% of managed forests and producing ~2 billion tons of renewable woody biomass. These pine forests support 5.5% of the regional jobs and contribute 7.5% to the bioeconomy. The trees also supply 34% of the local water yield and sequesters up to 23% of the regional greenhouse gas emissions. Despite their ecological and economical importance, the sustainability and health of loblolly pine forests are increasing challenged by climate change, invasive pests and pathogens, deforestation due to urbanization, and higher demand for fiber products due to population increase. In anticipation of these challenges, the productivity, quality, and resilience of loblolly pine must be increased through transformational genetic approaches to secure the nation&rsquo;s supply of sustainable and renewable fiber and bio-based products. In this project, we established a transgene-free (no foreign DNA) method to edit the genome of loblolly pine. The method harnesses the power of CRISPR-Cas ribonucleoprotein (RNP) complexes (DNA-free molecular scalpel) and the tree&rsquo;s native DNA repair machinery to generate precise edits in the tree genome that mimics natural genetic variation. This safe and robust method enables an accelerated development of climate-resilient pine trees with superior wood quality. Traits such as fiber strength, disease and abiotic stress resistance, and flowering could be improved using the established transgene-free CRISPR system in this project, in order to mitigate the consequences of global warming and enhance the wood-based bioeconomy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To develop this method, we first initiated 79 somatic embryogenic (SE) cell lines using ~3000 seeds collected from 11 elite loblolly pine families. The SE cell lines were screened for growth and cell viability, and top-performing lines were used to generate protoplasts (cells devoid of cell walls) for genome editing. We iteratively optimized the procedures, reagents, and conditions for loblolly pine protoplasts isolation, purification, and transfection. Highly pure and viable protoplasts could be isolated from pine SE and successfully transfected with protein-RNA complexes. We then assembled transgene-free RNPs targeting genes associated with wood formation and disease resistance, and delivered them individually into loblolly pine protoplasts using the methods developed in this project. CRISPR-driven mutations were observed for the target genes, with a majority of edits represented by loss-of-function single nucleotide indels. In this study, we successfully established a system for transgene-free genome editing of SE-originated protoplasts from loblolly pine. The system could facilitate future efforts to develop safe and robust approaches to accelerate the genetic improvement of this important forest species, and enhance forest resilience, adaptation, and carbon capture to mitigate climate change. This project supported the research, education, and training of one PhD student, one master&rsquo;s student, two undergraduate students, and one senior research scientist. The project outcomes have been disseminated through presentations at national and international conferences, such as the Plant Biology Worldwide Summit, the Plant Genomics &amp; Gene Editing Congress: USA, the IUFRO Tree Biotechnology Conference, and the International Symposium on Forest Tree Molecular Biology and Biotechnology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Rodolphe&nbsp;Barrangou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Loblolly pine (Pinus taeda) is the most widely distributed and commercially important tree species in the Southeastern US, constituting 71% of managed forests and producing ~2 billion tons of renewable woody biomass. These pine forests support 5.5% of the regional jobs and contribute 7.5% to the bioeconomy. The trees also supply 34% of the local water yield and sequesters up to 23% of the regional greenhouse gas emissions. Despite their ecological and economical importance, the sustainability and health of loblolly pine forests are increasing challenged by climate change, invasive pests and pathogens, deforestation due to urbanization, and higher demand for fiber products due to population increase. In anticipation of these challenges, the productivity, quality, and resilience of loblolly pine must be increased through transformational genetic approaches to secure the nation’s supply of sustainable and renewable fiber and bio-based products. In this project, we established a transgene-free (no foreign DNA) method to edit the genome of loblolly pine. The method harnesses the power of CRISPR-Cas ribonucleoprotein (RNP) complexes (DNA-free molecular scalpel) and the tree’s native DNA repair machinery to generate precise edits in the tree genome that mimics natural genetic variation. This safe and robust method enables an accelerated development of climate-resilient pine trees with superior wood quality. Traits such as fiber strength, disease and abiotic stress resistance, and flowering could be improved using the established transgene-free CRISPR system in this project, in order to mitigate the consequences of global warming and enhance the wood-based bioeconomy.     To develop this method, we first initiated 79 somatic embryogenic (SE) cell lines using ~3000 seeds collected from 11 elite loblolly pine families. The SE cell lines were screened for growth and cell viability, and top-performing lines were used to generate protoplasts (cells devoid of cell walls) for genome editing. We iteratively optimized the procedures, reagents, and conditions for loblolly pine protoplasts isolation, purification, and transfection. Highly pure and viable protoplasts could be isolated from pine SE and successfully transfected with protein-RNA complexes. We then assembled transgene-free RNPs targeting genes associated with wood formation and disease resistance, and delivered them individually into loblolly pine protoplasts using the methods developed in this project. CRISPR-driven mutations were observed for the target genes, with a majority of edits represented by loss-of-function single nucleotide indels. In this study, we successfully established a system for transgene-free genome editing of SE-originated protoplasts from loblolly pine. The system could facilitate future efforts to develop safe and robust approaches to accelerate the genetic improvement of this important forest species, and enhance forest resilience, adaptation, and carbon capture to mitigate climate change. This project supported the research, education, and training of one PhD student, one master’s student, two undergraduate students, and one senior research scientist. The project outcomes have been disseminated through presentations at national and international conferences, such as the Plant Biology Worldwide Summit, the Plant Genomics &amp; Gene Editing Congress: USA, the IUFRO Tree Biotechnology Conference, and the International Symposium on Forest Tree Molecular Biology and Biotechnology.          Last Modified: 01/04/2023       Submitted by: Rodolphe Barrangou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
