<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Dust Driven Multiphase Hydrodynamics in Planetary Nebulae]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>251831.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>251831</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Glen Langston</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>glangsto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924937</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Average stars, like the sun, eventually use up all their fuel and die. They leave behind beautiful corpses in the form large glowing clouds of gas and dust known as planetary nebulae. These nebulae are stunning and colorful with diverse and distinctive shapes, earning them names like cat?s eye, helix, and dumbbell. While a nebula is born from a round star, different effects in the life of stars result in nebulae with these distinctive shapes, for unknown reasons. These nebulae are also important sources of cosmic dust; it is this dust from which our planet and we were made. The role of dust in the shaping and aging of these nebulae is not well understood. The investigators study how the shapes of planetary nebulae can be explained by the interactions of gas flows, light, and dust particles that come from the star, just prior to its death. The shaping of these planetary nebulae occurs over thousands of years and at distances of many trillions of miles, making it difficult to experiment with them. Instead, the investigators will create super-computer simulations of planetary nebulae.  These models run in hours instead of thousands of years. These models give a better understanding of the interactions of dust, light, and gas. The investigators will compare their model results to observations of real planetary nebulae. This project combines knowledge from both astrophysics and engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This interdisciplinary approach will also apply to training graduate students and conducting K-12 outreach, using both engineering and astrophysics. The investigators will create classroom activities that help K-12 students understand the interactions of light and matter.  &lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The primary objective of this work is to determine the role of dust in the formation of observed small-scale (cometary knots) and large-scale (bipolar axisymmetric ejecta) hydrodynamic features found in planetary nebulae. The investigators hypothesize that these events are driven by multiphase coupling of dust and gas in shock and radiation driven hydrodynamics arising from perturbed, heterogeneous, initial conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044625</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>McFarland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob McFarland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mcfarlandja@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000679245</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778433124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3124 TAMU</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Spence Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1216</Code>
<Text>GALACTIC ASTRONOMY PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~6456</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~121133</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~124242</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought to understand how stars, like our own sun late in its life, distribute dust (solid particles of heavier elements like carbon, silicon, and oxygen) out to the distant surrounding space. This dust is important as it can group together again to form large rocky bodies like our own planet. The processing of this dust by these stars is poorly understood, and it seems to be grouped together into large clumps as the star evolves. As the star consumes its remaining fuel, it leaves behind a large glowing cloud (known as a planetary nebula) that highlights the presence of these dust clumps in diverse and distinctive features, such as the cometary knots observed in the helix nebula. The mechanisms for this clumping are unknown and important to determining how dust survives in these stellar remnants. The evolution of these features occurs over thousands of years such that we have not observed even a small part of their formation and growth. Instead of waiting for these features to evolve over hundreds of years, we can instead simulate them on super computers in hours if we understand the physics and use the correct models for dust, gas, and radiation interactions.</p> <p>In this project we first developed and tested such models. We used an approach where the gas was simulated on one mesh, as engineers would do for flow over an airplane wing, while the dusts was simulated one discrete points moving through the gas. We implemented new models that allowed these points to simulate the effects of dust around a star, such as a drag model allowing the dust to pull the gas with it, a heat transfer model allowing the gas and dust to be heated by one another, and a radiation model allowing light from the star to push the dust away. The models were tested against previous simpler simulation and shown to produce the desired effects, and some new unexpected results, such a significant amount of heat being produced from drag, much like friction in an engine produces additional heat.</p> <p>These models were then applied in a simulation of a dust-producing star. To do this, we had to develop a simple model for such a star based on the available information for these stars (what we have measured from observation of distant stars) and our ability to simulate them (how much computer processing power we could get). Since we did not know ahead of time what conditions might be important to the formation of dust clumps, we tested various possible conditions around the stars, such as fluctuating light intensity from the star and clustering of dust particles due to the gas flow. We found that the conditions around these stars worked against the formation of clumps, and that strong clumps would have to be created near the star to survive the processing by forces (e.g. radiation and drag) as the dust traveled away from the star, out to distant space.</p> <p>The project also supported the training of graduate students from underrepresented groups, studying in both engineering and astrophysics. These students benefited from this interdisciplinary project, learning methods and knowledge from both engineering and physics. Two students will earn their doctoral degrees in engineering as a result of this project and one in physics and astronomy. This project also supported outreach efforts, and lead to the development of remote activities during the covid pandemic that allowed K-12 students to interact with scientists in astrophysics and to learn about how light and dust interact.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/09/2023<br>      Modified by: Jacob&nbsp;Mcfarland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought to understand how stars, like our own sun late in its life, distribute dust (solid particles of heavier elements like carbon, silicon, and oxygen) out to the distant surrounding space. This dust is important as it can group together again to form large rocky bodies like our own planet. The processing of this dust by these stars is poorly understood, and it seems to be grouped together into large clumps as the star evolves. As the star consumes its remaining fuel, it leaves behind a large glowing cloud (known as a planetary nebula) that highlights the presence of these dust clumps in diverse and distinctive features, such as the cometary knots observed in the helix nebula. The mechanisms for this clumping are unknown and important to determining how dust survives in these stellar remnants. The evolution of these features occurs over thousands of years such that we have not observed even a small part of their formation and growth. Instead of waiting for these features to evolve over hundreds of years, we can instead simulate them on super computers in hours if we understand the physics and use the correct models for dust, gas, and radiation interactions.  In this project we first developed and tested such models. We used an approach where the gas was simulated on one mesh, as engineers would do for flow over an airplane wing, while the dusts was simulated one discrete points moving through the gas. We implemented new models that allowed these points to simulate the effects of dust around a star, such as a drag model allowing the dust to pull the gas with it, a heat transfer model allowing the gas and dust to be heated by one another, and a radiation model allowing light from the star to push the dust away. The models were tested against previous simpler simulation and shown to produce the desired effects, and some new unexpected results, such a significant amount of heat being produced from drag, much like friction in an engine produces additional heat.  These models were then applied in a simulation of a dust-producing star. To do this, we had to develop a simple model for such a star based on the available information for these stars (what we have measured from observation of distant stars) and our ability to simulate them (how much computer processing power we could get). Since we did not know ahead of time what conditions might be important to the formation of dust clumps, we tested various possible conditions around the stars, such as fluctuating light intensity from the star and clustering of dust particles due to the gas flow. We found that the conditions around these stars worked against the formation of clumps, and that strong clumps would have to be created near the star to survive the processing by forces (e.g. radiation and drag) as the dust traveled away from the star, out to distant space.  The project also supported the training of graduate students from underrepresented groups, studying in both engineering and astrophysics. These students benefited from this interdisciplinary project, learning methods and knowledge from both engineering and physics. Two students will earn their doctoral degrees in engineering as a result of this project and one in physics and astronomy. This project also supported outreach efforts, and lead to the development of remote activities during the covid pandemic that allowed K-12 students to interact with scientists in astrophysics and to learn about how light and dust interact.       Last Modified: 01/09/2023       Submitted by: Jacob Mcfarland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
