<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Enhancing Communities Preparedness and Resilience to Post-Wildfire Hydrology in Mountainous Areas]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>41287.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>41287</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Bushnell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lbushnel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Post-wildfire disasters such as flash floods, severe erosion, and debris flows like the Montecito, CA event that killed 23 people in 2018 are becoming more costly to lives and infrastructure. These disasters are anticipated to increase following the record wildfire season just experienced across the western U.S. Post-wildfire disasters cross multiple scientific disciplines and impact local communities to government agencies. A lack of observations in mountainous regions for weather, water, and land management has significantly limited the progression of scientific knowledge to better monitor and forecast post-wildfire disasters. Facing increased risk of damage to societal infrastructure and loss of human life, communities have identified the benefits from gap-filling observations of precipitation and surface water.  This project proposes to unite the scientific community, bridge with local entities, and coordinate observations and research efforts targeting the common goal of enhancing knowledge on post-wildfire hydrology and reducing the effects of post-wildfire disasters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will address both civic priorities and foster research by advancing monitoring technologies and forecasting tools of risk related to post-wildfire hydrology, which are currently inadequate in complex terrain. The University of Oklahoma and National Severe Storms Laboratory researchers will reach out to and work with core civic partners to refine the needs of communities and match expertise in hydrometeorology, social science, radar field observations, and research-to-operations experience to design a field deployment strategy in Colorado during the Stage 2 portion of the project. The project will establish a “mobile observatory” on burn areas comprised of mobile weather radars, stream sensors, disdrometers, and rain gauges. Datasets collected will advance the scientific community by providing unique, post-wildfire observations, while immediately enhancing the preparedness and resiliency of local communities by providing real-time information and capabilities to map the anticipated impacts. The project will explore the benefits of “forecasting proximity” in terms of risk perception and engage communities through local forecasting while improving their connections to the operational forecast grid. The proposed pilot project will make several substantial contributions to hydrologic, operational forecasting, and risk assessment sciences, with direct benefit to local communities. Because post-wildfire disasters impact basins and communities across the West, an advisory board committee will be set up that will involve several government agencies and local stakeholders from western states. It will foster the creation of coalitions for mobile observations beyond this pilot project. The results will shift flash-flooding prediction science and post-fire landscape management that translates into increased societal resilience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044056</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gourley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan J Gourley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jj.gourley@noaa.gov]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000083737</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Bodine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David J Bodine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bodine@ou.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000603622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Reedy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin S Reedy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jreedy@ou.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000668767</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pierre</FirstName>
<LastName>Kirstetter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pierre Kirstetter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pierre-emmanuel.kirstetter@ou.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>yagmur</FirstName>
<LastName>derin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>yagmur derin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yagmur.derin@ou.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834468</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>730193003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 PARRINGTON OVAL RM 301</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EVTSTTLCEWS5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oklahoma Norman Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~41287</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our team participated in community-of-practice activities organized by NSF and MetroLab Network, which included the writing of a press release, and participating in debates and interviews.</p> <p>Our team performed community deliberative engagement through exhaustive outreach. A workshop gathered actors involved in the mitigation of post-wildfire hydrology and community preparedness and resilience. We gathered input on civic priorities, needs, and risk perception; guidance for the project&rsquo;s design to enhance the existing hazard forecasts; and identified constraints shaping the actual implementation with civic and federal partners. The virtual workshop was hosted by the University of Oklahoma on April 8, 2021 and brought together more than 50 stakeholders from Colorado representing all actors involved in the mitigation of post-wildfire hydrology and in communities&rsquo; preparedness and resilience: leaders in emergency management (five different counties were represented); state agencies (e.g., Colorado Water Conservation Board, Colorado Division of Homeland Security &amp; Emergency Management, Colorado Department of Transportation); government agencies in research, training, and operations including forecasters (e.g., NWS, USGS, USFS, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers); nongovernmental organizations (e.g., Middle Colorado Watershed Council, Coalition for the Upper South Platte, Silver Jackets); and academia (OU, Colorado State University), for an energetic discussion on the challenges and potential opportunities to address flash flooding, severe erosion, and debris flows that often follow wildfires.</p> <p>To build a foundation for the workshop participants on the fundamental challenges, terminology, and potential solutions relevant to post-wildfire hydrology, a primer on the various societal, scientific, and forecasting challenges was provided through an initial &ldquo;Lightning Round&rdquo; of invited speakers highlighting local communities&rsquo;, EMs&rsquo;, and agencies&rsquo; perspectives. It was complemented by an overview of NWS operations and challenges in Colorado, and an OU/NSSL presentation on past experiences with mobile radar field deployments. After the Lightning Round, workshop participants were organized into four distinct &ldquo;Break-Out Sessions&rdquo; (BOS) for in-depth discussions focused on key questions regarding e.g., communities&rsquo; needs and risk perceptions, impact of local observations on Emergency Managers&rsquo; decision-making processes and NWS operations, and sustainability of the hydrometeorological mobile observatory. A final wrap-up session brought together all workshop participants for brief reports from the BOS moderators and general discussion with the entire group.&nbsp;<span>The workshop discussions led to several insightful conclusions that guided the project&rsquo;s direction, while clarifying the background and context, and highlighted constraints that shaped the Stage 2 proposal.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>Other outcomes include:</p> <ul> <li>Press release: University of Oklahoma scientists team up with the Colorado Water Conservation Board to&nbsp;meet a critical coordination need from local communities, state, and federal government agencies to mitigate the risk of hydrologic hazards following wildfires in the Intermountain West. A unique mobile observatory with real-time observations will enable more effective community responses.&nbsp;</li> <li>Link to abstract on nsf.gov:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2044056&amp;HistoricalAwards=false</li> <li>Social media:&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/NSFCIVIC/status/1415059534536527876">https://twitter.com/NSFCIVIC/status/1415059534536527876</a></li> <li>1-Page Project Overview tailored to a broad and diverse audience including community stakeholders and beneficiaries:</li> </ul> <p>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1MRNyR2at_3ooRMfP2SMcebZewOdmHiT6/view</p> <ul> <li>Project Video: https://vimeo.com/569906247</li> <li>Team Interview 1: https://vimeo.com/577332306</li> <li>Team Interview 2: https://vimeo.com/577332508</li> </ul> <p>A mentoring plan was designed following recommendations from the National Postdoctoral Association (NPA) and the National Academies of Sciences and Engineering and the Institute of Medicine 2000 report on &ldquo;Enhancing the Postdoctoral Experience for Scientists and Engineers&rdquo;. The workshop, the MetroLab activities, and the writing of the Stage 2 proposal provided unique learning and networking opportunities for the Postdoctoral Rearcher and students who were involved in its organization.</p> <p><span><span>Finally, this project provided opportunities for three early career faculty members (Dr. Kirstetter, Dee, and Reedy) to strengthen their research and education portfolios.</span><br /></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Pierre&nbsp;Kirstetter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our team participated in community-of-practice activities organized by NSF and MetroLab Network, which included the writing of a press release, and participating in debates and interviews.  Our team performed community deliberative engagement through exhaustive outreach. A workshop gathered actors involved in the mitigation of post-wildfire hydrology and community preparedness and resilience. We gathered input on civic priorities, needs, and risk perception; guidance for the project’s design to enhance the existing hazard forecasts; and identified constraints shaping the actual implementation with civic and federal partners. The virtual workshop was hosted by the University of Oklahoma on April 8, 2021 and brought together more than 50 stakeholders from Colorado representing all actors involved in the mitigation of post-wildfire hydrology and in communities’ preparedness and resilience: leaders in emergency management (five different counties were represented); state agencies (e.g., Colorado Water Conservation Board, Colorado Division of Homeland Security &amp; Emergency Management, Colorado Department of Transportation); government agencies in research, training, and operations including forecasters (e.g., NWS, USGS, USFS, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers); nongovernmental organizations (e.g., Middle Colorado Watershed Council, Coalition for the Upper South Platte, Silver Jackets); and academia (OU, Colorado State University), for an energetic discussion on the challenges and potential opportunities to address flash flooding, severe erosion, and debris flows that often follow wildfires.  To build a foundation for the workshop participants on the fundamental challenges, terminology, and potential solutions relevant to post-wildfire hydrology, a primer on the various societal, scientific, and forecasting challenges was provided through an initial "Lightning Round" of invited speakers highlighting local communities’, EMs’, and agencies’ perspectives. It was complemented by an overview of NWS operations and challenges in Colorado, and an OU/NSSL presentation on past experiences with mobile radar field deployments. After the Lightning Round, workshop participants were organized into four distinct "Break-Out Sessions" (BOS) for in-depth discussions focused on key questions regarding e.g., communities’ needs and risk perceptions, impact of local observations on Emergency Managers’ decision-making processes and NWS operations, and sustainability of the hydrometeorological mobile observatory. A final wrap-up session brought together all workshop participants for brief reports from the BOS moderators and general discussion with the entire group. The workshop discussions led to several insightful conclusions that guided the project’s direction, while clarifying the background and context, and highlighted constraints that shaped the Stage 2 proposal.   Other outcomes include:  Press release: University of Oklahoma scientists team up with the Colorado Water Conservation Board to meet a critical coordination need from local communities, state, and federal government agencies to mitigate the risk of hydrologic hazards following wildfires in the Intermountain West. A unique mobile observatory with real-time observations will enable more effective community responses.  Link to abstract on nsf.gov:          https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2044056&amp;HistoricalAwards=false Social media: https://twitter.com/NSFCIVIC/status/1415059534536527876 1-Page Project Overview tailored to a broad and diverse audience including community stakeholders and beneficiaries:   https://drive.google.com/file/d/1MRNyR2at_3ooRMfP2SMcebZewOdmHiT6/view  Project Video: https://vimeo.com/569906247 Team Interview 1: https://vimeo.com/577332306 Team Interview 2: https://vimeo.com/577332508   A mentoring plan was designed following recommendations from the National Postdoctoral Association (NPA) and the National Academies of Sciences and Engineering and the Institute of Medicine 2000 report on "Enhancing the Postdoctoral Experience for Scientists and Engineers". The workshop, the MetroLab activities, and the writing of the Stage 2 proposal provided unique learning and networking opportunities for the Postdoctoral Rearcher and students who were involved in its organization.  Finally, this project provided opportunities for three early career faculty members (Dr. Kirstetter, Dee, and Reedy) to strengthen their research and education portfolios.           Last Modified: 11/01/2022       Submitted by: Pierre Kirstetter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
