<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track A: Jitney+: Redesign of a Legacy Mobility Service for Lower-income Communities in the Post-COVID Digital Age]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49938.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49938</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Low income communities in urban environments chronically struggle with access to mobility and the correlated low quality of life metrics. In principle, on-demand ride-sharing services can address these issues by creating an efficient, real-time market—matching drivers with requests. However, the reality for these communities is far different, as the tendency in these services, primarily run by external business owners, is to avoid pickups in low income communities due to safety perception, and lack of trust among users to name a few.  This project focuses on ways to empower the residents within these communities to offer connected mobility solution, and investigate their specific needs and operational constraints that are not currently understood enough. The overarching objective of this work is to create an effective collaboration platform for community partners to communicate their mobility challenges and opportunities with researchers (from engineering, social sciences and computer science), industry partners and policy makers, and to steer these engagements towards a concrete plan for a one-year multi-sided pilot project on customized peer-to-peer mobility solutions for low income communities. The holistic nature of this work includes studies on the societal aspects of connected mobility, and how coherent sociotechnical solutions can be created and how their success can be measured by accompanying social studies. If successful, this planning work and its following pilot project will enable transformation in the mobility of many low income communities in the country, and contribute to a more equitable, more efficient, and eventually more prosperous nation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To overcome the mobility challenges in low-come communities, an empowering approach to on-demand services rooted in these communities is needed. To this end, this project creates a cyberinfrastructure that help the capital and labor arise from within these low-income communities, and mobility demands and resources are linked in a way that is compatible with community resources and needs. In particular, this project will plan an innovative community-focused ride-sharing service—Jitney+. This service effectively connects the community social graph with the resources graph, and the location graph, and addresses (1) the issue of trust among the drivers and passengers, (2) the digital divide and (3) safety concerns related the location and time of access and also to COVID-19 infection. This is done by facilitating effective collaboration among community partners, university researchers, industry partners, and city officials, with the focus on communities in the south side of Chicago and in Champaign County in Illinois. This project is supported by the CIVIC Innovation Challenge program Track A - Communities and Mobility: Offering Better Mobility Options to Solve the Spatial Mismatch Between Housing Affordability and Jobs through a collaboration between NSF and the Department of Energy Vehicle Transportation Office.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044055</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jane</FirstName>
<LastName>Macfarlane</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jane F Macfarlane</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Janemacfarlane@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810233</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Farnoush</FirstName>
<LastName>Banaei-Kashani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Farnoush Banaei-Kashani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[farnoush.banaei-kashani@ucdenver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000564682</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hari</FirstName>
<LastName>Sundaram</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hari Sundaram</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hs1@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000706278</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Garthe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel Garthe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rcgarthe@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hadi</FirstName>
<LastName>Meidani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hadi Meidani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[meidani@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000693706</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 S WRIGHT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana,</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49938</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Accessible mobility and the availability of&nbsp;work are central&nbsp;elements to a vibrant&nbsp;and inclusive civic&nbsp;society. Over the past decade, innovative ride-sharing solutions including Uber and Lyft have transformed car-ride services in a broad range of contexts. Despite this, low-income residents are largely excluded&nbsp;from such services either because ride-sharing providers own the cars and can opt to reject a ride, or because factors of race and perceptions of neighborhood safety can impact decisions on where to offer&nbsp;services. When&nbsp;mobility-to-work (MTW) programs are concerned, our surveys from a low-income community in Central Illinois showed that poverty is not a monolithic experience and that there are varied factors that can compound an individual's capacity to access&nbsp;and sustain&nbsp;employment. As a result, in this project we worked on an initial design and proposed activities for a community-run mobility service, noting&nbsp;interdependent relationship of (1) economic self-sufficiency, (2) mobility, and (3) social networking capacity and trust.&nbsp;The designed service is an integration of (1) a messaging system for low-income communities, previously developed by a member of the research team, and (2) Mobility Matching algorithms. The integrated Social Graph-Mobility Matching responds to the mobility needs by integrating network&nbsp;properties,&nbsp;notions&nbsp;of&nbsp;trust&nbsp;and&nbsp;status.&nbsp;The&nbsp;system&nbsp;fortifies&nbsp;a&nbsp;sense&nbsp;of&nbsp;social&nbsp;trust&nbsp;and cooperation necessary for wider practices of mutual aid to develop while allowing residents to identify and address under-met needs.</p> <p>One of the focus of our team in this planning period was on creating a baseline assessment of the range of compounding factors that can significantly debilitate a sense of independence, trust and security among low-income residents. This included such factors as access to affordable transportation as well as child care, trust in neighbors, and community safety. In March, we coordinated planning sessions with our community partners to design a multi-modal outreach plan with online options as well as community-centered activities that would reach low-income population. To overcome past experiences of low-response surveys (even with $25 payments for responses), we designed several lunch and dinner tabling session in 5 distinct housing sites (i.e. both high-rise buildings and sites with distributed individual units). We also kept online survey portals open to participants. Below are key findings.</p> <p>Results from the planning grant (PG) illustrated that poverty is not a monolithic experience for HACC and CT residents. Across the 111 participants who were surveyed, residents showed varying levels of mobility needs and liabilities, perceptions of their community, and community trust. First, the PG highlighted that residents&nbsp;of&nbsp;HACC and CT have a need for&nbsp;more reliable transportation.&nbsp;About&nbsp;1 in 5 residents did not&nbsp;feel they had reliable transportation in a normal week; also, about 1 in 4 residents felt that there are&nbsp;certain areas or regions in the community that are difficult to get to because of lack of transportation. Although 31.6% would not generally take a ride from a neighbor, 48.4% said they would for a low fee or cost, 12.6% for no fee, 3.2% for a guarantee they would return the favor, and 4.2% for some other compensation. Second, residents also indicated that their employment has been impacted by mobility constraints. For example, 17.8% have quit or lost a job because they did not have reliable transportation&nbsp;to get to work. 25.5% have been prevented from applying for/taking a job because of arranging transportation for work. Finally, only 24.8% of residents agreed that people in their neighborhood can be trusted. 60.9% of residents worry about safety, crime, or violence in their neighborhood, and 65.1% of residents agree that safety, crime, and violence impact their choices about transportation and how they choose to travel. At the conclusion of the project, the team prepared and submitted a Stage 2 proposal for a one-year pilot study on evaluating the effectiveness and improvement of the proposed mobility service.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Hadi&nbsp;Meidani</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Accessible mobility and the availability of work are central elements to a vibrant and inclusive civic society. Over the past decade, innovative ride-sharing solutions including Uber and Lyft have transformed car-ride services in a broad range of contexts. Despite this, low-income residents are largely excluded from such services either because ride-sharing providers own the cars and can opt to reject a ride, or because factors of race and perceptions of neighborhood safety can impact decisions on where to offer services. When mobility-to-work (MTW) programs are concerned, our surveys from a low-income community in Central Illinois showed that poverty is not a monolithic experience and that there are varied factors that can compound an individual's capacity to access and sustain employment. As a result, in this project we worked on an initial design and proposed activities for a community-run mobility service, noting interdependent relationship of (1) economic self-sufficiency, (2) mobility, and (3) social networking capacity and trust. The designed service is an integration of (1) a messaging system for low-income communities, previously developed by a member of the research team, and (2) Mobility Matching algorithms. The integrated Social Graph-Mobility Matching responds to the mobility needs by integrating network properties, notions of trust and status. The system fortifies a sense of social trust and cooperation necessary for wider practices of mutual aid to develop while allowing residents to identify and address under-met needs.  One of the focus of our team in this planning period was on creating a baseline assessment of the range of compounding factors that can significantly debilitate a sense of independence, trust and security among low-income residents. This included such factors as access to affordable transportation as well as child care, trust in neighbors, and community safety. In March, we coordinated planning sessions with our community partners to design a multi-modal outreach plan with online options as well as community-centered activities that would reach low-income population. To overcome past experiences of low-response surveys (even with $25 payments for responses), we designed several lunch and dinner tabling session in 5 distinct housing sites (i.e. both high-rise buildings and sites with distributed individual units). We also kept online survey portals open to participants. Below are key findings.  Results from the planning grant (PG) illustrated that poverty is not a monolithic experience for HACC and CT residents. Across the 111 participants who were surveyed, residents showed varying levels of mobility needs and liabilities, perceptions of their community, and community trust. First, the PG highlighted that residents of HACC and CT have a need for more reliable transportation. About 1 in 5 residents did not feel they had reliable transportation in a normal week; also, about 1 in 4 residents felt that there are certain areas or regions in the community that are difficult to get to because of lack of transportation. Although 31.6% would not generally take a ride from a neighbor, 48.4% said they would for a low fee or cost, 12.6% for no fee, 3.2% for a guarantee they would return the favor, and 4.2% for some other compensation. Second, residents also indicated that their employment has been impacted by mobility constraints. For example, 17.8% have quit or lost a job because they did not have reliable transportation to get to work. 25.5% have been prevented from applying for/taking a job because of arranging transportation for work. Finally, only 24.8% of residents agreed that people in their neighborhood can be trusted. 60.9% of residents worry about safety, crime, or violence in their neighborhood, and 65.1% of residents agree that safety, crime, and violence impact their choices about transportation and how they choose to travel. At the conclusion of the project, the team prepared and submitted a Stage 2 proposal for a one-year pilot study on evaluating the effectiveness and improvement of the proposed mobility service.       Last Modified: 04/04/2023       Submitted by: Hadi Meidani]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
