<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PFT-TT: Accessible Metal 3D Printing Using Directed Acoustic Energy Direct-write]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249725.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29282</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Partnerships for Innovation - Technology Translation (PFI-TT) project is the seamless and well-informed integration and transition of tasks in the project, ranging from acquiring and applying targeted scientific knowledge, to process development, and market needs-directed technology development roadmap. The project will culminate not only in scientific knowledge to enable advancement of a new metal 3D printing technique into a feasible technology, but it will also identify the context and market in which this new technology can maximize impact. The project will deliver a clear roadmap for commercialization of a new, massively-accessible, metal 3D printing technology. Furthermore, the highly interactive research and development environment in the project challenges how students understand and approach engineering problems. Problems are solved not only from the perspective of the scientific community, but from an engineering feasibility, cost viability, and long-term marketability, as well as the customer experience point of views.  The project provides students with leadership development in innovation and entrepreneurship in STEM. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project allows students involved in this program to obtain scientific knowledge specifically related to the how acoustic energy changes the crystalline lattice defect dynamics under oscillatory shear strain and how defects interact with one another.  This knowledge fills the gap in the current literature on how acoustic energy alters dislocation dynamics and interaction across multiple interfaces.  The acoustic energy and voxel compression are used to construct a metal 3D printing process via the direct write of solid metal wires.   Through experimentation, analytical and computation modeling, the knowledge acquired here not only allows students to deepen their understanding of material mechanics and process physics, but it also allows them to apply the knowledge to the design and development of a new manufacturing process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by Partnerships for Innovation (PFI) and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044352</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keng</FirstName>
<LastName>Hsu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keng Hsu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[keng.h.hsu@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000664522</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>LOUISVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>402081838</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5028523788</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2301 S 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E1KJM4T54MK6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF LOUISVILLE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Louisville]]></Name>
<CityName>Louisville</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>402920001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2301 S 3rd Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~29280</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Pa4"><strong>Project outcome in training and professional development:</strong></p> <p class="Pa4">This project provided research assistantship support for 1 graduate student in year 1. During the one-year period the student obtained the following training and development.</p> <ul> <li>Knowledge in solid mechanics, hot deformation, continuous mechanics, and ultrasonics;</li> <li>Training in operation of surface characterization tools and technologies:  <ul> <li>Metallography</li> <li>Scanning Electron Microscopy</li> <li>Electron Back-Scattered Diffraction analysis </li> </ul> </li> <li>Obtained skills of collection, analysis, and presentation of technical data and information;</li> </ul> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa4"><strong>Dissemination of project results:</strong></p> <p class="Default">The results were presented at the NAMRC conference and a conference paper was submitted and published. Specifically:</p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Journal paper:</strong></p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;">A. Deshpande, S. D. Nath, E. Fernandez, S. Atre, <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Keng Hsu</span>, ?Effect of Post Processing Heat Treatment Routes on Microstructure and Mechanical Property Evolution of Haynes 282 Ni-Based Superalloy Fabricated with Selective Laser Melting (SLM)?, <em>Metals</em>, 10(5), 629, 2020.</p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Conference Papers and Presentations:</strong></p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;">Presentation: In-process Microstructure Tuning in Solid-State Ambient Condition Metal Direct Manufacturing, NAMRC 2020.</p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Technologies or Techniques:</strong></p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;">Directed Acoustic Energy Deposition</p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa4" style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Provisional Patents:</strong></p> <ol style="padding-left: 30px;"> <li>&nbsp;<ol> <li>INTERMITTENT MATERIAL-TOOL INTERACTION CONTROL ENABLING&nbsp;CONTINUOUS DEPOSITION OF SOLID METAL VOXELS USING LOCAL HIGHFREQUENCY, SMALL-DISPLACEMENT OSCILLATORY STRAIN ENERGY, 63284735</li> <li>TOOL-MATERIAL ENERGY TRANSFER CONTROL IN HIGH-FREQUENCY, OSCILLATORY STRAIN-BASED MATERIAL DEPOSITION AND JOINING PROCESS FOR CONTROL, 63289999</li> </ol></li> </ol> <p><strong>Impacts:</strong></p> <p>Through the project, the team advanced the knowledge in feasibility of a new metal additive manufacturing process.&nbsp; Knowledge generated through this project also have impact on other discpline in that it can advance further development in ultrasound-assisted metal forming processes to increase productivity and quality control.&nbsp; In terms of institutional resources,&nbsp;this project allows the team to construct the first system that allows for simultaneous application of transverse-mode ultrasound vibration and application of compression while in-situ force and displacement feedback.&nbsp; This apparatus can be open up for use to other faculty and researchers in the university as a resources for investigation of mechanics of material deformation under assistance of acoustic energy.&nbsp; This project also generated significant impact in technology transfer in that it produced two additional provisional patent applications that further protects the core technology.&nbsp; It also executed the partnership between the university and project consultant company and established a process and trust between the two organizations for further collaboration in their partnership.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>FInally this project generated additional impact on society&nbsp;in that this project allowed close collaboration of researchers and students. It allowed all team members on the project to work closely and collaboratively with experts in the collaborator in the industry. This enhances the educational experiences of the students and researchers on the project and provided a view for other researchers of a successful model of academia-industry collaboration.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Keng&nbsp;Hsu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044352/2044352_10716328_1657567813614_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044352/2044352_10716328_1657567813614_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Predictive model for process mechanics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2044352/2044352_10716328_1657567813614_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Predictive model for process mechanics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">the developed model precise predicted the mechanicals of feedstock during 3D printing. It allows for control of material property of as-printed products</div> <div class="imageCredit">Keng Hsu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Keng&nbsp;Hsu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Predictive model for process mechanics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Project outcome in training and professional development: This project provided research assistantship support for 1 graduate student in year 1. During the one-year period the student obtained the following training and development.  Knowledge in solid mechanics, hot deformation, continuous mechanics, and ultrasonics; Training in operation of surface characterization tools and technologies:   Metallography Scanning Electron Microscopy Electron Back-Scattered Diffraction analysis    Obtained skills of collection, analysis, and presentation of technical data and information;    Dissemination of project results: The results were presented at the NAMRC conference and a conference paper was submitted and published. Specifically: Journal paper: A. Deshpande, S. D. Nath, E. Fernandez, S. Atre, Keng Hsu, ?Effect of Post Processing Heat Treatment Routes on Microstructure and Mechanical Property Evolution of Haynes 282 Ni-Based Superalloy Fabricated with Selective Laser Melting (SLM)?, Metals, 10(5), 629, 2020.   Conference Papers and Presentations: Presentation: In-process Microstructure Tuning in Solid-State Ambient Condition Metal Direct Manufacturing, NAMRC 2020.   Technologies or Techniques: Directed Acoustic Energy Deposition   Provisional Patents:    INTERMITTENT MATERIAL-TOOL INTERACTION CONTROL ENABLING CONTINUOUS DEPOSITION OF SOLID METAL VOXELS USING LOCAL HIGHFREQUENCY, SMALL-DISPLACEMENT OSCILLATORY STRAIN ENERGY, 63284735 TOOL-MATERIAL ENERGY TRANSFER CONTROL IN HIGH-FREQUENCY, OSCILLATORY STRAIN-BASED MATERIAL DEPOSITION AND JOINING PROCESS FOR CONTROL, 63289999    Impacts:  Through the project, the team advanced the knowledge in feasibility of a new metal additive manufacturing process.  Knowledge generated through this project also have impact on other discpline in that it can advance further development in ultrasound-assisted metal forming processes to increase productivity and quality control.  In terms of institutional resources, this project allows the team to construct the first system that allows for simultaneous application of transverse-mode ultrasound vibration and application of compression while in-situ force and displacement feedback.  This apparatus can be open up for use to other faculty and researchers in the university as a resources for investigation of mechanics of material deformation under assistance of acoustic energy.  This project also generated significant impact in technology transfer in that it produced two additional provisional patent applications that further protects the core technology.  It also executed the partnership between the university and project consultant company and established a process and trust between the two organizations for further collaboration in their partnership.    FInally this project generated additional impact on society in that this project allowed close collaboration of researchers and students. It allowed all team members on the project to work closely and collaboratively with experts in the collaborator in the industry. This enhances the educational experiences of the students and researchers on the project and provided a view for other researchers of a successful model of academia-industry collaboration.               Last Modified: 07/11/2022       Submitted by: Keng Hsu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
