<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Strengthening Resilience of Ojibwe Nations across Generations (STRONG): Sovereignty, Food, Water, and Cultural (in)Security]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michal Ziv-El</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mzivel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924926</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Practicing resilience has always been vital to Ojibwe lifeways. Grounded in the importance of place, Ojibwe worldviews recognize the hierarchically dependent Four Orders (physical, plant, animal, human) and the importance of cultural security for maintaining these relationships. When any of these orders is threatened, resilience and sustainability are also threatened. Environmentally destructive development and climate change, alongside cultural decline, for example, impact communities’ abilities to respond to climate change and natural disasters. This project aims to address the resilience challenges faced by Indigenous communities by bringing together scientific and traditional ecological knowledge and utilizing data science and advanced sensing technologies to strengthen data sovereignty, resource sustainability, and climate resilience in Ojibwe communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding Indigenous resilience is a complex endeavor. Most resilience science generally develops in isolation from the communities experiencing climate change, natural disasters, and extreme weather events and focuses primarily on cities, large-scale food and energy production, water resources, and industrial systems. Integrating scientific and traditional ecological knowledge to strengthen resilience requires collaborative, sovereignty-affirming, tribally-driven research to address many fundamental questions: (1) How can transdisciplinary research best foster resilience in the face of long-term declines in environmental quality and short-term extreme events?; (2) How can scientific and traditional ecological knowledge be synergized to improve resilience in Indigenous communities?; (3) What mechanisms, tools, and technologies best support collection and synthesis of scientific and traditional ecological knowledge?; and, (4) What indicators can most effectively translate synthesized knowledge into improved resilience capabilities in Indigenous communities? This planning project brings together a core group of scientists in engineering, natural resource management, computer science, and social sciences with community leaders and knowledge holders to identify culturally relevant indicators for monitoring resilience and co-produce decision-support tools to strengthen community resilience. This will be achieved by: (1) developing a fundamental and respectful understanding of traditional ecological knowledge, systems, and co-production; (2) developing understanding of the threats to Ojibwe resilience; (3) establishing new methodologies incorporating the relationships of the Ojibwe Four Orders with state-of-the-art environmental sensing and data science to help identify and evaluate resilience solutions; and, (4) developing a framework to identify and analyze pathways to adaptation and/or increased resilience for Ojibwe nations/ The proposed plan will offer a resilience framework to develop monitoring, prediction, and response systems and decision-making tools that can be extended to other Native Nations and communities to advance cultural, food, and water security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/15/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044053</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Packman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Packman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[a-packman@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000395101</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Marion Suiseeya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly Marion Suiseeya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kimberly.suiseeya@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000616319</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Josiah</FirstName>
<LastName>Hester</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Josiah D Hester</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[josiah@gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000753638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
<LastName>Loew</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patricia A Loew</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[patricia.loew@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilbert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan H Gilbert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jgilbert@glifwc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>602080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>633 CLARK STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EXZVPWZBLUE8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602012919</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2205 Tech Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This planning grant supported relationship building and strengthening between Northwestern University researchers, the Great Lakes Indian Fish and Wildlife Commission (GLIFWC), and Native Nation members of GLIFWC. Through relationship building, we built the foundation necessary for co-developing multiple, successful grant proposals that advance tribally driven research to meet the complex and evolving needs of Native Nations in the Western Great Lakes and strengthen Ojibwe Nations&rsquo; scientific capacities to support advances in resilience to environmental change. The result is a comprehensive research plan for knowledge co-production that supports developing useful and useable data-drive approaches to disaster anticipation and mitigation.</p> <p>The project established a new approach to integrating Indigenous knowledge, scientific knowledge, and multi-modal data from advanced sensing technologies. This traditional knowledge framework guides the development of research designs to empirically capture both Indigenous knowledge and scientific knowledge that can help decision-makers and resource managers understand how environmental change, including climate change, impacts the function and health of manoomin, or wild rice, and its interdependent ecosystems &ndash; the health of which constitutes key indicators of resilience for Ojibwe communities.</p> <p>To achieve these goals, the STRONG team held three listening sessions, co-developed two grant proposals, deployed a Sage node and other environmental sensors to begin collecting pilot data, created a new data set of more than 400 governance institutions that impact tribal resilience, cultivated relationships with tribal colleges, and identified new opportunities for collaboration. Team members have presented preliminary work from the planning grant to multiple audiences, including academic conferences, tribal government agencies, tribal council, and community groups. In addition to the relationship-building that was the primary focus of the planning grant, the project also contributed to advances in computer science and engineering by motivating and informing nascent efforts in differential privacy, data sovereignty, and ultra-low-power sensing technologies. By centering Indigenous data governance and capacity needs, these advancements contribute to expanding the reach and impact of advanced data science in Native Nations.</p> <p>Through its dedicated attention to tribally driven research and commitments to Indigenous data sovereignty, this work will benefit current and future projects by expanding cyberinfrastructure to Native Nations, creating new pathways for integrating Indigenous knowledge and scientific knowledge to inform convergent research, and supporting Ojibwe Nations in addressing core community needs and research priorities that can help strengthen their cultural, food, and water security.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Kimberly&nbsp;Marion Suiseeya</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2044053/2044053_10713419_1682867855508_tk_2Artboard3(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2044053/2044053_10713419_1682867855508_tk_2Artboard3(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Traditional Knowledge Framework"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2044053/2044053_10713419_1682867855508_tk_2Artboard3(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Traditional Knowledge Framework"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This traditional knowledge framework guides the development of research designs to empirically capture both Indigenous knowledge and scientific knowledge that can help decision-makers and resource managers understand how environmental change, including climate change, impacts wild rice.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Marion Suiseeya</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;Marion Suiseeya</div> <div class="imageTitle">Traditional Knowledge Framework</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2044053/2044053_10713419_1682867577928_MarionSuiseeya_GraphicAbstract--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2044053/2044053_10713419_1682867577928_MarionSuiseeya_GraphicAbstract--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STRONG Graphic Abstract"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2044053/2044053_10713419_1682867577928_MarionSuiseeya_GraphicAbstract--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STRONG Graphic Abstract"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Summary of the proposed research plan to advance Ojibwe resilience.</div> <div class="imageCredit">K. Marion Suiseeya</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;Marion Suiseeya</div> <div class="imageTitle">STRONG Graphic Abstract</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This planning grant supported relationship building and strengthening between Northwestern University researchers, the Great Lakes Indian Fish and Wildlife Commission (GLIFWC), and Native Nation members of GLIFWC. Through relationship building, we built the foundation necessary for co-developing multiple, successful grant proposals that advance tribally driven research to meet the complex and evolving needs of Native Nations in the Western Great Lakes and strengthen Ojibwe Nations’ scientific capacities to support advances in resilience to environmental change. The result is a comprehensive research plan for knowledge co-production that supports developing useful and useable data-drive approaches to disaster anticipation and mitigation.  The project established a new approach to integrating Indigenous knowledge, scientific knowledge, and multi-modal data from advanced sensing technologies. This traditional knowledge framework guides the development of research designs to empirically capture both Indigenous knowledge and scientific knowledge that can help decision-makers and resource managers understand how environmental change, including climate change, impacts the function and health of manoomin, or wild rice, and its interdependent ecosystems &ndash; the health of which constitutes key indicators of resilience for Ojibwe communities.  To achieve these goals, the STRONG team held three listening sessions, co-developed two grant proposals, deployed a Sage node and other environmental sensors to begin collecting pilot data, created a new data set of more than 400 governance institutions that impact tribal resilience, cultivated relationships with tribal colleges, and identified new opportunities for collaboration. Team members have presented preliminary work from the planning grant to multiple audiences, including academic conferences, tribal government agencies, tribal council, and community groups. In addition to the relationship-building that was the primary focus of the planning grant, the project also contributed to advances in computer science and engineering by motivating and informing nascent efforts in differential privacy, data sovereignty, and ultra-low-power sensing technologies. By centering Indigenous data governance and capacity needs, these advancements contribute to expanding the reach and impact of advanced data science in Native Nations.  Through its dedicated attention to tribally driven research and commitments to Indigenous data sovereignty, this work will benefit current and future projects by expanding cyberinfrastructure to Native Nations, creating new pathways for integrating Indigenous knowledge and scientific knowledge to inform convergent research, and supporting Ojibwe Nations in addressing core community needs and research priorities that can help strengthen their cultural, food, and water security.       Last Modified: 04/30/2023       Submitted by: Kimberly Marion Suiseeya]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
