<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Regulation of Hyperinflammation and Cell Survival Under Hypoxia with NELL1/NV1: A Therapy for Severe Lung Tissue Damage in Viral Infections (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>242342.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>242342</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is the development of a first-in-class therapeutic that minimizes lung damage and promotes tissue healing under the adverse environment of viral infection. The current standard of care for COVID-19 patients battling SARS-CoV-2 infection is limited to supportive care, long hospitalization, and re-purposed anti-inflammatory or anti-viral drugs. Many survivors suffer long-term lung scarring that reduces respiratory function. There remains a need for effective therapeutics that prevent or reduce virus-induced lung damage and/or promote tissue healing. Recombinant human NELL1 protein has an excellent safety profile in healing tissue injuries and a virus-agnostic mode of action. NELL1 is strongly differentiated from COVID-19 therapeutics in clinical development because it can be manufactured large-scale, cost-effectively, and has broad utility in treating future viral outbreaks independent of causative virus, strain, or variant. The proposed studies will rapidly advance NELL1 towards preclinical and clinical studies using COVID-19 expedited path(s). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will demonstrate the scientific and technical feasibility of advancing NELL1 as a protein therapeutic for the treatment of viral-based respiratory damage, including damage caused by SARS-CoV-2. The first technical objective is to demonstrate NELL1 potential in promoting cell survival under hypoxic conditions and reducing inflammation in epithelial cell cultures. After NELL1 treatment and exposure to hypoxic growth conditions, the survival of bronchial epithelial cells and accumulation of reactive oxygen species will be monitored relative to no treatment controls. Similarly, inflammation will be induced in primary epithelial cells treated with NELL1 and inflammatory marker abundance and cell survival will be compared to no treatment control cells. Success is demonstrated by ≥30% cell survival under each condition and a concordant reduction in reactive oxygen species and markers of inflammation in cells treated with NELL1. The second technical objective is to demonstrate in vivo efficacy of NELL1 in modulating SARS-Co-V-2 induced cytokine storm. These studies will be performed in a validated hACE2 transgenic mouse model and it is expected that the abundance of at least three cytokines will be reduced by ≥30% in treated animals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2045393</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cymbeline</FirstName>
<LastName>Culiat</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cymbeline Culiat</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cymbeline@nell-one.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834507</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NELLONE THERAPEUTICS, INC.</Name>
<CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>379312052</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8653007161</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11020 SOLWAY SCHOOL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 101]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>X42MJDLH51V5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NELLONE THERAPEUTICS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>R757Q29DFNW5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NELLONE THERAPEUTICS, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379312052</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11020 SOLWAY SCHOOL RD STE 101]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~242342</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The endogenous NELL1 protein is most abundant and active during fetal development, during which it regulates the growth and maturation of cells of the digestive and respiratory systems. Previous work suggested that a NELL1 drug might be helpful in treating lung tissues damaged by COVID-19 or other viruses, but it had not tested in any cell or tissue models of respiratory damage.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit &mdash; Our Phase I studies filled this gap, and demonstrated the potential of an NV1 (our proprietary shorter version of NELL1 and therapeutic candidate) drug to&nbsp;minimize lung damage and promote lung tissue regeneration&nbsp;under the adverse environment of viral infection. Using a variety of cell-based models and mouse studies we demonstrated that:&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>NV1 is active in lung cells under hyperinflammation and starved for oxygen, at the same effective dose as observed in non-respiratory tissues.&nbsp;</li> <li>NV1 is a modulator of the immune response that reduces the impact of several potent, pro-inflammatory molecules that drive severe lung damage in COVID-19 and other viral infections.&nbsp;</li> <li>NV1 boosts the secretion of molecules that are needed in high amounts to neutralize and clear viruses.&nbsp;</li> <li>NV1 upregulates molecules that are associated with tissue regeneration to promote healing.&nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>Broader Impact &mdash; Collectively, our Phase I results establish the therapeutic candidacy of NV1 in lungs that are damaged by hyperinflammation and low oxygen,&nbsp;the two conditions that make tissue healing very difficult and place patients at greatest risk for COVID-19 mortality and/or long-term disability (<em>i.e.,</em>&nbsp;long COVID or Post-acute Sequelae of COVID-19/PASC).&nbsp;NV1 addresses an unmet need in treating lung tissue damage resulting in life-threatening respiratory distress (Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome or ARDS). Despite COVID-19 vaccine availability and anti-viral therapeutics, severe lung tissue damage persists in many survivors and remains a life-threatening risk for many patients. These health risks are considerable in U.S. patients who are immune compromised, do not have easy access to medical resources, or otherwise cannot &ndash; or will not &ndash; get immunized. The global needs and disparities pose an even more significant demand for an NV1 therapeutic.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/04/2022<br>      Modified by: Cymbeline&nbsp;Culiat</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The endogenous NELL1 protein is most abundant and active during fetal development, during which it regulates the growth and maturation of cells of the digestive and respiratory systems. Previous work suggested that a NELL1 drug might be helpful in treating lung tissues damaged by COVID-19 or other viruses, but it had not tested in any cell or tissue models of respiratory damage.   Intellectual Merit &mdash; Our Phase I studies filled this gap, and demonstrated the potential of an NV1 (our proprietary shorter version of NELL1 and therapeutic candidate) drug to minimize lung damage and promote lung tissue regeneration under the adverse environment of viral infection. Using a variety of cell-based models and mouse studies we demonstrated that:   NV1 is active in lung cells under hyperinflammation and starved for oxygen, at the same effective dose as observed in non-respiratory tissues.  NV1 is a modulator of the immune response that reduces the impact of several potent, pro-inflammatory molecules that drive severe lung damage in COVID-19 and other viral infections.  NV1 boosts the secretion of molecules that are needed in high amounts to neutralize and clear viruses.  NV1 upregulates molecules that are associated with tissue regeneration to promote healing.    Broader Impact &mdash; Collectively, our Phase I results establish the therapeutic candidacy of NV1 in lungs that are damaged by hyperinflammation and low oxygen, the two conditions that make tissue healing very difficult and place patients at greatest risk for COVID-19 mortality and/or long-term disability (i.e., long COVID or Post-acute Sequelae of COVID-19/PASC). NV1 addresses an unmet need in treating lung tissue damage resulting in life-threatening respiratory distress (Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome or ARDS). Despite COVID-19 vaccine availability and anti-viral therapeutics, severe lung tissue damage persists in many survivors and remains a life-threatening risk for many patients. These health risks are considerable in U.S. patients who are immune compromised, do not have easy access to medical resources, or otherwise cannot &ndash; or will not &ndash; get immunized. The global needs and disparities pose an even more significant demand for an NV1 therapeutic.        Last Modified: 11/04/2022       Submitted by: Cymbeline Culiat]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
