<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Asthenospheric melting and melt-induced evolution of the lithosphere beneath the Colorado Plateau and the Basin and Range from a seismic characterization of mantle layering]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>83067.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>83067</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Hearn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ehearn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925338</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Partial melting in the Earth's upper mantle plays a key role in controlling surface volcanism. It also impacts the evolution of tectonic plates and the deformation of the hot mantle underneath, called the asthenosphere. In recent years, the continental United States has been blanketed by EarthScope's Transportable Array, a program that deployed thousands of seismic instruments. The collected data provide unprecedented new constraints on the structure of the uppermost mantle, informing its dynamics and history of formation and alteration. Here, the researchers analyze the data from the Colorado Plateau, an area with ancient Proterozoic crust. This area has remained relatively undeformed through multiple compression episodes and subsequent extension of the surrounding Basin and Range. The rise of the Plateau from near sea level to its current elevation is not well understood. The volcanism of the Basin and Range is now actively encroaching on the ancient Plateau.  By combining seismology and thermodynamic modeling, the team maps out the partial melt and alteration of the uppermost mantle.  This project brings new light on the past evolution and present state of an important region of the southwestern United States. It also supports an early-career female scientist, the principal investigator, and provides training to an undergraduate student in the field of seismology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team investigates the Colorado Plateau region, where disparate tectonic settings are juxtaposed within a small geographical area. The researchers use surface-wave dispersion data and information derived from S-to-P receiver functions about sharp velocity gradients in the upper mantle. They calculate accurate seismic-velocity models which employ a geologically reasonable layered framework. The models build on the Principal Investigator's previous work with receiver functions, which provides the layered lithosphere-asthenosphere framework in which to invert the dispersion data. The team combine seismic analysis with thermodynamic modeling in a self-consistent way to estimate regional velocity structures. The modeling accounts for the composition, pressure and temperature, as well as melt fraction at depth. These estimates are constrained by compositional and temperature data from the abundant volcanism and xenoliths in the area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2045264</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaherty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James B Gaherty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[james.gaherty@nau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000086733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northern Arizona University</Name>
<CityName>FLAGSTAFF</CityName>
<ZipCode>86011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9285230886</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S KNOLES DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[ROOM 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MXHAS3AKPRN1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHERN ARIZONA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northern Arizona University]]></Name>
<CityName>Flagstaff</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>860110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1395 South Knoles Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1031</Code>
<Text>STUDIES OF THE EARTH'S DEEP INTERIOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~83067</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The landscape of the inter-mountain western United States, spanning from the Sierra Nevada mountains in California to the high-plains regions of the Dakotas, Nebraska, Colorado, and New Mexico, has been constructed and modified by sequences of tectonic uplift and volcanic eruptions over the past 50 million years.&nbsp; This activity is driven from the mantle beneath the region, where the process of cold material sinking and hot material rising pushes on and deforms the overriding crust, and partial melting of the mantle in the hot regions produces the magma feeding volcanoes.&nbsp; In the shallow mantle just below the crust, seismic imaging suggests that the western US is one of the hottest regions of the planet, and the tectonic deformation and volcanism driven by mantle flow in the region remain active today.&nbsp;</p> <p>One of the key factors that controls the deformation and volcanism -- where, when, and how it occurs -- is the strength of the rocks in the mantle.&nbsp; This strength is very sensitive to temperature, with hot rocks being weak and easy to deform, and cold rocks being stronger and stiffer. Strength is also sensitive to whether the rocks are hot enough to melt, as the introduction of even tiny fractions of molten rock (partial melt) can dramatically weaken an otherwise-solid rock.&nbsp; The production and accumulation of partial melt in the mantle can then also lead to subsequent volcanism at the surface.&nbsp; Accurately characterizing the distribution of partial melt in the mantle is thus key to understanding past and present deformation and volcanism, but it is very difficult.&nbsp; Seismic imaging is the most common way to detect the presence of melt in the mantle, but the seismic evidence of melt is very difficult to distinguish from that of high temperature.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, we developed a new seismic-imaging algorithm designed to better characterize the seismic architecture of the upper mantle, with a specific goal of improving our understanding of the distribution of partial melt.&nbsp; The algorithm makes use of existing seismic observations from the western US that were collected using NSF's successful EarthScope Transportable Array.&nbsp; We combine observations that provide complementary seismic constraints: 1) direct wave speeds, which constrain absolute seismic velocity with the upper 300 km of the crust and mantle; and 2) estimates of the depth and magnitude in abrupt changes in velocity with depth, specifically a sharp increase associated with the crust-mantle boundary, and a deeper sharp decrease often associated with the base of rigid lithosphere overlying the weaker asthenosphere, where partial melt might accumulate.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; These observations provide independent constraints on the thermal structure of the mantle and associated partial melt, but combining them provides mutually consistent models for the western US that can be quantitatively evaluated for temperature and the presence of partial melt.</p> <p>Intellectual merit:&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The new seismic models demonstrate that the ensemble dataset can better constrain sharp minima in asthenosphere Vs than previous smooth seismic models for the western United States. The results place the sharp decrease in velocity at approximately 75 km (45 miles) beneath the Basin and Range province and 80 to 100 km (48-60 miles) beneath the interior of the Colorado Plateau and stable North America. The seismic velocities suggest that this decrease represents the lithosphere-asthenosphere boundary (LAB) both in the Basin and Range and Colorado Plateau provinces, while further east beneath the Wyoming craton and the Great Plains, the velocities suggest that the sharp drop is relatively cold and thus within the lithosphere. &nbsp;Compared to predictions of seismic velocity derived from experiments on mantle-like rocks, the observed velocities in the asthenosphere are too slow to be explained by temperature alone over a large swath of the region south and west of the Rocky Mountains (Basin and Range and Rio Grande rift of Nevada, Utah, Arizona, and New Mexico), and we confidently infer that partial melt must be present in the mantle in these regions.&nbsp; Consistent with this inference, nearly all volcanism less than 2.6 million-years old in the western US occurred where we infer the presence of mantle melt.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We have developed a new imaging algorithm for disparate seismic observations within a structured, geologically reasonable framework that will be useful for a variety of tectonic environments and regions.&nbsp; The estimate of partial melt distribution in the western US mantle provides an improved perspective on mantle strength, and an updated framework for interpreting past, present, and likely future volcanism across the region.&nbsp; The project provided support for two early-career Post-Doctoral scientists, who furthered their skills in seismic modeling and data-science algorithm development.&nbsp; One is now working professionally in the Data Science industry, while the other is utilizing these results in seeking jobs in academia.&nbsp; It has provided the PI new experience in high-performance computing, which he will use in future research and student training projects.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2022<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;B&nbsp;Gaherty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The landscape of the inter-mountain western United States, spanning from the Sierra Nevada mountains in California to the high-plains regions of the Dakotas, Nebraska, Colorado, and New Mexico, has been constructed and modified by sequences of tectonic uplift and volcanic eruptions over the past 50 million years.  This activity is driven from the mantle beneath the region, where the process of cold material sinking and hot material rising pushes on and deforms the overriding crust, and partial melting of the mantle in the hot regions produces the magma feeding volcanoes.  In the shallow mantle just below the crust, seismic imaging suggests that the western US is one of the hottest regions of the planet, and the tectonic deformation and volcanism driven by mantle flow in the region remain active today.   One of the key factors that controls the deformation and volcanism -- where, when, and how it occurs -- is the strength of the rocks in the mantle.  This strength is very sensitive to temperature, with hot rocks being weak and easy to deform, and cold rocks being stronger and stiffer. Strength is also sensitive to whether the rocks are hot enough to melt, as the introduction of even tiny fractions of molten rock (partial melt) can dramatically weaken an otherwise-solid rock.  The production and accumulation of partial melt in the mantle can then also lead to subsequent volcanism at the surface.  Accurately characterizing the distribution of partial melt in the mantle is thus key to understanding past and present deformation and volcanism, but it is very difficult.  Seismic imaging is the most common way to detect the presence of melt in the mantle, but the seismic evidence of melt is very difficult to distinguish from that of high temperature.       In this project, we developed a new seismic-imaging algorithm designed to better characterize the seismic architecture of the upper mantle, with a specific goal of improving our understanding of the distribution of partial melt.  The algorithm makes use of existing seismic observations from the western US that were collected using NSF's successful EarthScope Transportable Array.  We combine observations that provide complementary seismic constraints: 1) direct wave speeds, which constrain absolute seismic velocity with the upper 300 km of the crust and mantle; and 2) estimates of the depth and magnitude in abrupt changes in velocity with depth, specifically a sharp increase associated with the crust-mantle boundary, and a deeper sharp decrease often associated with the base of rigid lithosphere overlying the weaker asthenosphere, where partial melt might accumulate.    These observations provide independent constraints on the thermal structure of the mantle and associated partial melt, but combining them provides mutually consistent models for the western US that can be quantitatively evaluated for temperature and the presence of partial melt.  Intellectual merit:     The new seismic models demonstrate that the ensemble dataset can better constrain sharp minima in asthenosphere Vs than previous smooth seismic models for the western United States. The results place the sharp decrease in velocity at approximately 75 km (45 miles) beneath the Basin and Range province and 80 to 100 km (48-60 miles) beneath the interior of the Colorado Plateau and stable North America. The seismic velocities suggest that this decrease represents the lithosphere-asthenosphere boundary (LAB) both in the Basin and Range and Colorado Plateau provinces, while further east beneath the Wyoming craton and the Great Plains, the velocities suggest that the sharp drop is relatively cold and thus within the lithosphere.  Compared to predictions of seismic velocity derived from experiments on mantle-like rocks, the observed velocities in the asthenosphere are too slow to be explained by temperature alone over a large swath of the region south and west of the Rocky Mountains (Basin and Range and Rio Grande rift of Nevada, Utah, Arizona, and New Mexico), and we confidently infer that partial melt must be present in the mantle in these regions.  Consistent with this inference, nearly all volcanism less than 2.6 million-years old in the western US occurred where we infer the presence of mantle melt.  Broader Impacts:        We have developed a new imaging algorithm for disparate seismic observations within a structured, geologically reasonable framework that will be useful for a variety of tectonic environments and regions.  The estimate of partial melt distribution in the western US mantle provides an improved perspective on mantle strength, and an updated framework for interpreting past, present, and likely future volcanism across the region.  The project provided support for two early-career Post-Doctoral scientists, who furthered their skills in seismic modeling and data-science algorithm development.  One is now working professionally in the Data Science industry, while the other is utilizing these results in seeking jobs in academia.  It has provided the PI new experience in high-performance computing, which he will use in future research and student training projects.       Last Modified: 08/30/2022       Submitted by: James B Gaherty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
