<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Point-Of-Use Nano-Mosaic Filter Technology for Lithium]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is in the development of an efficient, rapid, and cost-effective point-of use technology to recover lithium from brine resources. Current brine operations are capital intensive and incur significant lead time (2 years) with low recovery (30%) for producing high-grade lithium. The proposed technology targets two-fold reduction in operation cost, high lithium recovery (90%), and reducing extraction time from 2 years to less than 24 hours. Contributing to the world-wide Total Addressable Market (TAM) of ~$992 billion, this technology will impact the global lithium market, growing at an estimated compound annual growth rate (CAGR) of 1.9% for  energy storage, electronic bikes, electrification of tools, and other battery-intense applications.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project proposes to develop a point-of-use nanomembrane filter for lithium extraction from non-traditional water resources. The proposed filter utilizes a robust, porous, and surface charged tailored sorbent of a novel coordination polymer framework prepared from an abundant natural polyphenol. The sorbents possess molecular sieving ability, tailorable pore size up to the pore dimension &lt;2 nm, and functional coordination sites for high binding affinity for lithium ions. The novelty of the innovation over current technologies (e.g., solar evaporation and ion-exchange techniques) is nano-based filter technology with selective affinity for lithium, enabling rapid and efficient extraction and recovery of lithium. The research objective is to demonstrate the proof-of-concept for recovery within 24 hours as either lithium chloride or lithium carbonate with targeted recovery efficiency and conversion &gt;90% in a subsequent step. The project includes: (1) Fabricating the membrane from the molecular sieves, (2) evaluating the lithium sieving performance, recovery, and conversion, and (3) fabricating a prototype filter unit. These developments will directly address current limitations in extraction time and efficiency, cost, recovery efficiency of lithium, and environmental impact of solar evaporation, ion-exchange and solvent extraction, and osmosis membrane systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2045379</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheeba</FirstName>
<LastName>Dawood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sheeba Dawood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sheeba.dawood@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000831604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MINERVA LITHIUM LLC</Name>
<CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
<ZipCode>274014898</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3362852860</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2901 E GATE CITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FFTUD93N4YZ8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MINERVA LITHIUM LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MINERVA LITHIUM LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274014904</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview:</strong> The global demand for lithium is witnessing exponential growth owing to its increased demand for energy storage, electronic bikes, electrification of tools, and other battery-intense applications. The lithium-ion battery market is projected to reach US$ 94.4 billion by 2025 thus outpacing the rate at which the lithium is currently mined from primary resources. Minerva Lithium aims to address this unmet need by developing an efficient, rapid, and cost-effective lithium extraction technology using a novel lithium sieving Nanomosaic solid-phase extraction (SPE) technology to ensure that supply matches the growing demand by reducing the cost significantly and cutting down the extraction time, literally from 2 years for traditional solar evaporation methods to less than 24 hours with above 85% recovery efficiency.</p> <p><strong>Technical Outcome:</strong> During the Phase I project period, we were able to develop and test the feasibility of, low-cost, Nanomosaic SPE technology that can extract lithium with sorption efficiency &gt;87% from brine solutions with lithium concentration up to 1000 ppm and salinity level up to 40,000 ppm. We also proved the feasibility to convert into pure lithium carbonate by stripping lithium from the sorbents using household vinegar followed by thermal crystallization to obtain battery-grade LCE with 99.99% purity. Furthermore, the current bench scale set up targets to treat 100 gal/min while desalinating the dissolved TDS and recovering lithium with ~80% efficiency followed by converting battery-grade LEC with 80% efficiency. Our results have proved that our Nano Mosaic SPE technology has potential for translating into a viable commercial product in the next phase the project.</p> <p><strong>Societal Outcome: </strong>The commercial potential of this technology is in the development of an efficient, rapid, and cost-effective lithium extraction flow process of <em>Nano Mosaic SPE</em> technology, which can be incorporated into existing brine operations and the ore-mined slurry. With the successful completion of the project and continuation into Phase II and III, our lithium extraction flow technology will significantly impact and benefit the lithium market, in which the current price for battery grade LCE is about $60,000 per ton, contributing a world-wide with the Total Addressable Market (TAM) of about $992 billion. Additionally, our technoeconomic analysis predict that we should be able to manufacture the smallest size of our proprietary reusable cartridge (100 gal/min) for a low cost (&lt;$1500). Given that our unique advantage will be improving the selectivity and the recovery efficiency of the extraction process this should make our lithium extraction flow process appealing to the smaller operators in lithium mining from hard rock and salar brines.</p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Societal and public as a whole:</span></em></strong> In overall, we believe that our lithium extraction technology will significantly impact and benefit the society and public, including lithium production companies, battery industries, automobiles, oil companies, petrochemical companies, produced water companies, mining companies, and water purification companies, as they are the largest producers of brines or providing services for purification and analysis of brines. The end-users of this technology include oil drillers, lithium producers, and energy storage device producers as well as the governmental entities such as Department of Energy, International Energy Agency, and Department of Interior.<strong> </strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Sheeba&nbsp;Dawood</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044536434_grouo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044536434_grouo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Minerva Lithium Team"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044536434_grouo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Minerva Lithium Team"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Left to right: Kelvin Adrah (intern), Hemali Rathnayake (co-founder), Sheeba Dawood (co-founder, CEO) and Zack Allen (intern)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Minerva Lithium</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sheeba&nbsp;Dawood</div> <div class="imageTitle">Minerva Lithium Team</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044692729_Picture1-Materials--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044692729_Picture1-Materials--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanomosaic sorbents"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044692729_Picture1-Materials--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanomosaic sorbents"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nanomosaic sorbent materials that selectively recovers Lithium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Minerva Lithium</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sheeba&nbsp;Dawood</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanomosaic sorbents</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044756571_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044756571_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Filter Unit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2045379/2045379_10758196_1683044756571_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Filter Unit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Brine flows into metal columns, which use Nano Mosaic to capture first all salts and minerals, and then just lithium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Minerva Lithium</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sheeba&nbsp;Dawood</div> <div class="imageTitle">Filter Unit</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview: The global demand for lithium is witnessing exponential growth owing to its increased demand for energy storage, electronic bikes, electrification of tools, and other battery-intense applications. The lithium-ion battery market is projected to reach US$ 94.4 billion by 2025 thus outpacing the rate at which the lithium is currently mined from primary resources. Minerva Lithium aims to address this unmet need by developing an efficient, rapid, and cost-effective lithium extraction technology using a novel lithium sieving Nanomosaic solid-phase extraction (SPE) technology to ensure that supply matches the growing demand by reducing the cost significantly and cutting down the extraction time, literally from 2 years for traditional solar evaporation methods to less than 24 hours with above 85% recovery efficiency.  Technical Outcome: During the Phase I project period, we were able to develop and test the feasibility of, low-cost, Nanomosaic SPE technology that can extract lithium with sorption efficiency &gt;87% from brine solutions with lithium concentration up to 1000 ppm and salinity level up to 40,000 ppm. We also proved the feasibility to convert into pure lithium carbonate by stripping lithium from the sorbents using household vinegar followed by thermal crystallization to obtain battery-grade LCE with 99.99% purity. Furthermore, the current bench scale set up targets to treat 100 gal/min while desalinating the dissolved TDS and recovering lithium with ~80% efficiency followed by converting battery-grade LEC with 80% efficiency. Our results have proved that our Nano Mosaic SPE technology has potential for translating into a viable commercial product in the next phase the project.  Societal Outcome: The commercial potential of this technology is in the development of an efficient, rapid, and cost-effective lithium extraction flow process of Nano Mosaic SPE technology, which can be incorporated into existing brine operations and the ore-mined slurry. With the successful completion of the project and continuation into Phase II and III, our lithium extraction flow technology will significantly impact and benefit the lithium market, in which the current price for battery grade LCE is about $60,000 per ton, contributing a world-wide with the Total Addressable Market (TAM) of about $992 billion. Additionally, our technoeconomic analysis predict that we should be able to manufacture the smallest size of our proprietary reusable cartridge (100 gal/min) for a low cost (&lt;$1500). Given that our unique advantage will be improving the selectivity and the recovery efficiency of the extraction process this should make our lithium extraction flow process appealing to the smaller operators in lithium mining from hard rock and salar brines.  Societal and public as a whole: In overall, we believe that our lithium extraction technology will significantly impact and benefit the society and public, including lithium production companies, battery industries, automobiles, oil companies, petrochemical companies, produced water companies, mining companies, and water purification companies, as they are the largest producers of brines or providing services for purification and analysis of brines. The end-users of this technology include oil drillers, lithium producers, and energy storage device producers as well as the governmental entities such as Department of Energy, International Energy Agency, and Department of Interior.           Last Modified: 05/02/2023       Submitted by: Sheeba Dawood]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
