<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research in DRMS: Incorporating Psychological Distance Framing in Narrative Persuasion]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22654.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22654</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Scientists often use numbers and statistics to communicate health and environmental risks with the public. Members of the public, however, may find this type of messaging difficult to understand or unappealing. In contrast, narrative or stories may offer an effective alternative. When reading a well-crafted narrative, people may find themselves absorbed into an imaginary world and identify with the characters portrayed. These processes, termed as transportation and identification, illustrate how narratives may change people’s attitudes and behaviors. Notably, when people are engaged in a narrative, they may feel closer to the characters or the scenario, which may also influence their perception about the issue featured in the story. This research project examines whether narratives indeed reduce the distance people perceive toward the characters and the scenario and subsequently influence their attitudes toward two risk topics – ocean plastic pollution and e-cigarette use. Specifically, participants will read a narrative that features either a close scenario (e.g., ocean plastic pollution harming their own country) or a far scenario (e.g., ocean plastic pollution harming a foreign country), and portrays characters that are either similar or different from them. We then examine whether these differences in the narrative influence their transportation and identification levels, and more importantly, whether they report attitude changes that are consistent with the positions promoted in the narrative. This project will help risk communication experts craft narrative persuasion messages to target different individuals more effectively. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project seeks to advance the theorization of narrative persuasion in risk communication through the lens of psychological distance. There are two main objectives. First, this research explores how using narrative can influence risk communication outcomes. The central argument is that via the mediation of transportation and identification, the effectiveness of narrative persuasion is influenced by the perceived distance between audience and the risk featured in the narrative. Second, the research aims to incorporate distance framing into narrative message design to effectively communicate about abstract and uncertain risks. Specifically, this research seeks to identify the impacts of distance cues associated with narrative character and narrative scenario in actualizing persuasion effects. The two experiments feature different character-based and scenario-based distance cues. The experiments focus on one environmental risk – ocean plastic pollution, and one health risk – e-cigarette use. Intrinsic to public perception of these two topics are all four dimensions of psychological distance – social, spatial, temporal, and hypothetical. By testing the proposed theoretical framework in different environmental and health contexts, this research has broad theoretical and practical implications. Findings from this project contribute to the literature on narrative persuasion and risk communication and inform the design of narrative messaging that is widely utilized in information campaigns and entertainment education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/04/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2046692</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet Z Yang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zyang5@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000589019</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>SIXIAO</FirstName>
<LastName>LIU</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>SIXIAO LIU</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sixiaoli@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000835093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282577</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 LEE ENTRANCE STE 211</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LMCJKRFW5R81</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GMZUKXFDJMA9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142601060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~22654</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Narrative persuasion is an appealing message strategy. When reading a well-crafted narrative, people often find themselves immersed in an imaginary world and morphed into the standpoints of narrative characters. Through these processes, people are often motivated to learn from the narrative characters and apply the knowledge to their future practice. In addition to transportation and identification, narratives may also impact people&rsquo;s beliefs and behaviors by reshaping their risk assessment. The findings of this research project supported this conjunction. Specifically, people&rsquo;s perceived distance between themselves and the risk featured in the narrative can be reshaped. The changes in distance perceptions impact people&rsquo;s attitude, behavioral intention, and policy support regarding the risk. When an environmental risk (i.e., ocean plastic pollution) was featured, people preferred a narrative featuring socially far characters&rsquo; encounters in a geographically close location. After reading this type of narrative, they perceived the risk caused by ocean plastic pollution as a relevant, certain and urgent threat and reacted more positively in dealing with the risk. As a comparison, the narrative with close distance cues embedded in the depiction of character and scenario was least effective in approaching the public and producing persuasive effects. Differently, when a health risk (i.e., vaping-related lung disease) was featured, the same type of narrative was most effective in delivering risk information and persuading the public. People were sensitive to the narrative introducing a socially close character&rsquo;s vaping experience and how his choice negatively influenced his well-being. From a peer&rsquo;s perspective, learning the dire consequences experienced by the character alarmed the audience and motivated them to adopt recommended actions to protect their health. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual merit:&nbsp;</p> <p>This research project proposes a new perspective to examine the effect of narrative persuasion and its utility in risk communication through the lens of psychological distance. First, this research has merit in expanding the discussion on psychological distance. Psychological distance has been mostly studied as a framing technique in the non-narrative format. This research investigates how narratives with different distance cues influence people&rsquo;s distance perceptions across dimensions. Second, this research contributes to the theorizing of narrative persuasion. The results suggest that psychological distance perception may also work as a pathway that relays narrative effects along with transportation and identification. Lastly, this research applies the proposed theoretical framework to investigate two important environmental and health risks: ocean plastic pollution and e-cigarette use. The findings suggest that the narratives with distal cues in character or scenario depiction are more helpful in communicating ocean plastic pollution, while the narrative with proximal cues congruently embedded in character and scenario depiction is more effective in communicating health threats caused by e-cigarette use.</p> <p>Broader impacts:</p> <p>This research project has the potential to provide theoretical contributions to a broader area of science. By investigating how distance-framed narratives influence the way people process the message and cope with the risk introduced in the message, this research links two promising fields of risk communication and social psychology. In addition, the findings observed in the study on e-cigarette use may have the potential to expand the discussion on tobacco control and other substance abuse in the field of public health. People often fail to comprehend how environmental and health risks affect them in the long run. This research affirms that narratives may be particularly effective in communicating risks with high catastrophic potential. The findings also suggest that different risk contexts invite different combinations of distance cues in narrative design. Practitioners may consider strategically customizing the message according to the risk context focused and the characteristics of the audiences. Distal cues may be more effective in communicating environmental hazards, such as climate change. In contrast, the effectiveness of health narratives may be boosted when proximal cues are incorporated. In addition, when analyzing the role of psychological distance in facilitating persuasive effects, temporal distance perception is consistently related to positive communication outcomes among different distance dimensions. Based on this observation, when developing risk communication messages in the narrative format, it is helpful to feature an engaging storyline to stress the urgency of risk issues that people may fail to see as relevant to them at the current point.</p> <p>Based on the data obtained, a doctoral dissertation advised by the PI and conducted by the Co-PI was successfully defended in May 2021. Additionally, one peer-reviewed journal article has been accepted for publication. Another three manuscripts are under review or in preparation. Six conference papers have been presented at national and international conferences, including the&nbsp;<em>Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) Annual Conference 2021&amp;2022, International Communication Association Annual Conference 2022,</em>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<em>Society for Risk Analysis Annual Meeting 2021 &amp; 2022</em>. One paper presented at the&nbsp;<em>AEJMC Annual Conference 2021</em>&nbsp;received a Top Student Paper Award, and another one presented at the&nbsp;<em>AEJMC Annual Conference 2022</em>&nbsp;received a Top Faculty Paper Award.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Janet&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Yang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Narrative persuasion is an appealing message strategy. When reading a well-crafted narrative, people often find themselves immersed in an imaginary world and morphed into the standpoints of narrative characters. Through these processes, people are often motivated to learn from the narrative characters and apply the knowledge to their future practice. In addition to transportation and identification, narratives may also impact people’s beliefs and behaviors by reshaping their risk assessment. The findings of this research project supported this conjunction. Specifically, people’s perceived distance between themselves and the risk featured in the narrative can be reshaped. The changes in distance perceptions impact people’s attitude, behavioral intention, and policy support regarding the risk. When an environmental risk (i.e., ocean plastic pollution) was featured, people preferred a narrative featuring socially far characters’ encounters in a geographically close location. After reading this type of narrative, they perceived the risk caused by ocean plastic pollution as a relevant, certain and urgent threat and reacted more positively in dealing with the risk. As a comparison, the narrative with close distance cues embedded in the depiction of character and scenario was least effective in approaching the public and producing persuasive effects. Differently, when a health risk (i.e., vaping-related lung disease) was featured, the same type of narrative was most effective in delivering risk information and persuading the public. People were sensitive to the narrative introducing a socially close character’s vaping experience and how his choice negatively influenced his well-being. From a peer’s perspective, learning the dire consequences experienced by the character alarmed the audience and motivated them to adopt recommended actions to protect their health.     Intellectual merit:   This research project proposes a new perspective to examine the effect of narrative persuasion and its utility in risk communication through the lens of psychological distance. First, this research has merit in expanding the discussion on psychological distance. Psychological distance has been mostly studied as a framing technique in the non-narrative format. This research investigates how narratives with different distance cues influence people’s distance perceptions across dimensions. Second, this research contributes to the theorizing of narrative persuasion. The results suggest that psychological distance perception may also work as a pathway that relays narrative effects along with transportation and identification. Lastly, this research applies the proposed theoretical framework to investigate two important environmental and health risks: ocean plastic pollution and e-cigarette use. The findings suggest that the narratives with distal cues in character or scenario depiction are more helpful in communicating ocean plastic pollution, while the narrative with proximal cues congruently embedded in character and scenario depiction is more effective in communicating health threats caused by e-cigarette use.  Broader impacts:  This research project has the potential to provide theoretical contributions to a broader area of science. By investigating how distance-framed narratives influence the way people process the message and cope with the risk introduced in the message, this research links two promising fields of risk communication and social psychology. In addition, the findings observed in the study on e-cigarette use may have the potential to expand the discussion on tobacco control and other substance abuse in the field of public health. People often fail to comprehend how environmental and health risks affect them in the long run. This research affirms that narratives may be particularly effective in communicating risks with high catastrophic potential. The findings also suggest that different risk contexts invite different combinations of distance cues in narrative design. Practitioners may consider strategically customizing the message according to the risk context focused and the characteristics of the audiences. Distal cues may be more effective in communicating environmental hazards, such as climate change. In contrast, the effectiveness of health narratives may be boosted when proximal cues are incorporated. In addition, when analyzing the role of psychological distance in facilitating persuasive effects, temporal distance perception is consistently related to positive communication outcomes among different distance dimensions. Based on this observation, when developing risk communication messages in the narrative format, it is helpful to feature an engaging storyline to stress the urgency of risk issues that people may fail to see as relevant to them at the current point.  Based on the data obtained, a doctoral dissertation advised by the PI and conducted by the Co-PI was successfully defended in May 2021. Additionally, one peer-reviewed journal article has been accepted for publication. Another three manuscripts are under review or in preparation. Six conference papers have been presented at national and international conferences, including the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) Annual Conference 2021&amp;2022, International Communication Association Annual Conference 2022, and Society for Risk Analysis Annual Meeting 2021 &amp; 2022. One paper presented at the AEJMC Annual Conference 2021 received a Top Student Paper Award, and another one presented at the AEJMC Annual Conference 2022 received a Top Faculty Paper Award.       Last Modified: 01/04/2023       Submitted by: Janet Z Yang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
