<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  PolyBrick™: Polymer-regolith composite landing pads build from in-situ lunar materials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255916.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255916</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to enhance exploration and commercial development of the Moon and, eventually, solar system, by lowering the risk of damage to surface and orbital infrastructure from ejected lunar dust during rocket landings and launches. This activity is in the area of material processing/manufacturing in space, and focuses on the space infrastructure (civil works) market sector, similar to roads and airports on Earth. Creating a viable, cost-effective solution to mitigate lunar dust will lower the cost of accessing the lunar surface and accelerate the development of lunar surface infrastructure that is necessary for all aspects of sustainable commercial space development, including mining, manufacturing, construction, habitation, power generation, communications, and in particular, transportation. Facilitating lunar exploration will expand scientific knowledge of the solar system.  It will also enhance commercial development that will expand economic opportunities by opening new areas of the economy in space, with inevitable spin-off benefits for life on Earth. In the long term, the capacity to create new areas for habitation on the Moon and throughout the solar system will have profound impacts on human society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project proposes building lunar landing pads to address the problem of surface dust ejected during rocket landings and launches, which can otherwise damage both nearby and distant infrastructure, including those structures located the other side of the Moon and in orbit. To minimize transport costs from Earth, surface infrastructure must be constructed from local materials as much as possible. Instead of using high-energy processes to harden regolith, this approach will bind it with a high-performance polymer created from lunar volatiles co-located with water-ice in polar regions. This solution reduces mass, cost, and technical risk by leveraging anticipated water-ice mining operations and utilizing discarded volatiles from their operations to produce high-quality polymers.  The approach may be sustainable, producing enough material annually to replace worn-out sections of landing pads. Phase I will focus on converting raw volatiles into polymer precursors, fabricating/testing candidate composite materials, and elaborating the concept of operations, through a combination of research, modeling, and laboratory experiments. Information gathered during Phase I will narrow the range of candidate polymers for further consideration, identifying chemical synthesis pathways for more extensive development, and highlighting areas of improvement to maximize commercial success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2048453</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffery</FirstName>
<LastName>Greenblatt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffery B Greenblatt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeff@emerging-futures.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000817692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>EMERGING FUTURES LLC</Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>972093359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106936452</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>721 NW 9TH AVE.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[SUITE 195]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z4UFK836T3L6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMERGING FUTURES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emerging Futures LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947102604</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2726 Eighth St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~255916</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>SBIR Phase I: PolyBrick<sup>TM</sup>:&nbsp;</strong><strong>Polymer-regolith composite landing pads build from in-situ lunar materials</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;">Project Outcomes</p> <p style="text-align: center;">NSF Grant 2048453</p> <p style="text-align: center;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: center;">Jeffery B. Greenblatt, CEO, Emerging Futures, LLC</p> <p style="text-align: center;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: center;">January 10, 2023</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The goals of the project were to identify a set of processes that convert raw materials found in water ice on the lunar surface into high-performance polymers that, when mixed with lunar regolith and cured, can deliver a product in the form of a durable landing pad for spacecraft, mitigating the critical problem of lunar dust generation. Due to the complexity of converting raw materials into polymers, this Phase I project focused on simulating the initial separation and purification of key raw materials from lunar ice deposits; and simulating the subsequent conversion of these materials into precursor chemicals for the production of polymers envisioned for mixing with regolith to produce durable landing pad materials. The chemical process modeling results generated will help inform future research.</p> <p>Two other major activities were simulating the pressure and temperature environment of a rocket exhaust plume in proximity to a landing pad on the lunar surface, producing finished polymer-regolith composite brick samples, and performing strength and thermal testing on them, in order to help determine which types of polymers might be suitable to produce. The data obtained will be valuable in developing better landing pad materials. In addition, market research on the business need for lunar landing pads was conducted that resulted in some adjustments to the research focus, in order to better understand how near-term market opportunities could be addressed from a technical perspective.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have advanced the state of knowledge in understanding lunar surface plume dynamics, physical properties of polymer-regolith composite materials, and chemical transformation of volatiles into polymer precursors for construction of lunar landing pads. Further, this work is helping facilitate the expansion of commercial activities into space that will grow the global economy, as well as foster greater human participation in and experience of the cosmos, with many intangible benefits.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/16/2023<br>      Modified by: Jeffery&nbsp;B&nbsp;Greenblatt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: PolyBrickTM: Polymer-regolith composite landing pads build from in-situ lunar materials Project Outcomes NSF Grant 2048453   Jeffery B. Greenblatt, CEO, Emerging Futures, LLC   January 10, 2023     The goals of the project were to identify a set of processes that convert raw materials found in water ice on the lunar surface into high-performance polymers that, when mixed with lunar regolith and cured, can deliver a product in the form of a durable landing pad for spacecraft, mitigating the critical problem of lunar dust generation. Due to the complexity of converting raw materials into polymers, this Phase I project focused on simulating the initial separation and purification of key raw materials from lunar ice deposits; and simulating the subsequent conversion of these materials into precursor chemicals for the production of polymers envisioned for mixing with regolith to produce durable landing pad materials. The chemical process modeling results generated will help inform future research.  Two other major activities were simulating the pressure and temperature environment of a rocket exhaust plume in proximity to a landing pad on the lunar surface, producing finished polymer-regolith composite brick samples, and performing strength and thermal testing on them, in order to help determine which types of polymers might be suitable to produce. The data obtained will be valuable in developing better landing pad materials. In addition, market research on the business need for lunar landing pads was conducted that resulted in some adjustments to the research focus, in order to better understand how near-term market opportunities could be addressed from a technical perspective.   We have advanced the state of knowledge in understanding lunar surface plume dynamics, physical properties of polymer-regolith composite materials, and chemical transformation of volatiles into polymer precursors for construction of lunar landing pads. Further, this work is helping facilitate the expansion of commercial activities into space that will grow the global economy, as well as foster greater human participation in and experience of the cosmos, with many intangible benefits.       Last Modified: 01/16/2023       Submitted by: Jeffery B Greenblatt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
