<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Technologies of Transaction in Moral Economic Framework]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This doctoral dissertation project investigates collaboration between industries that typically operate outside the sphere of traditional finance. It focuses on the financial obstacles encountered by these industries, as well as how alliances among non-traditional industries allow these to be overcome. Specifically, using linguistic and cultural anthropological approaches, the research examines what role digital currency plays in facilitating financial market access among marginalized workers, as well as what beliefs and experiences most directly shape moral and economic notions of value within these transactional spaces. Research findings will be broadly disseminated to professionals, policy makers, and researchers in relevant fields and will include public outreach efforts to support the well-being of marginalized communities. Additionally, the research contributes to the training of a U.S.-based graduate student. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through a combination of in-person and digital ethnographic fieldwork at corporate offices and within the broader community of financially marginal individuals, as well as semiotic, social network, and other methods of data analysis, the project examines the economic, political and ethical motivations of this collaboration as well as its material and symbolic impacts. The researcher will conduct digital archival research to trace the financial and moral discourses that have shaped the margins of the finance industry and conduct interviews with users of alternate forms of financial transaction. The research builds on multiple anthropological literatures to provide a fresh perspective on how moral, monetary, and meaning-making practices interact in the creation and discernment of value.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2048350</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Esra</FirstName>
<LastName>Padgett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Esra S Padgett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[epadgett@gradcenter.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Reyes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela Reyes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arreye@hunter.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000761269</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Graduate School University Center</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128177526</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>365 5TH AVE STE 8113</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QVW9TFAZJFE7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Graduate School University Center]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[365 Fifth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~25200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF Outcome</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Esra Padgett has completed research for her dissertation, &ldquo;Technologies of Transaction in Moral Economic Framework&rdquo; supported by the NSF Doctoral Dissertation Research Grant. During her funding period, she spent 12 months in Los Angeles conducting participant observation at the offices of a cryptocurrency company. As an anthropologist, Padgett was interested in understanding how novel financial technologies can be made useful to marginalized workers experiencing exclusion from mainstream financial institutions. Using linguistic and cultural anthropological approaches, the research specifically focused on the shared marginality of a legally marginal currency and a group of marginalized workers in order to advance understandings of financial access for disenfranchised communities as well as the study of moral and economic notions of value.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As a participant observer, Padgett accomplished the goal of her research and assisted in creating documentation materials to create a bridge between academia and public activism. By sharing research materials, including interviews with marginalized workers experiencing financial discrimination, she has helped create a resource for future public outreach. The data collected during this period is the foundation for an argument Padgett is formulating about the relationship between economic marginality, cultural stigma, and ethical decision-making. Through years of financial exclusion, marginalized workers have not only become hyper-knowledgeable about financial tools, but often serve as the test cases for emergent technologies. Many of these workers believe that banking should be a human right and have begun to organize around this issue in formal legal contexts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Padgett also travelled to Las Vegas, Miami and Washington D.C. during her grant period to observe trade conventions, industry meet-ups and congressional fly-ins. The Miami trip centered around a tradeshow where the cryptocurrency company&rsquo;s first product, a payment processor, was introduced to an industry experiencing financial discrimination. Padgett was able to observe how the marginalized laborers first using a novel financial tool help shape a product through feedback and initial trials. During the trip to D.C., Padgett observed as workers with histories of financial discrimination spoke with congress people on the issue of fair banking. Padgett&rsquo;s involvement extends beyond her own research interests, and she helped draft the formal letter to congress members for this lobbying trip. In both trips, cultural and ethical notions of value were integral to the financial devaluation of these laborers, as they became marginalized by financial institutions despite working in legal businesses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Padgett&rsquo;s research over the course of the grant period forms the basis of her dissertation. The research is an important contribution to multiple anthropological literatures as it provides a fresh perspective on how moral, monetary and meaning-making practices interact in the creation and discernment of value and will be completed in 2024.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Esra&nbsp;S&nbsp;Padgett</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF Outcome     Esra Padgett has completed research for her dissertation, "Technologies of Transaction in Moral Economic Framework" supported by the NSF Doctoral Dissertation Research Grant. During her funding period, she spent 12 months in Los Angeles conducting participant observation at the offices of a cryptocurrency company. As an anthropologist, Padgett was interested in understanding how novel financial technologies can be made useful to marginalized workers experiencing exclusion from mainstream financial institutions. Using linguistic and cultural anthropological approaches, the research specifically focused on the shared marginality of a legally marginal currency and a group of marginalized workers in order to advance understandings of financial access for disenfranchised communities as well as the study of moral and economic notions of value.     As a participant observer, Padgett accomplished the goal of her research and assisted in creating documentation materials to create a bridge between academia and public activism. By sharing research materials, including interviews with marginalized workers experiencing financial discrimination, she has helped create a resource for future public outreach. The data collected during this period is the foundation for an argument Padgett is formulating about the relationship between economic marginality, cultural stigma, and ethical decision-making. Through years of financial exclusion, marginalized workers have not only become hyper-knowledgeable about financial tools, but often serve as the test cases for emergent technologies. Many of these workers believe that banking should be a human right and have begun to organize around this issue in formal legal contexts.     Padgett also travelled to Las Vegas, Miami and Washington D.C. during her grant period to observe trade conventions, industry meet-ups and congressional fly-ins. The Miami trip centered around a tradeshow where the cryptocurrency company’s first product, a payment processor, was introduced to an industry experiencing financial discrimination. Padgett was able to observe how the marginalized laborers first using a novel financial tool help shape a product through feedback and initial trials. During the trip to D.C., Padgett observed as workers with histories of financial discrimination spoke with congress people on the issue of fair banking. Padgett’s involvement extends beyond her own research interests, and she helped draft the formal letter to congress members for this lobbying trip. In both trips, cultural and ethical notions of value were integral to the financial devaluation of these laborers, as they became marginalized by financial institutions despite working in legal businesses.     Padgett’s research over the course of the grant period forms the basis of her dissertation. The research is an important contribution to multiple anthropological literatures as it provides a fresh perspective on how moral, monetary and meaning-making practices interact in the creation and discernment of value and will be completed in 2024.             Last Modified: 08/01/2023       Submitted by: Esra S Padgett]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
