<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Point-of-use microfluidics-based electrochemical platform for per- and polyfluoroalkyl substance (PFAS) detection in source water]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a point-of-use, microfluidics-based electrochemical platform for per- and polyfluoroalkyl substance (PFAS) detection in source water. Human exposure to PFAS is a public health concern. The commercialization of a point-of-use electrochemical PFAS detection device will significantly improve water quality by providing an on-site, cost-effective portable technology to detect emerging contaminants. It offers a unique replaceable cartridge system of capture molecules that integrates seamlessly with the sensor module to test for a catalog of contaminants. The point-of-use device automates sample analysis and displays lab-quality results in an easily understood format, eliminating the need for bulky equipment, tedious sample preparation, and trained laboratory technicians. This simple display solves major issues of PFAS tests currently available in the market.   Additionally, the device will be rapid, reliable, and affordable, making it ideal for use in low-resource or underserved areas with limited access to advanced equipment. The availability of a modular, rapid device will allow researchers to quickly optimize and rapidly respond. As the sensor is tailorable to a variety of potential contaminants, threats, and diseases, it may have multiple applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a rapid, sensitive, and selective, field-deployable, microfluidics-based, point-of-use electrochemical sensor platform. The platform integrates non-planar interdigitated electrodes with a microfluidic channel packed with an engineered nanoporous material called metal-organic framework. This platform has significant benefits over the current generation of electrochemical biosensors. Electrode nanoporosity mitigates non-specific adsorption and overcomes diffusion limitations leading to rapid signal acquisition. The microelectrode design results in a high signal-to-noise ratio leading to increased sensitivity. Sensitivity and selectivity can be decoupled using the shear force (controlled using the flow-rate) as a tuning parameter. The device’s current detection limit of 0.5 ng/L for perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) is much lower than the US Environmental Protection Agency's health advisory levels of 70 ng/L or 70 ppt in drinking water. Finally, the developed sensor's modular nature allows the sensor to be decoupled from the capture molecule interface. The sensor can be easily adapted by packing different capture molecule-specific materials to detect many different emerging contaminants in drinking water like GenX compounds and heavy metals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2048361</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sagnik</FirstName>
<LastName>Basuray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sagnik Basuray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sagnik.basuray@njit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000693459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>323 DR MARTIN LUTHER KING JR BLV</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SGBMHQ7VXNH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW JERSEY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Jersey Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Heights]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary outcomes of the project can be divided into two parts. The first outcome is related to customer discovery to conduct interviews with potential customers and partners to understand better the demand for testing per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in the source water. The second outcome is the commercial goals to understand the commerciality of our novel electrochemical sensing platform that utilizes a shear-enhanced, flow-through, nanoporous, and capacitive electrode technology (hereafter called &ldquo;ESSENCE&rdquo;) as a PFAS detection sensor. The statistical analysis of post-interview learnings was 92.9% agreed that PFOS/PFOA remains the most important emerging contaminant to be detected. Other contaminates of interest includes 1,4-dioxane (28.6%), microplastics (14.3%), 1,2,3-TCP (7.1%), EDB 97.1%) and NDMA (7.1%).Tandem Mass Spectroscopy remains the preferred gold standard method (85.7%), followed by HPLC (21.4%). 57.1% of customers preferred a one-day turnaround time instead of 3 weeks standard wait time. In addition, 42.8% of customers would like to pay around $150 per water sample vs. $300-$400 standard analysis rate. ESSENCE could be an important asset for testing PFAS with the prime feature of testing two ppt PFAS in 10-15 minutes which is not available currently in the market. Civil engineers at remediation sites of defense preferred automated PFAS analysis with a time of 10 minutes, and the same was achieved in the lab with further product modifications. We trained multiple undergraduate and high school students from underrepresented groups and minorities. Some high school and undergraduate researchers are authors of the submitted manuscripts. Co-EL Dr. Charmi Chande participated in and won The Business Model competition held at NJIT. The competition and lecture series helped Charmi to understand the essential components of making a slide deck for pitching and further investment strategies.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Sagnik&nbsp;Basuray</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary outcomes of the project can be divided into two parts. The first outcome is related to customer discovery to conduct interviews with potential customers and partners to understand better the demand for testing per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in the source water. The second outcome is the commercial goals to understand the commerciality of our novel electrochemical sensing platform that utilizes a shear-enhanced, flow-through, nanoporous, and capacitive electrode technology (hereafter called "ESSENCE") as a PFAS detection sensor. The statistical analysis of post-interview learnings was 92.9% agreed that PFOS/PFOA remains the most important emerging contaminant to be detected. Other contaminates of interest includes 1,4-dioxane (28.6%), microplastics (14.3%), 1,2,3-TCP (7.1%), EDB 97.1%) and NDMA (7.1%).Tandem Mass Spectroscopy remains the preferred gold standard method (85.7%), followed by HPLC (21.4%). 57.1% of customers preferred a one-day turnaround time instead of 3 weeks standard wait time. In addition, 42.8% of customers would like to pay around $150 per water sample vs. $300-$400 standard analysis rate. ESSENCE could be an important asset for testing PFAS with the prime feature of testing two ppt PFAS in 10-15 minutes which is not available currently in the market. Civil engineers at remediation sites of defense preferred automated PFAS analysis with a time of 10 minutes, and the same was achieved in the lab with further product modifications. We trained multiple undergraduate and high school students from underrepresented groups and minorities. Some high school and undergraduate researchers are authors of the submitted manuscripts. Co-EL Dr. Charmi Chande participated in and won The Business Model competition held at NJIT. The competition and lecture series helped Charmi to understand the essential components of making a slide deck for pitching and further investment strategies.        Last Modified: 09/14/2023       Submitted by: Sagnik Basuray]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
