<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research in Economics: Internal Migration and the Diffusion of Schooling in the US]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By the late 19th century, the United States achieved very strong school enrollment rates. This project examines the role of internal migration in the spread of education, using novel historical data that covers many aspects of American economic and social life before and after the Civil War.  The information recorded in the dataset includes the value of the taxed property and the amounts of tax revenue raised the number of public and private schools, teachers, and pupils in those schools; their finances by revenue source; the number of libraries and newspapers printed; and the prevailing wages paid to different kinds of labor. Utilizing this data, the project considers potential mechanisms to understand how internal migration affected local schooling choices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project explores how migration from more educated states affect school enrollment rates for the local population. The project builds on the notion that inequality in school enrollments can be explained by the origins of migrants who chose to live in a given county. Accordingly, internal migration was an important channel in the spread of schools in the US. Using detailed historical data, the project examines specific channels through which migrants from more educated states improved the schooling outcomes of the locals. The project particularly focuses on the funding of schools through property taxes to consider that migrants from states with functioning public systems can be instrumental for more public funding for schools in their destinations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049699</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Petra</FirstName>
<LastName>Moser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Petra Moser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pmoser@stern.nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000063629</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vasily</FirstName>
<LastName>Rusanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vasily Rusanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vr856@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833018</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQ S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NX9PXMKW5KW8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100121276</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[40 W. 4th St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, we collected social statistics schedules from the US Censuses of 1850, 1860, and 1870. We focused on a sample for ten states: Arkansas, California, Iowa, Illinois, Indiana, Kansas, Michigan, Minnesota, Missouri, and Wisconsin. The final digitized dataset includes county-level information on taxes, property valuations, crops, educational institutions, newspapers, libraries, wages, and crime. We additionally collected information from the 1906 publication of the "Men of Science," a biographical dictionary of US scientists who worked in US colleges, universities, and research labs.<br /><br />In our first project, "Internal Migration and the Diffusion of Schooling in the United States," we use county-level social statistics data to understand internal migration's role in promoting primary education in mid-19th century America. During this period, the United States achieved the highest primary school enrollment rate in the world. We investigate how internal migrants from relatively more educated origin states helped the proliferation of schools in their destinations. Using the population Census, we track the migration and enrollment decisions of millions of families in 1850-1870. We combine these data with the tuition costs and school taxes from the newly-digitized social statistics.<br /><br />We study how the enrollment rates of the natives were affected by the arrival of migrants from different origin states. We find that native, non-migrant parents were more likely to enroll their children in school in the counties that received relatively more migrants from more educated origin states. To tackle the concerns of reverse causality (for example, internal migrants from more educated states choosing to go to places with higher enrollments), we predict the number of migrants with the agro-climatic similarity between origins and destinations. Using the predicted number of migrants as an instrumental variable for the actual migration confirms our results. We also show that migrants help form functioning public systems for funding schools in their destinations. Our results speak to how extraordinary levels of internal migration in the United States mattered for economic development and, specifically, boosted school enrollment rates.<br /><br />In a second project, we study the role of education in determining the opportunity to become a scientist. We hand-collect information from the 1906 edition of a biographical dictionary of scientists, the American Men of Science (MoS). This dictionary contains biographies of researchers working in US colleges, universities, and research labs. By matching data on scientists' careers to the population Census, we study how parental occupations, wealth, and location affect scientists' careers and their discoveries. To that end, we reconstruct these scientists' life and career paths, starting from their birth through their undergraduate and graduate training and then their appointments as instructors and researchers.<br /><br />We investigate the role of access to primary and secondary educational institutions during childhood in a scientific career. From the social statistics, we leverage detailed information on schools in the counties where scientists grew up. We look at how access to public education encourages broad-based participation in science by women and men from economically and ethnically diverse backgrounds, using the family characteristics from the sample linked to the Population Census. We anticipate sizable effects given that access to science was so concentrated. We also test whether attending elite research universities removes the differences in family origins for research output.<br /><br />The social statistics from 1850-1870 are ready to become a publicly available dataset. We cleaned the data, removing the inconsistencies, verifying checksums, and aggregating values to the county level. The data will interest any researcher, whether an economist, a historian, a sociologist or a political scientist&#8288;, studying that period of American history.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Vasily&nbsp;Rusanov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, we collected social statistics schedules from the US Censuses of 1850, 1860, and 1870. We focused on a sample for ten states: Arkansas, California, Iowa, Illinois, Indiana, Kansas, Michigan, Minnesota, Missouri, and Wisconsin. The final digitized dataset includes county-level information on taxes, property valuations, crops, educational institutions, newspapers, libraries, wages, and crime. We additionally collected information from the 1906 publication of the "Men of Science," a biographical dictionary of US scientists who worked in US colleges, universities, and research labs.  In our first project, "Internal Migration and the Diffusion of Schooling in the United States," we use county-level social statistics data to understand internal migration's role in promoting primary education in mid-19th century America. During this period, the United States achieved the highest primary school enrollment rate in the world. We investigate how internal migrants from relatively more educated origin states helped the proliferation of schools in their destinations. Using the population Census, we track the migration and enrollment decisions of millions of families in 1850-1870. We combine these data with the tuition costs and school taxes from the newly-digitized social statistics.  We study how the enrollment rates of the natives were affected by the arrival of migrants from different origin states. We find that native, non-migrant parents were more likely to enroll their children in school in the counties that received relatively more migrants from more educated origin states. To tackle the concerns of reverse causality (for example, internal migrants from more educated states choosing to go to places with higher enrollments), we predict the number of migrants with the agro-climatic similarity between origins and destinations. Using the predicted number of migrants as an instrumental variable for the actual migration confirms our results. We also show that migrants help form functioning public systems for funding schools in their destinations. Our results speak to how extraordinary levels of internal migration in the United States mattered for economic development and, specifically, boosted school enrollment rates.  In a second project, we study the role of education in determining the opportunity to become a scientist. We hand-collect information from the 1906 edition of a biographical dictionary of scientists, the American Men of Science (MoS). This dictionary contains biographies of researchers working in US colleges, universities, and research labs. By matching data on scientists' careers to the population Census, we study how parental occupations, wealth, and location affect scientists' careers and their discoveries. To that end, we reconstruct these scientists' life and career paths, starting from their birth through their undergraduate and graduate training and then their appointments as instructors and researchers.  We investigate the role of access to primary and secondary educational institutions during childhood in a scientific career. From the social statistics, we leverage detailed information on schools in the counties where scientists grew up. We look at how access to public education encourages broad-based participation in science by women and men from economically and ethnically diverse backgrounds, using the family characteristics from the sample linked to the Population Census. We anticipate sizable effects given that access to science was so concentrated. We also test whether attending elite research universities removes the differences in family origins for research output.  The social statistics from 1850-1870 are ready to become a publicly available dataset. We cleaned the data, removing the inconsistencies, verifying checksums, and aggregating values to the county level. The data will interest any researcher, whether an economist, a historian, a sociologist or a political scientist&#8288;, studying that period of American history.       Last Modified: 10/26/2022       Submitted by: Vasily Rusanov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
