<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Transatlantic (US-NI-RoI) Workshop on Collaborative IoT/CPS Research Opportunities – Security and Trust Beyond Hardening]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>80258.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>103023</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Roxanne Nikolaus</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rnikolau@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927578</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The continuous prevalence of Internet-of-Things (IoT) and the blurring boundary between cyber and physical systems have brought a plethora of opportunities to improve our ways of life. Along with the opportunities come the security risks associated with the rapid introduction and integration of information technologies and operational technologies. This project aims to foster collaborations between U.S. researchers and those from the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland to leverage expertise toward development of novel research projects in the thematic areas of IoT/Cyberphysical (CPS) Cybersecurity. This trilateral collaboration will facilitate identification of key science questions and develop mutually beneficial partnerships to address them. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two virtual interactive webinars and an in-person culminating workshop will bring together researchers and industry representative in Forensic-ready IoT/CPS, Privacy Preserving CPS, and Adversarial Learning CPS, as well as Crosscutting Research in Policy and Usability. The outcome is expected to be innovative and viable solutions proposed by multiple trilateral collaborative teams.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049960</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shanchieh</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shanchieh J Yang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sjyeec@rit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000492209</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J6TWTRKC1X14</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROCHESTER INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rochester Institute of Tech]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5914</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6869</Code>
<Text>US/IRELAND R &amp; D</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~96023</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~7000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project hosted a total of 5 webinars and 1 in-person workshop between fall 2020 to fall 2022. The overarching goal of the webinars and workshop is to foster trilateral research collaborations between the United States, Ireland, and Northern Ireland, in the area of IoT/CPS Cybersecurity. Specific research themes include Adversarial Learning, Forensic Ready, and Privacy Preserving IoT/CPS.</p> <p>The first three webinars (Dec 2020, Feb 2021, and April 2021) totaled 70+ attendees with each breakout sessions having approximately 20~25 active participants from across all three regions. The webinar series started with an introduction of the NSF 20-264 opportunity, which enables trliateral collaborations in a broad spectrum of research areas, including the specific emphasis of this project - IoT/CPS Cybersecurity. The active discussions have led to sharing of expertise, research challenges, and ideas to foster transatlantic collaborations.</p> <p>The fourth webinar was a student-centered symposium, co-located with RIT's CyberVSR Symposium in August 2021. There was a total of 28 student presenters, whereas 10 were from Ireland and Northern Ireland regions and 7 were from US, and the remaining 11 were from other countries as part of CyberVSR program. There were about 70+ participants duringthe virtual event.</p> <p>The fifth webinar was hosted in November 2021 and consisted of 3 technical presentations, one from each of the three regions. A total of about 20 participants were in this webinar.</p> <p>The final culminating "Transatlantic Workshop on IoT/CPS Cybersecurity" were in Dublin, Ireland from October 20~21, 2022, and had a total of 55 attendees, including 17 from the United States, 21 from Ireland, and 11 from Ireland, along with other guests. A trilateral community of researchers has been established with ongoing collaborations and international visits.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Shanchieh&nbsp;J&nbsp;Yang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project hosted a total of 5 webinars and 1 in-person workshop between fall 2020 to fall 2022. The overarching goal of the webinars and workshop is to foster trilateral research collaborations between the United States, Ireland, and Northern Ireland, in the area of IoT/CPS Cybersecurity. Specific research themes include Adversarial Learning, Forensic Ready, and Privacy Preserving IoT/CPS.  The first three webinars (Dec 2020, Feb 2021, and April 2021) totaled 70+ attendees with each breakout sessions having approximately 20~25 active participants from across all three regions. The webinar series started with an introduction of the NSF 20-264 opportunity, which enables trliateral collaborations in a broad spectrum of research areas, including the specific emphasis of this project - IoT/CPS Cybersecurity. The active discussions have led to sharing of expertise, research challenges, and ideas to foster transatlantic collaborations.  The fourth webinar was a student-centered symposium, co-located with RIT's CyberVSR Symposium in August 2021. There was a total of 28 student presenters, whereas 10 were from Ireland and Northern Ireland regions and 7 were from US, and the remaining 11 were from other countries as part of CyberVSR program. There were about 70+ participants duringthe virtual event.  The fifth webinar was hosted in November 2021 and consisted of 3 technical presentations, one from each of the three regions. A total of about 20 participants were in this webinar.  The final culminating "Transatlantic Workshop on IoT/CPS Cybersecurity" were in Dublin, Ireland from October 20~21, 2022, and had a total of 55 attendees, including 17 from the United States, 21 from Ireland, and 11 from Ireland, along with other guests. A trilateral community of researchers has been established with ongoing collaborations and international visits.       Last Modified: 08/12/2023       Submitted by: Shanchieh J Yang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
