<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop:  Aligning AI and U.S. Advanced Manufacturing Competitiveness]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98280.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98280</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Kramer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bkramer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925348</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Workshop on Aligning AI and U.S. Advanced Manufacturing Competitiveness will convene the advanced manufacturing research and practitioner communities, relevant companies, federal agencies and national laboratories and the Manufacturing USA Institutes and experts in artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML) applications, information technology, and computer science to comprehensively assess the role of AI in manufacturing competitiveness. The workshop, held under the auspices of the Subcommittee on Advanced Manufacturing and the Subcommittee on Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence of the National Science and Technology Council, seizes on a moment of opportunity that results from the converging effects of the accelerating digital transformation of the global manufacturing industry, major global competitiveness drivers for both advanced manufacturing and AI/ML, and the sustained impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on manufacturing supply chains.  When taken together, there emerges a need to: accelerate a U.S. manufacturing consensus on resilient manufacturing as a priority, address how the digital transformation of manufacturing shapes and is shaped by that transformation, and focus national attention on AI/ML technologies in the context of the nation’s manufacturing priorities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will be a professionally-managed, virtual teleconference that will emphasize the following manufacturing priorities related to digitalization: manufacturing ecosystem and supply chain restructuring, connectedness, visibility, interoperability, and agility in preparing for and responding to global and national disruptions; greater performance and precision in advanced process and machine operations as key assets in resilient manufacturing ecosystems; a safe and healthy, broadly-skilled, and data-savvy workforce that can be more flexibly deployed; and industry data flow and exchange, cyber opportunity, and national cyber and data security.   The workshop will generate a cross-stakeholder consensus on what roles AI has and can have in improving U.S. manufacturing competitiveness and promoting collaboration by the advanced manufacturing and AI/ML research communities in formulating a national strategy that encompasses the workforce, technology and implementation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049670</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jdavis@oarc.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000299877</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951405</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[BOX 951405, 2333C Murphy]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7484</Code>
<Text>IIS Special Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>075Z</Code>
<Text>Artificial Intelligence (AI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>079Z</Code>
<Text>Machine Learning Theory</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~98280</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Workshop 1, titled "Aligning Artificial Intelligence and U.S. Advanced Manufacturing Competitiveness," was held on December 2020 as an NSF/NIST sponsored event, hosted by UCLA, and as the first of a three-workshop Symposium to address the U.S. Strategy for Resilient Manufacturing Ecosystems through AI. <span>Workshop 1 benefitted from the experience of over 90 experts in manufacturing and AI from academia, industry, and government and was unique in bringing together communities that have not extensively interacted.&nbsp;</span>The Workshop 1 report, released in March 2021&nbsp;</span>identified AI for Industry-Wide Data Sharing, AI for the Factory Floor, AI for Discovery of Capabilities and Solutions, and AI for Building Resilient Supply Chains, as the priority areas of AI opportunity for manufacturing competitiveness and joint AI and manufacturing R&amp;D. A key outcome from Workshop 1 was the specificiation of an implementation framework in which these four areas form a system of programs, interwoven with development principles, to drive demand for digitalization and the adoption of AI. &nbsp;</p> <p>Workshop participants were enthusiastic about both the near term and long term benefits of applying AI to manufacturing. These included far better use of industry data and scaled use of domain knowlege throughout the industry, noting that AI is not a replacement for domain knowledge. They identified priority opportunities, challenges, and collaboration points for accelerating the implementation of AI in manufacturing, and used the span of economic value as the topmost driver: market share, productivity, energy and material consumption, national security, and climate, environmental, and ecosystem impacts. A key observation was that manufacturing has derived little benefit from the&nbsp;<em>network effects</em>&nbsp;that have transformed other industries, even though the potential is high for&nbsp;<em>AI</em>,&nbsp;<em>machine learning, predictive modeling, and networked</em>&nbsp;<em>data centric analytics</em>&nbsp;and solutions to enable such a transformation.</p> <p>In assessing AI in manufacturing, it was noted that current AI applications are almost&nbsp;<em>exclusively</em>&nbsp;for machine and operational units, i.e. component levels within individual company operations, and rarely extend&nbsp;to line operations, intracompany systems, or intercompany supply chains. This observation focused workshop discussions on the&nbsp;transformational opportunities afforded by the application of AI methods and tools to support manufacturing operations beyond the component level. The participants stressed that, with broad industry adoption, AI and machine learning systems have the potential to transform the prevailing manufacturing business model, which emphasizes the proprietary nature of data. This transformation, which is essential for the successful implementation of AI solutions, can also be enabled by AI tools for data privacy, discovery, and reuse, essentially using AI to enable AI.&nbsp;&nbsp;The workshop identified seven key principles for realizing full value and wide adoption of AI in manufacturing:&nbsp;</p> <p>1) The entire manufacturing industry, including small, medium, and large manufacturers, suppliers, and R&amp;D collaborators, must extend digital transformation to the industry level. There are significant benefits to adopting highly connected industry business practices that involve shared data and knowhow, in addition to scaling the customary contractual exchange of data.&nbsp;</p> <p>2) AI must focus on untapped opportunities within and across all operations, but within the span of economic benefit. Access to routine industry data and the right tools for putting these data to use for economic benefit is the key requirement for wide industry adoption of AI.</p> <p>3) There is a need for appropriate methods and tools to provide assurances that critical proprietary data will be protected, while allowing noncritical data to be shared for the training of AI systems. Such tools must provide the guarantees on security and control for data access that manufacturing companies require for the full benefit of network effects to be realized on a national scale.</p> <p>4) Agreements and de facto standards for data formats, timing, and sharing will be needed, along with the implementation tools needed to apply them to produce value.</p> <p>5) Important lessons for building industry-wide data and cross-industry modeling networks critical for AI can be learned from other industries that have gained competitive advantages by doing so.&nbsp;</p> <p>6) AI tools that link supply chains can improve manufacturing resilience by increasing supply chain visibility and coordination, decreasing duplication of productive capacity, improving productivity management across companies, and providing individual manufacturers with the flexibility to re-tool and re-specify operations to change product type and production volume.</p> <p>7) AI tools and networked, data centric modeling approaches are actively researched and rapidly evolving, making it difficult to predict the skills that tomorrow's manufacturing workforce will need, but we cannot wait for tomorrow's tools to be available. There is an urgent need to configure educational programs that provide the foundational knowledge that today's engineers and technicians will need, using existing data centric methods as a bridge to the AI tools of the future.&nbsp;</p> <p><span>Workshop 2 builds on Workshop 1 to prioritize </span>R&amp;D strategies, determine their integration into an industry-wide adoption strategy, and scale the adoption of AI for manufacturing competitiveness.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2021<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Davis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2049670/2049670_10700537_1640276092970_AIImplementationFramework--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2049670/2049670_10700537_1640276092970_AIImplementationFramework--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AI Implementation Framework"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2049670/2049670_10700537_1640276092970_AIImplementationFramework--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AI Implementation Framework"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">AI Implementation Framework for the Adoption of AI in Manufacturing</div> <div class="imageCredit">NSF/NIST Sponsored Workshop 1</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Davis</div> <div class="imageTitle">AI Implementation Framework</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Workshop 1, titled "Aligning Artificial Intelligence and U.S. Advanced Manufacturing Competitiveness," was held on December 2020 as an NSF/NIST sponsored event, hosted by UCLA, and as the first of a three-workshop Symposium to address the U.S. Strategy for Resilient Manufacturing Ecosystems through AI. Workshop 1 benefitted from the experience of over 90 experts in manufacturing and AI from academia, industry, and government and was unique in bringing together communities that have not extensively interacted. The Workshop 1 report, released in March 2021 identified AI for Industry-Wide Data Sharing, AI for the Factory Floor, AI for Discovery of Capabilities and Solutions, and AI for Building Resilient Supply Chains, as the priority areas of AI opportunity for manufacturing competitiveness and joint AI and manufacturing R&amp;D. A key outcome from Workshop 1 was the specificiation of an implementation framework in which these four areas form a system of programs, interwoven with development principles, to drive demand for digitalization and the adoption of AI.    Workshop participants were enthusiastic about both the near term and long term benefits of applying AI to manufacturing. These included far better use of industry data and scaled use of domain knowlege throughout the industry, noting that AI is not a replacement for domain knowledge. They identified priority opportunities, challenges, and collaboration points for accelerating the implementation of AI in manufacturing, and used the span of economic value as the topmost driver: market share, productivity, energy and material consumption, national security, and climate, environmental, and ecosystem impacts. A key observation was that manufacturing has derived little benefit from the network effects that have transformed other industries, even though the potential is high for AI, machine learning, predictive modeling, and networked data centric analytics and solutions to enable such a transformation.  In assessing AI in manufacturing, it was noted that current AI applications are almost exclusively for machine and operational units, i.e. component levels within individual company operations, and rarely extend to line operations, intracompany systems, or intercompany supply chains. This observation focused workshop discussions on the transformational opportunities afforded by the application of AI methods and tools to support manufacturing operations beyond the component level. The participants stressed that, with broad industry adoption, AI and machine learning systems have the potential to transform the prevailing manufacturing business model, which emphasizes the proprietary nature of data. This transformation, which is essential for the successful implementation of AI solutions, can also be enabled by AI tools for data privacy, discovery, and reuse, essentially using AI to enable AI.  The workshop identified seven key principles for realizing full value and wide adoption of AI in manufacturing:   1) The entire manufacturing industry, including small, medium, and large manufacturers, suppliers, and R&amp;D collaborators, must extend digital transformation to the industry level. There are significant benefits to adopting highly connected industry business practices that involve shared data and knowhow, in addition to scaling the customary contractual exchange of data.   2) AI must focus on untapped opportunities within and across all operations, but within the span of economic benefit. Access to routine industry data and the right tools for putting these data to use for economic benefit is the key requirement for wide industry adoption of AI.  3) There is a need for appropriate methods and tools to provide assurances that critical proprietary data will be protected, while allowing noncritical data to be shared for the training of AI systems. Such tools must provide the guarantees on security and control for data access that manufacturing companies require for the full benefit of network effects to be realized on a national scale.  4) Agreements and de facto standards for data formats, timing, and sharing will be needed, along with the implementation tools needed to apply them to produce value.  5) Important lessons for building industry-wide data and cross-industry modeling networks critical for AI can be learned from other industries that have gained competitive advantages by doing so.   6) AI tools that link supply chains can improve manufacturing resilience by increasing supply chain visibility and coordination, decreasing duplication of productive capacity, improving productivity management across companies, and providing individual manufacturers with the flexibility to re-tool and re-specify operations to change product type and production volume.  7) AI tools and networked, data centric modeling approaches are actively researched and rapidly evolving, making it difficult to predict the skills that tomorrow's manufacturing workforce will need, but we cannot wait for tomorrow's tools to be available. There is an urgent need to configure educational programs that provide the foundational knowledge that today's engineers and technicians will need, using existing data centric methods as a bridge to the AI tools of the future.   Workshop 2 builds on Workshop 1 to prioritize R&amp;D strategies, determine their integration into an industry-wide adoption strategy, and scale the adoption of AI for manufacturing competitiveness.                Last Modified: 12/23/2021       Submitted by: James F Davis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
