<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER: The Arithmetic of Fields and the Complexity of Algebraic Structures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/31/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8984.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8984</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The PI will investigate a number of problems, using homotopy aspects of arithmetic geometry, that may be thought of as generalizations of the period-index problem for the Brauer group, the u-invariant problem for quadratic forms, and the Hasse principle for a quadratic form over a number field. The project will focus on the interaction of field arithmetic and the complexity of algebraic structures, such as quadratic forms, Brauer groups, linear algebraic groups and homogeneous varieties. The project represents a set of techniques and experiments designed to capitalize on the new topological perspective in the study of algebraic structures. It will aim to support and further the interactions of these areas with arithmetic algebraic geometry, algebraic topology and the algebraic geometry of stacks and moduli.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The relevance of these topics, rooted in algebra within pure mathematics, is exhibited by their connections to a wide range of other subjects in recent years. Besides their many ties to other branches of mathematics, the algebraic structures at the core of this proposal have also found applications within diverse areas from theoretical physics to wireless communications.  The research component of this project will seek to capitalize on and enrich our understanding of the many connections to other areas of study in order to gain more leverage in understanding these fundamental and important algebraic structures.  The project's outreach components include funding conferences aimed at establishing a community inclusive of graduate students and young researchers, undergraduate colloquium aimed at increasing interest in mathematics, and facilitating a mentoring program for high school students in northeast Georgia interested in mathematics. It will also pursue strategies towards improving the mentoring and retention of graduate students in mathematics.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049180</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Krashen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Krashen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dkrashen@sas.upenn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000466757</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 RUTGERS PLZ</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001617DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~8984</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF grant supported a number of activities: research support for the PI and multiple graduate students, partial funding for conferences particularly aimed at fostering connections between senior and junior researchers, funding for the UGA MathCamp summer day camp program for high school students near Athens, Georgia. In addition, the grant gave travel support to facilitate a number of collaborations between the PI and other researchers.</p> <p>During the grant period, the PI and his collaborators obtained various new results comprising roughly 14 papers, on topics related the complexity of algebraic structures and field arithmetic, such as the development of new local-global principles, results on the behavior of quadratic forms (the u-invariant problem), and central simple algebras and Galois cohomology (the period-index and symbol length problems).</p> <p>The grant also played a critical role in supporting the research of 8 of the PI's graduate students, 6 of whom graduated during the award period, and two others still progressing towards their degrees. Of the graduated students, three are at tenure track positions, with one already having obtained tenure. Another is currently in a postdoctoral position, and the other two are working in industry.</p> <p>During the summers of 2012, 2015, and 2018, the grant gave partial support to the "Brauer Group at Pingree Park" conference, which has been running every 2-3 years for roughly 40 years. Traditionally the conference has aimed to facilitate interaction between young and established researchers involved with division algebras, the Brauer group, and related structures. The grant funding allowed this conference to continue to thrive and grow, and by providing support to younger researchers in particular, expanded the reach by making it possible for a wider group of participants to come.</p> <p>During the summers of 2013, 2014, 2016 and 2018 the grant funded (with help from the University of Georgia at Athens mathematics department) week long MathCamp for high school students in the greater Athens area in Georgia (http://torsor.github.io/mathcamp/). This was a small but very successful program, designed and co-directed by the PI and Prof. Angela Gibney. A typical camp involved about 25 high school students, 5 faculty from UGA and elsewhere, 5-6 UGA graduate students, and 5-6 UGA undergraduates. This was open to a students regardless of backgrounds, was very low cost for them (a cost of roughly $30 for the week for snacks and t-shirts). The participants were a diverse, friendly and highly motivated group, and the projects, including such things as braids, knots, cryptography, epidemiology, gerrymandering, graph theory and logic.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Krashen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF grant supported a number of activities: research support for the PI and multiple graduate students, partial funding for conferences particularly aimed at fostering connections between senior and junior researchers, funding for the UGA MathCamp summer day camp program for high school students near Athens, Georgia. In addition, the grant gave travel support to facilitate a number of collaborations between the PI and other researchers.  During the grant period, the PI and his collaborators obtained various new results comprising roughly 14 papers, on topics related the complexity of algebraic structures and field arithmetic, such as the development of new local-global principles, results on the behavior of quadratic forms (the u-invariant problem), and central simple algebras and Galois cohomology (the period-index and symbol length problems).  The grant also played a critical role in supporting the research of 8 of the PI's graduate students, 6 of whom graduated during the award period, and two others still progressing towards their degrees. Of the graduated students, three are at tenure track positions, with one already having obtained tenure. Another is currently in a postdoctoral position, and the other two are working in industry.  During the summers of 2012, 2015, and 2018, the grant gave partial support to the "Brauer Group at Pingree Park" conference, which has been running every 2-3 years for roughly 40 years. Traditionally the conference has aimed to facilitate interaction between young and established researchers involved with division algebras, the Brauer group, and related structures. The grant funding allowed this conference to continue to thrive and grow, and by providing support to younger researchers in particular, expanded the reach by making it possible for a wider group of participants to come.  During the summers of 2013, 2014, 2016 and 2018 the grant funded (with help from the University of Georgia at Athens mathematics department) week long MathCamp for high school students in the greater Athens area in Georgia (http://torsor.github.io/mathcamp/). This was a small but very successful program, designed and co-directed by the PI and Prof. Angela Gibney. A typical camp involved about 25 high school students, 5 faculty from UGA and elsewhere, 5-6 UGA graduate students, and 5-6 UGA undergraduates. This was open to a students regardless of backgrounds, was very low cost for them (a cost of roughly $30 for the week for snacks and t-shirts). The participants were a diverse, friendly and highly motivated group, and the projects, including such things as braids, knots, cryptography, epidemiology, gerrymandering, graph theory and logic.       Last Modified: 12/29/2021       Submitted by: Daniel Krashen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
