<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Firm Relocation as Environmental Policy: Impacts on Agglomeration and the Environment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As countries industrialize, trade-offs between promoting economic growth and negative environment effects such as pollution and emissions become more binding. Because environmental policies impact firm decisions, they provide a lens to test theories of firm interactions that contribute to our understanding of firm behavior. This research project will study the effects a policy which relocated firms located in densely urban areas to industrial locations  outside the city. The goal was to move polluting firms out of high population density areas so that they would affect fewer people. Because random drawings were held to assign plots at the new location to firms as industrial plots became available,  the randomization makes the firms that relocated earlier comparable to those that relocated later. This makes it possible to provide an improved understanding of how the presence of industrial activity at a variety of scales affects air quality and emissions in urban areas, workers’ choices of where to live. Additionally, the proposal develops a new method of inferring air pollution levels from historical high-resolution satellite images which can be helpful whenever direct measurements are not available.  This innovative design allows the researchers allows researchers to assess the impact of industrial policy on the environment. The results of this research will provide inputs into  environmental policy and thus establish the US as the global leader in environment research and policy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding aggregate and distributional consequences of environmental policies is important to inform policies that balance the growth-pollution trade-off. We use the randomized removal of firms from city centers at different times to assess neighborhood-level policy impacts on a range of outcomes such as agglomeration, entry and exit, environmental quality, and land values. A key input to the analysis is fine resolution air quality measures spanning a fifteen year period. The proposed research will use deep learning methods applied to satellite imagery to create pollution measures at a fine spatial and temporal resolution. Furthermore, conditional on a firm’s assigned plot being in one of four size categories, the specific plot that a firm allotted was also random. This generates random variation in firms’ neighbors, as well as in location characteristics such as proximity to infrastructure like roads. The project will estimate how different aspects of firm location impact firm outcomes and how these effects are heterogeneous depending on neighbors’ characteristics. In studies of agglomeration and density, truly experimental variation is almost entirely absent so that most identification is either quasi-experimental or model-based. This study is the first to conduct a joint experimental analysis of how firm density impacts environmental quality, firm outcomes, and agglomeration. The results of this research will provide inputs into environmental policy and thus establish the US as the global leader in environment research and policy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Namrata</FirstName>
<LastName>Kala</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Namrata Kala</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kala@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000784754</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Gechter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael D Gechter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mdg5396@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000835705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~249998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Firm location decisions are one of the most important decisions managers make, optimizing factors such as proximity to customers, suppliers, and useful information. At the same time, these decisions may have effects on local neighborhoods, by providing access to jobs, impacting environmental quality, and contributing to local economic activity. For this reason, numerous policies attempt to change location choices of firms, for instance, place-based policies that incentivize firms to locate in particular areas. The fact that firms choose their location based on factors we lack direct measurements of makes estimating the impact of firm presence on the local economy difficult. Policies that shock firm location decisions can help overcome this, but in many cases, may be bundled with other features -- for instance, place-based policies that incentivize firms to locate in certain areas often provide local infrastructure or tax benefits.</p> <p>In this project, we study a policy that is a common environmental policy tool in developing countries, namely firm relocation. These polices act as a form of ex-post zoning, moving existing firms operating in high-density areas to more remote locations. We study a specific environmental relocation policy that moved over 20,000 small firms operating within city limits in New Delhi to industrial areas outside the city over several years. A unique feature of this policy is that due to a shortage of industrial plots when relocation began, plot allotment was done via a series of lotteries between 2000 and 2005, with firms actually moving between 2006 and 2010.</p> <p>This generates random variation in firm presence over the time period, between neighborhoods with a greater number of firms receiving a plot earlier in the process, and those with a greater number of firms receiving a plot later in the process. Combining several data sources with administrative data on the relocation policy, we estimate the impact of firm presence on environmental quality (neighborhood-level fine particulate matter concentrations). The randomized removal of small-to-medium-sized firms from neighborhoods allows us to causally estimate their contribution to environmental outcomes, which is not feasible using standard methods that directly measure the emissions of specific plants. Since this size of firm predominates in developing countries, understanding their emission profile is key to informing policymakers on the potential effects of policies targeting them.&nbsp;</p> <p>We find that a one standard deviation increase in the proportion of firms in a neighborhood that had won a lottery by 2004 (about 18% of firms) reduces PM levels by about 1 microgram per cubic meter. However, relocation is very costly for the relocated firms. We are able to show how survival probabilities for relocated firms decrease in the distance they are relocated, underscoring the importance of firm&rsquo;s chosen location and the costs of being moved from that location. We find that relocation caused an increase in relocated firms' exit rate between 18 and 32 percentage points. Our cost-benefit analysis, which converts the reduction in PM levels to the statistical value of lives lost and compares this to costs associated with firm death, finds that the benefits outweigh the costs.</p> <p>Given that firms typically form industry clusters, how damaging was the policy&rsquo;s random assignment of plots to firms, which spread all industries evenly across industrial areas? We take advantage of the random assignment to identify the impact of different neighbor industrial compositions on a firm of any industry. This shows us that 1.6 percentage points of the effect of relocation on exit is attributable to the uniform random assignment of firms to plots. We show that an optimal assignment of firms to parts of industrial areas would eliminate this policy design effect on exit.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;D&nbsp;Gechter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Firm location decisions are one of the most important decisions managers make, optimizing factors such as proximity to customers, suppliers, and useful information. At the same time, these decisions may have effects on local neighborhoods, by providing access to jobs, impacting environmental quality, and contributing to local economic activity. For this reason, numerous policies attempt to change location choices of firms, for instance, place-based policies that incentivize firms to locate in particular areas. The fact that firms choose their location based on factors we lack direct measurements of makes estimating the impact of firm presence on the local economy difficult. Policies that shock firm location decisions can help overcome this, but in many cases, may be bundled with other features -- for instance, place-based policies that incentivize firms to locate in certain areas often provide local infrastructure or tax benefits.  In this project, we study a policy that is a common environmental policy tool in developing countries, namely firm relocation. These polices act as a form of ex-post zoning, moving existing firms operating in high-density areas to more remote locations. We study a specific environmental relocation policy that moved over 20,000 small firms operating within city limits in New Delhi to industrial areas outside the city over several years. A unique feature of this policy is that due to a shortage of industrial plots when relocation began, plot allotment was done via a series of lotteries between 2000 and 2005, with firms actually moving between 2006 and 2010.  This generates random variation in firm presence over the time period, between neighborhoods with a greater number of firms receiving a plot earlier in the process, and those with a greater number of firms receiving a plot later in the process. Combining several data sources with administrative data on the relocation policy, we estimate the impact of firm presence on environmental quality (neighborhood-level fine particulate matter concentrations). The randomized removal of small-to-medium-sized firms from neighborhoods allows us to causally estimate their contribution to environmental outcomes, which is not feasible using standard methods that directly measure the emissions of specific plants. Since this size of firm predominates in developing countries, understanding their emission profile is key to informing policymakers on the potential effects of policies targeting them.   We find that a one standard deviation increase in the proportion of firms in a neighborhood that had won a lottery by 2004 (about 18% of firms) reduces PM levels by about 1 microgram per cubic meter. However, relocation is very costly for the relocated firms. We are able to show how survival probabilities for relocated firms decrease in the distance they are relocated, underscoring the importance of firm’s chosen location and the costs of being moved from that location. We find that relocation caused an increase in relocated firms' exit rate between 18 and 32 percentage points. Our cost-benefit analysis, which converts the reduction in PM levels to the statistical value of lives lost and compares this to costs associated with firm death, finds that the benefits outweigh the costs.  Given that firms typically form industry clusters, how damaging was the policy’s random assignment of plots to firms, which spread all industries evenly across industrial areas? We take advantage of the random assignment to identify the impact of different neighbor industrial compositions on a firm of any industry. This shows us that 1.6 percentage points of the effect of relocation on exit is attributable to the uniform random assignment of firms to plots. We show that an optimal assignment of firms to parts of industrial areas would eliminate this policy design effect on exit.             Last Modified: 09/29/2023       Submitted by: Michael D Gechter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
