<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Integrative International Interventions: Militant Violence and Human Security in Contemporary Conflicts]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>158154.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>167154</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lee Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[International actors, such as international organizations, non-governmental organizations, as well as state actors, intervene in those internal conflicts in a variety of ways, altering the conflict dynamics with implications for human security. Under what conditions are international interventions effective in reducing militant violence? The integrative international interventions (Triple-i) project examines the humanitarian consequences of various international intervention policies in reducing militant violence. The issues of violence against civilians, violence against women, and violence against children are the center of the inquiry. The project has three objectives: 1) to identify intervention opportunities and challenges to human security in conflict zones, 2) to develop an integrative theory of international interventions for human security, and 3) to test and measure the efficacy of various measures dealing with militant violence around the world. The PIs collect data for the variety of international intervention efforts and militant group characteristics and analyze the patterns of approximately 1,200 militant groups’ violence in about 120 countries around the world between 1990 and 2020. The comprehensive and systematic assessment of costs, benefits, and associated risks of intervention measures is part of the analysis. Time-series intervention analysis will be used to evaluate the choice and efficacy of intervention measures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs develop an integrative framework to study the choice and efficacy of various international intervention measures, develops a categorization for the conditions of engaging militants, the implementation of a measurement strategy of militant adaptability, and a coding strategy for major international interventions.  Broader Impacts include a sharable database that will be available to academics and policy makers and training for undergraduate and graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2049443</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hyeran</FirstName>
<LastName>Jo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hyeran Jo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hyeranjo@polisci.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000535133</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 HARVEY MITCHELL PKY S STE 30</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF6XLNB4CDJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HH6VX5XDL284</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778434348</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4348 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>118Y</Code>
<Text>Security &amp; Preparedness</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~167154</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project improves our understanding of how the variety of international efforts reduce militant violence in conflict zones around the world. Militant violence is a significant problem with human security implications. The world has experienced 40-50 civil conflicts between 1990 and 2020. Many people in those conflicts often suffer killing and other forms of violence. Other parts of the world feel spillover effects in the form of refugee flows and economic disruptions. Understanding the opportunities and challenges of what the international community can do and cannot do is crucial.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With the goal of studying the ways to reduce militant violence in conflict zones, the project presents a study of international efforts in an integrated fashion. Thus far, previous studies looked at individual international measures, such as sanctions or peacekeeping, as if they are separate. Challenging that notion, this project 1) examines a comprehensive listing of international intervention efforts, ranging from economic and military measures to legal and diplomatic ones, 2) provides an integrative theory that can explain the employment and efficacy of various international measures in reducing the militant violence, and 3) collects and analyzes the dataset of international efforts to reduce militant violence for the past three decades, 1990-2020. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The key theoretical finding is encapsulated in the idea of tailoring-to-the-target. When international measures are employed with the understanding of the militant characteristics, they can have potential to succeed in reducing violence. For instance, economic or financial sanctions may not be efficacious in reducing violence when militant groups can find alternative ways of funding in an adaptive fashion. In some situations where militant groups are militarily started strong but losing battles, diplomatic solutions may work better with the help of peacekeeping forces that can provide a buffer. In other situations, militant groups that have close ties with the civilian population and governing experience present the possibility of humanitarian engagement, instead of other costly interventions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The finding also dovetails with the identification of the inherent limitation of the international community as an intervener. The collective action problems abound, given the diverse set of national interests and the nature of mandates in international and regional bodies. In addition, the difficulty of obtaining the following all three elements curtails international efforts: 1) the ability to enforce peace, 2) the unbiasedness toward warring parties, and 3) the consent from the host government. Navigating the trilemma sometimes results in intended consequences for external interveners in internal conflicts. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The integrative international interventions (3i) dataset is the key platform where the above theoretical expectations are tested. The dataset covers the sample of countries and militant groups spanning the past three decades, 1990-2020, and features military, diplomatic, economic, and legal measures, in addition to militant group characteristics. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project is well positioned to produce several broader impacts. The building and construction of the dataset contributed to the education and training of the scientific workforce. As well, the education experience as well as the finding well extends to other disciplines beyond international relations. Policy impacts are also expected as the PI engages policymakers in governments, international organizations, and non-governmental organizations working in the field of peacemaking and conflict resolution. The engagement is done via scholarly publications, conference presentations, and public-facing short pieces.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Hyeran&nbsp;Jo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project improves our understanding of how the variety of international efforts reduce militant violence in conflict zones around the world. Militant violence is a significant problem with human security implications. The world has experienced 40-50 civil conflicts between 1990 and 2020. Many people in those conflicts often suffer killing and other forms of violence. Other parts of the world feel spillover effects in the form of refugee flows and economic disruptions. Understanding the opportunities and challenges of what the international community can do and cannot do is crucial.     With the goal of studying the ways to reduce militant violence in conflict zones, the project presents a study of international efforts in an integrated fashion. Thus far, previous studies looked at individual international measures, such as sanctions or peacekeeping, as if they are separate. Challenging that notion, this project 1) examines a comprehensive listing of international intervention efforts, ranging from economic and military measures to legal and diplomatic ones, 2) provides an integrative theory that can explain the employment and efficacy of various international measures in reducing the militant violence, and 3) collects and analyzes the dataset of international efforts to reduce militant violence for the past three decades, 1990-2020.           The key theoretical finding is encapsulated in the idea of tailoring-to-the-target. When international measures are employed with the understanding of the militant characteristics, they can have potential to succeed in reducing violence. For instance, economic or financial sanctions may not be efficacious in reducing violence when militant groups can find alternative ways of funding in an adaptive fashion. In some situations where militant groups are militarily started strong but losing battles, diplomatic solutions may work better with the help of peacekeeping forces that can provide a buffer. In other situations, militant groups that have close ties with the civilian population and governing experience present the possibility of humanitarian engagement, instead of other costly interventions.     The finding also dovetails with the identification of the inherent limitation of the international community as an intervener. The collective action problems abound, given the diverse set of national interests and the nature of mandates in international and regional bodies. In addition, the difficulty of obtaining the following all three elements curtails international efforts: 1) the ability to enforce peace, 2) the unbiasedness toward warring parties, and 3) the consent from the host government. Navigating the trilemma sometimes results in intended consequences for external interveners in internal conflicts.            The integrative international interventions (3i) dataset is the key platform where the above theoretical expectations are tested. The dataset covers the sample of countries and militant groups spanning the past three decades, 1990-2020, and features military, diplomatic, economic, and legal measures, in addition to militant group characteristics.       The project is well positioned to produce several broader impacts. The building and construction of the dataset contributed to the education and training of the scientific workforce. As well, the education experience as well as the finding well extends to other disciplines beyond international relations. Policy impacts are also expected as the PI engages policymakers in governments, international organizations, and non-governmental organizations working in the field of peacemaking and conflict resolution. The engagement is done via scholarly publications, conference presentations, and public-facing short pieces.          Last Modified: 09/25/2023       Submitted by: Hyeran Jo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
