<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Microfluidic Corralling Technology for Progressive Sperm Separation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of sperm separation technology to improve the conventional assisted reproductive technologies such as in-vitro fertilization (IVF) and intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI), which suffer from lack of efficiency (30-40%) efficiency. The global IVF market size was valued at around $18.3 billion in 2019 and is expected to rise to $37.7 billion by 2027. This growth is expected based on the growth of infertility during the last decade. Therefore, the demands for IVF treatments and including sperm separation utilities are increasing as well. Moreover, gamete treatments are considered crucial towards the modification of the whole IVF process, and extraction of the sperm with the best quality increasingly attracts interest. Although the current methods are able to extract sperm with the purity of 30 to 40%, the control on sperm motility is missing. In addition, traditional methods are time and labor-intensive, and their natural need for external force makes them hazardous to the DNA content of the sperm. The proposed project will explore translation of a microfluidic platform for sperm separation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will optimize the key step of the IVF microfluidics platform, which is sperm selection. Ultimately, the goal is to minimize gamete manipulation and costs associated with IVF to improve gamete treatment and fertilization success. The proposed microfluidic technology is a passive and efficient way to separate motile and healthy sperm from dead and abnormal cells so that the separated sample exhibits 100% motility. Moreover, the control over the motility of the separated sperm in this technology makes it suitable for gamete treatment purposes, which is desired by IVF clinicians. The proposed design is a microchamber-based microfluidic platform that may separate progressive motile sperm from nonviable sperm and debris as well as trapped nonprogressive sperm in the microchambers. The platform is operated in a short period of time (&lt;10 min), without any prior sample preparation. This microfluidic platform may provide a facile solution for high-throughput collection of progressive sperm useful for assisted reproductive technologies while still benefiting from micron-scale physics that makes it suitable for fundamental research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050245</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alireza</FirstName>
<LastName>Abbaspourrad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alireza Abbaspourrad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Alireza@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836338</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148530001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcome Report</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project revolves around a groundbreaking technology called Microfluidic Corralling Technology for Progressive Sperm Separation, aimed at revolutionizing assisted reproductive technologies (ART) through precise control over in vitro fertilization (IVF) processes. This technology has the potential to improve fertility treatment outcomes, benefitting couples striving to conceive. The project encompasses both intellectual merits, as it advances scientific understanding, and broader impacts, as it addresses pressing societal concerns.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>The project's goals underscore its intellectual significance. By delving into the pain points experienced by both ART clinics and patients, the team seeks to refine the value propositions of the proposed technology. This involves an assessment of the current chip's design and a reevaluation of the developed chip's design for sperm separation and IVF-on-a-chip, aligning it with the input received from clinics. Through extensive interviews with over 250 fertility stakeholders and work in actual fertility clinics, the project taps into valuable insights from medical professionals, including doctors, nurses, embryologists, and andrologists. The interdisciplinary nature of this collaboration, merging engineering, biology, and fertility, contributes to its intellectual richness.</p> <p>Moreover, the exploration of international markets expands the project's scope beyond national borders, enriching its global perspective. The team's in-depth understanding of IVF and ICSI procedures through visiting fertility clinics, coupled with the publication of seven papers and several patents, showcases their commitment to advancing knowledge in the field. The intellectual merit of this endeavor lies in its potential to refine and redefine established practices, offering innovative solutions to long-standing challenges in fertility treatments.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>The societal implications of this project extend beyond the realm of science and technology. Since the advent of IVF in 1978, millions of couples worldwide have benefitted from assisted reproductive technologies. However, challenges persist, including the financial burden of fertility treatments. The average cost of a single IVF cycle, ranging from $10,000 to $15,000, poses a significant obstacle for many hopeful parents. The project's promise of improved success rates and streamlined procedures has the potential to not only enhance outcomes but also alleviate the financial strain on couples seeking fertility treatments.</p> <p>Moreover, the project's emphasis on reducing manual manipulation in sperm selection and its potential to minimize DNA damage in sperm represent a leap towards safer and more effective fertility procedures. This aligns with the broader societal goal of ensuring the well-being of both parents and offspring, a fundamental consideration in reproductive technologies.</p> <p>The project's potential to democratize fertility treatments is a significant societal impact. By offering a customizable, user-friendly, and cost-effective solution, fertility clinics and hospitals can cater to a wider demographic, making IVF more accessible. The streamlined procedures can also save valuable time, reducing the emotional and psychological toll on couples undergoing fertility treatments.</p> <p>This endeavor also aligns with educational pursuits, expanding opportunities for infertility doctors, nurses, andrologists, embryologists, and a younger generation of scientists. The interdisciplinary nature of the project, bridging engineering and biology, enriches educational landscapes and promotes collaboration across disciplines. Furthermore, the potential applications for both human and precious animals (K9 dog, bovine, horse, etc.) fertility research underlines the project's multifaceted reach.</p> <p>In summary, the project centered around Microfluidic Corralling Technology for Progressive Sperm Separation encompasses both intellectual merit and broader impacts. Its goals, which involve refining technology through collaboration with fertility stakeholders, stand as a testament to its intellectual significance. The potential to improve fertility treatment outcomes, reduce costs, and streamline procedures extends the project's impact well beyond the scientific realm. By addressing the financial burden, democratizing access, and contributing to the well-being of families, the project resonates with societal needs and aspirations. Ultimately, this endeavor holds the promise of transforming the landscape of fertility treatments, making them more effective, accessible, and emotionally sustainable for countless individuals and couples worldwide.</p> <p>In the end, the team successfully received the STTR Phase I award to continue their successful experiences with both regional and national I-corps.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Alireza&nbsp;Abbaspourrad</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcome Report     The project revolves around a groundbreaking technology called Microfluidic Corralling Technology for Progressive Sperm Separation, aimed at revolutionizing assisted reproductive technologies (ART) through precise control over in vitro fertilization (IVF) processes. This technology has the potential to improve fertility treatment outcomes, benefitting couples striving to conceive. The project encompasses both intellectual merits, as it advances scientific understanding, and broader impacts, as it addresses pressing societal concerns.     Intellectual Merit:  The project's goals underscore its intellectual significance. By delving into the pain points experienced by both ART clinics and patients, the team seeks to refine the value propositions of the proposed technology. This involves an assessment of the current chip's design and a reevaluation of the developed chip's design for sperm separation and IVF-on-a-chip, aligning it with the input received from clinics. Through extensive interviews with over 250 fertility stakeholders and work in actual fertility clinics, the project taps into valuable insights from medical professionals, including doctors, nurses, embryologists, and andrologists. The interdisciplinary nature of this collaboration, merging engineering, biology, and fertility, contributes to its intellectual richness.  Moreover, the exploration of international markets expands the project's scope beyond national borders, enriching its global perspective. The team's in-depth understanding of IVF and ICSI procedures through visiting fertility clinics, coupled with the publication of seven papers and several patents, showcases their commitment to advancing knowledge in the field. The intellectual merit of this endeavor lies in its potential to refine and redefine established practices, offering innovative solutions to long-standing challenges in fertility treatments.     Broader Impacts:  The societal implications of this project extend beyond the realm of science and technology. Since the advent of IVF in 1978, millions of couples worldwide have benefitted from assisted reproductive technologies. However, challenges persist, including the financial burden of fertility treatments. The average cost of a single IVF cycle, ranging from $10,000 to $15,000, poses a significant obstacle for many hopeful parents. The project's promise of improved success rates and streamlined procedures has the potential to not only enhance outcomes but also alleviate the financial strain on couples seeking fertility treatments.  Moreover, the project's emphasis on reducing manual manipulation in sperm selection and its potential to minimize DNA damage in sperm represent a leap towards safer and more effective fertility procedures. This aligns with the broader societal goal of ensuring the well-being of both parents and offspring, a fundamental consideration in reproductive technologies.  The project's potential to democratize fertility treatments is a significant societal impact. By offering a customizable, user-friendly, and cost-effective solution, fertility clinics and hospitals can cater to a wider demographic, making IVF more accessible. The streamlined procedures can also save valuable time, reducing the emotional and psychological toll on couples undergoing fertility treatments.  This endeavor also aligns with educational pursuits, expanding opportunities for infertility doctors, nurses, andrologists, embryologists, and a younger generation of scientists. The interdisciplinary nature of the project, bridging engineering and biology, enriches educational landscapes and promotes collaboration across disciplines. Furthermore, the potential applications for both human and precious animals (K9 dog, bovine, horse, etc.) fertility research underlines the project's multifaceted reach.  In summary, the project centered around Microfluidic Corralling Technology for Progressive Sperm Separation encompasses both intellectual merit and broader impacts. Its goals, which involve refining technology through collaboration with fertility stakeholders, stand as a testament to its intellectual significance. The potential to improve fertility treatment outcomes, reduce costs, and streamline procedures extends the project's impact well beyond the scientific realm. By addressing the financial burden, democratizing access, and contributing to the well-being of families, the project resonates with societal needs and aspirations. Ultimately, this endeavor holds the promise of transforming the landscape of fertility treatments, making them more effective, accessible, and emotionally sustainable for countless individuals and couples worldwide.  In the end, the team successfully received the STTR Phase I award to continue their successful experiences with both regional and national I-corps.           Last Modified: 09/11/2023       Submitted by: Alireza Abbaspourrad]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
