<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building STEM Teacher Capacity in Southeastern Tennessee]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Kim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924458</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to serve the national need for highly effective STEM teachers by developing a one-year Master of Arts in STEM Teaching degree program at Maryville College. This additional pathway to teaching licensure will address the needs of STEM majors who decide upon a teaching profession later in their college careers or even after graduation. Because of state licensure requirements, college students seeking teaching degrees are required to complete high credit-count coursework in both their primary STEM majors and in education. To do so in four years, most students begin on the traditional STEM education pathway, and their college coursework plans are prescriptive to ensure graduation within four years. The restrictions of this model can discourage transfer students as well as late deciders from pursuing teaching careers, as these students must often commit to at least two more years of study. The development and implementation of a Master of Arts in STEM teaching program aims to lower barriers for STEM majors to choose teaching as a profession.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During this project, Maryville College will partner with Blount County Public Schools, a neighboring high-need local education agency and four regional partners.  Regional partners include the Great Smoky Mountains Institute at Tremont, an environmental education center in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, the STEM Innovation Network of Tennessee, and the Little River Watershed Association.  As the overarching goal of this project is to develop a one-year Master of Arts in STEM Teaching degree program, the project has three major objectives.  One is to create a viable, attractive pathway for STEM majors from Maryville College and for transfer students from community colleges to pursue teacher licensure midway through their college careers.  A second objective is to create educational materials to raise awareness of the new master’s program among Maryville College STEM students, regional STEM graduates, community college students, and potential professional partners with employees who may be interested in teaching.  The third objective is to forge partnerships with several regional organizations to develop a recruitment pipeline of STEM professionals who want to change careers.  The project also aims to provide professional development opportunities for undergraduate students and Master of Arts in STEM Teaching students through internships and teaching-related field experiences. Project evaluation will provide an opportunity to analyze the successes and challenges in developing and launching the proposed program, yielding valuable data for future program innovations at Maryville and for other institutions planning fifth-year STEM MAT program implementation. This Capacity Building project is supported through the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce). The Noyce program supports talented STEM undergraduate majors and professionals to become effective K-12 STEM teachers and experienced, exemplary K-12 teachers to become STEM master teachers in high-need school districts. It also supports research on the persistence, retention, and effectiveness of K-12 STEM teachers in high-need school districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050248</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Gardner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cynthia C Gardner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cynthia.gardner@maryvillecollege.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805201</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Duncan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan C Duncan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Nathan.Duncan@maryvillecollege.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805199</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Ross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel J Ross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dan.ross@maryvillecollege.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805269</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Maryville College</Name>
<CityName>MARYVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>378045907</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659818167</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>502 E LAMAR ALEXANDER PKWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SML4TMRCDJL1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARYVILLE COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Maryville College]]></Name>
<CityName>Maryville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>378045907</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[502 E. Lamar Alexander Pkwy.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-e142bcf1-7fff-3bb9-968a-162337b060f0"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project, ?Building STEM Teacher Capacity in Southeastern Tennessee,? aimed to increase the numbers of effective secondary STEM educators through a new Master of Arts in Teaching (MAT) Secondary STEM degree program. Collaboration with regional STEM partners, such as the Great Smoky Mountain Institute at Tremont, TN STEM Innovation Network, Oak Ridge Laboratory, and TN State Parks, resulted in extracurricular components of the MAT STEM program that equipped candidates with skills to plan and facilitate integrated STEM learning.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The new MAT degree forged collaborations between Maryville College (MC) Education and STEM faculty, Admissions, and Marketing who worked together to design approaches that invite STEM majors to consider teaching as a career option. As the first graduate program at MC, targeted marketing materials were developed for the MAT degree among four constituencies: current MC STEM students, STEM graduates from area colleges and universities, employees at area STEM-related entities, and career changers with a STEM background. Informational flyers were created and distributed in high schools, community colleges, businesses, and the local Chamber of Commerce. Billboards, radio spots, and Facebook ads were designed and placed to reach a broader audience. Early Entry to the MAT degree was promoted at informational sessions held during MC Open House events and at regional College Fairs.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Analysis of Facebook ads were ongoing and showed they reached 7,292 people and resulted in 94 clicks on the post. The ads targeted people aged 25-66 who were in college or a college graduate in STEM fields. A survey to assess MC STEM students? exposure to the marketing materials is being developed and will be deployed in fall 2022. Likewise, candidate?s implementation of integrated STEM using strategies learned during extracurricular components will be measured during their year-long internship in a secondary school classroom.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The support from the NSF Robert Noyce Capacity Building grant allowed us to develop approaches and strategies to recruit for the first graduate program at MC, an MAT in Secondary STEM. The project advanced our knowledge and understanding about recruiting secondary STEM teachers, and designing a program to immerse candidates in evidence-based approaches to integrated STEM education. The targeted marketing campaign will continue to grow and raise awareness of the degree program, which will increase the number of vitally important secondary STEM teachers in Southeast Tennessee.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Cynthia&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gardner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This project, ?Building STEM Teacher Capacity in Southeastern Tennessee,? aimed to increase the numbers of effective secondary STEM educators through a new Master of Arts in Teaching (MAT) Secondary STEM degree program. Collaboration with regional STEM partners, such as the Great Smoky Mountain Institute at Tremont, TN STEM Innovation Network, Oak Ridge Laboratory, and TN State Parks, resulted in extracurricular components of the MAT STEM program that equipped candidates with skills to plan and facilitate integrated STEM learning.  The new MAT degree forged collaborations between Maryville College (MC) Education and STEM faculty, Admissions, and Marketing who worked together to design approaches that invite STEM majors to consider teaching as a career option. As the first graduate program at MC, targeted marketing materials were developed for the MAT degree among four constituencies: current MC STEM students, STEM graduates from area colleges and universities, employees at area STEM-related entities, and career changers with a STEM background. Informational flyers were created and distributed in high schools, community colleges, businesses, and the local Chamber of Commerce. Billboards, radio spots, and Facebook ads were designed and placed to reach a broader audience. Early Entry to the MAT degree was promoted at informational sessions held during MC Open House events and at regional College Fairs.  Analysis of Facebook ads were ongoing and showed they reached 7,292 people and resulted in 94 clicks on the post. The ads targeted people aged 25-66 who were in college or a college graduate in STEM fields. A survey to assess MC STEM students? exposure to the marketing materials is being developed and will be deployed in fall 2022. Likewise, candidate?s implementation of integrated STEM using strategies learned during extracurricular components will be measured during their year-long internship in a secondary school classroom.  The support from the NSF Robert Noyce Capacity Building grant allowed us to develop approaches and strategies to recruit for the first graduate program at MC, an MAT in Secondary STEM. The project advanced our knowledge and understanding about recruiting secondary STEM teachers, and designing a program to immerse candidates in evidence-based approaches to integrated STEM education. The targeted marketing campaign will continue to grow and raise awareness of the degree program, which will increase the number of vitally important secondary STEM teachers in Southeast Tennessee.               Last Modified: 06/27/2022       Submitted by: Cynthia C Gardner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
