<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building Capacity for Assuring High Quality, Licensed Computer Science Teachers across Hawai’i]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74940.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74940</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bonnie Green</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bongreen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924386</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to serve the national need of increasing the number of qualified and licensed computer science teachers. The state of Hawai‘i, a hub for technologically innovation in the Pacific, offers computer science in all public high schools throughout the state. As more elementary, middle, and high school computer science courses are established, an increase is needed in the number of qualified, licensed computer science teachers. The project seeks to provide a framework for licensure in computer science education for college students majoring in computer science or mathematics. The project team will determine critical components needed in a culturally responsive computer science curriculum in a state that has a majority of minority students. With its established online learning infrastructure, the university intends to initially develop a curriculum that can be accessed online or face-to-face, which may increase access to the certificate program by removing the barrier of commuting to the Honolulu-based campus. The project also focuses on building capacity for future recruitment and retention that will allow successful statewide alliances to be scaled up for broader impact.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project at the University of Hawai’i at Manoa, a public teaching and research university, will partner with the Hawai’i Department of Education, the sole school district in the state of Hawai’i. The project goal is to build capacity to provide a pathway for computer science and mathematics majors to obtain licensure to teach computer science in K-12 through developing the infrastructure for a five-course computer science education certificate program. It is the intent of this project to increase content knowledge, pedagogical content knowledge, culturally sustaining knowledge, and pedagogical practices to align with the K-12 computer science teaching standards. The knowledge gained through this project may guide future research and interventions designed to enhance individual aspirations and capacity of underrepresented groups to pursue computer science teaching. The project includes an advisory board of content experts, education partners, industry partners, teacher education faculty experts, and computer science faculty experts.  This Board will evaluate the development of the new teacher preparation program to determine if it is sound in both content and context for Hawai‘i. The resulting curriculum and development process will be shared at local and national education conferences. This Capacity Building project is supported through the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce). The Noyce program supports talented STEM undergraduate majors and professionals to become effective K-12 STEM teachers and experienced, exemplary K-12 teachers to become STEM master teachers in high-need school districts. It also supports research on the persistence, retention, and effectiveness of K-12 STEM teachers in high-need school districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050630</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael-Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Ogawa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael-Brian Ogawa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ogawam@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000560076</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Crosby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha E Crosby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[crosby@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000417932</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alethea</FirstName>
<LastName>Serna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alethea K Serna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kserna@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thanh Truc</FirstName>
<LastName>Nguyen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thanh Truc T Nguyen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nguyen@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000073130</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2425 CAMPUS RD SINCLAIR RM 1</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NSCKLFSSABF2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1776 University Avenue WA I-101]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~74940</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">The Building Capacity for Assuring High Quality, License Computer Science Teachers Across Hawai&lsquo;i project was a 10-month $75K National Science Foundation (NSF) project. The project was extended at no cost to 22 months due to the COVID-19 pandemic. The NSF grant (2050630) was a Robert Noyce Capacity Building project at the University of Hawai&lsquo;i at M&#257;noa (UHM) in partnership with the Hawai&lsquo;i Department of Education (HIDOE).&nbsp;The project's primary goal was to build institutional capacity to produce highly skilled and knowledgeable K&ndash;12 computer science teachers in the HIDOE, which serves about 85% of the school children in Hawai&lsquo;i across six islands. The project team developed the beginning skeleton of a future computer science education certificate program that will lead towards teacher licensure in computer science, including those who are pursuing their primary bachelor degrees in computer science or a related field.</p> <p>Recognizing the importance of computer skills to prepare students for college, community, and career opportunities, the HIDOE offers at least one computer science course in each high school beginning in the 2020&ndash;2021 school year. Spurred by the passing of Act 51(HRS 302A-323) in 2018 by the Hawai&lsquo;i State Legislature, which requires a statewide kindergarten through twelfth grade computer science curriculum plan by the 2021&ndash;2022 school year, the HIDOE is experiencing a high need for computer science teachers. In SY 2019&ndash;20, there were 170 teachers teaching a computer science or computer science related course across the 257 public schools in the state. At the time of the start of this project, only 53 of the 170 computer science teachers were licensed in science, engineering, technology, mathematics (STEM), STEM, or CTE and hold an Every Student Succeeds Act (ESSA) highly qualified designation; twelve were licensed in computer science. As of December 2022, Hawai&lsquo;i was also facing a new Act 158&nbsp;(SB 242) mandate to have computer science in all elementary schools by 2025.</p> <p>The central goal of this project was to develop the infrastructure for a computer science education certificate program since no teacher education program in computer science education existed in the state of Hawai&lsquo;i. The HIDOE Computer Science team partnered with education and information computer science faculty at UHM to review and start the redesign of both information computer science and education courses towards an overall framework for the certificate program. In addition to the quality of the computer science education, of utmost importance to the effort was the consideration that the CS education program was culturally responsive in a state that has a majority of minority students.&nbsp;</p> <p>UHM will continue to obtain input about the needs of students Hawai&lsquo;i public school teachers who, despite the lack of a CS teacher education program, have obtained CS licensure. With its established online learning infrastructure and once approved by the UHM Faculty Senate, UHM will develop a curriculum that can be accessed online or face-to-face, which may increase access to the certificate program by removing the barrier of commuting to the Honolulu-based campus. The project will also continue to build capacity for future recruitment and retention that will allow successful statewide alliances to be scaled up for broader impact and a&nbsp;community college preservice teacher education program for CS professionals who may wish to change careers, as well as to promote transfer of community college CS majors into an existing university-based preservice teacher education program.</p> <p>The HIDOE is a minority-serving district with 29% students of native Hawaiian ancestry and 88% overall minority enrollment. The project team is keenly aware of the majority minority state that is Hawai&lsquo;i and the need to develop programs that serve its multicultural community and the need to provide more equitable access for girls and other underrepresented minority students in computer science and STEM. This pursuit is the norm for the work of the university and K&ndash;12 public schools. Undergirding this project was the attention to inclusion strategies used to recruit girls and women into computer science to redefine the gendered symbolism of computer science. Also, this project team was committed to increasing the representation of Native Hawaiians in all STEM fields. The project team will continue to engage in research and interventions designed to enhance individual aspirations of girls and other underrepresented groups and capacity to pursue computer science and other technical careers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Thanh Truc&nbsp;T&nbsp;Nguyen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The Building Capacity for Assuring High Quality, License Computer Science Teachers Across Hawai‘i project was a 10-month $75K National Science Foundation (NSF) project. The project was extended at no cost to 22 months due to the COVID-19 pandemic. The NSF grant (2050630) was a Robert Noyce Capacity Building project at the University of Hawai‘i at M&#257;noa (UHM) in partnership with the Hawai‘i Department of Education (HIDOE). The project's primary goal was to build institutional capacity to produce highly skilled and knowledgeable K&ndash;12 computer science teachers in the HIDOE, which serves about 85% of the school children in Hawai‘i across six islands. The project team developed the beginning skeleton of a future computer science education certificate program that will lead towards teacher licensure in computer science, including those who are pursuing their primary bachelor degrees in computer science or a related field.  Recognizing the importance of computer skills to prepare students for college, community, and career opportunities, the HIDOE offers at least one computer science course in each high school beginning in the 2020&ndash;2021 school year. Spurred by the passing of Act 51(HRS 302A-323) in 2018 by the Hawai‘i State Legislature, which requires a statewide kindergarten through twelfth grade computer science curriculum plan by the 2021&ndash;2022 school year, the HIDOE is experiencing a high need for computer science teachers. In SY 2019&ndash;20, there were 170 teachers teaching a computer science or computer science related course across the 257 public schools in the state. At the time of the start of this project, only 53 of the 170 computer science teachers were licensed in science, engineering, technology, mathematics (STEM), STEM, or CTE and hold an Every Student Succeeds Act (ESSA) highly qualified designation; twelve were licensed in computer science. As of December 2022, Hawai‘i was also facing a new Act 158 (SB 242) mandate to have computer science in all elementary schools by 2025.  The central goal of this project was to develop the infrastructure for a computer science education certificate program since no teacher education program in computer science education existed in the state of Hawai‘i. The HIDOE Computer Science team partnered with education and information computer science faculty at UHM to review and start the redesign of both information computer science and education courses towards an overall framework for the certificate program. In addition to the quality of the computer science education, of utmost importance to the effort was the consideration that the CS education program was culturally responsive in a state that has a majority of minority students.   UHM will continue to obtain input about the needs of students Hawai‘i public school teachers who, despite the lack of a CS teacher education program, have obtained CS licensure. With its established online learning infrastructure and once approved by the UHM Faculty Senate, UHM will develop a curriculum that can be accessed online or face-to-face, which may increase access to the certificate program by removing the barrier of commuting to the Honolulu-based campus. The project will also continue to build capacity for future recruitment and retention that will allow successful statewide alliances to be scaled up for broader impact and a community college preservice teacher education program for CS professionals who may wish to change careers, as well as to promote transfer of community college CS majors into an existing university-based preservice teacher education program.  The HIDOE is a minority-serving district with 29% students of native Hawaiian ancestry and 88% overall minority enrollment. The project team is keenly aware of the majority minority state that is Hawai‘i and the need to develop programs that serve its multicultural community and the need to provide more equitable access for girls and other underrepresented minority students in computer science and STEM. This pursuit is the norm for the work of the university and K&ndash;12 public schools. Undergirding this project was the attention to inclusion strategies used to recruit girls and women into computer science to redefine the gendered symbolism of computer science. Also, this project team was committed to increasing the representation of Native Hawaiians in all STEM fields. The project team will continue to engage in research and interventions designed to enhance individual aspirations of girls and other underrepresented groups and capacity to pursue computer science and other technical careers.       Last Modified: 04/30/2023       Submitted by: Thanh Truc T Nguyen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
