<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Developing a Program to Meet the Need for Prepared and Diverse STEM Teachers in Houston]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>122389.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>122389</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julio Soto</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgsoto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922973</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to serve the national need for increased numbers and diversity of highly qualified STEM teachers and educational leaders. Public schools face a shortage of STEM teachers, especially those with a STEM degree and who represent the diversity of the community they are serving. This shortage likely limits K-12 student STEM learning and may decrease their interest in pursuing further education in STEM.  As a result, the lack of highly qualified STEM teachers can affect representation of underrepresented minorities in the STEM workforce. Houston Baptist University is a four-year undergraduate Hispanic-Serving Institution in Houston, Texas, one of the most diverse cities in the nation. The demographics of students at the University mirror those of the K-12 students in the Houston area. The project includes collaboration with the Lone Star College System, a public community college system and the largest institution of higher learning in the Houston area.  Through this collaboration, the project aims to develop a program to prepare students to become K-12 teachers and leaders by obtaining both a Bachelor of Science degree in a STEM major and a Master of Education degree.  This capacity building project also aims to identify ways to retain these prepared and diverse educators in the Houston area. The development of this program will provide an alternate career route for STEM majors that is designed to address a shortage of prepared and diverse educators in the community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project at Houston Baptist University includes partnerships with the Lone Star College System and Houston Independent School District. The primary goal of this project is to develop and implement plans for a five-year BS/MEd pathway for STEM majors to earn their teaching licensure in a fifth-year program and eventually enter the Houston workforce as STEM teachers and education leaders.  Project aims include: 1) increasing capacity for student success in STEM; 2) expanding capacity of the Houston Baptist University curriculum for STEM teaching licensure; and 3) strengthening capacity for professional development for STEM educators. This project seeks to identify challenges that lead to the persistent shortage of qualified and diverse STEM educators in Houston Independent School District. The needs of college students pursuing a STEM degree, STEM teachers, and local K-12 school administrators will be assessed to determine capacity for continuous growth of the program. If successful, development of the program has the potential to serve as a model for understanding STEM teacher shortages in urban school districts serving predominantly underrepresented students. Findings also have potential to be applied to other institutions with student groups experiencing similar challenges preventing them from remaining in the community and serving through teaching. This Capacity Building project is supported through the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce). The Noyce program supports talented STEM undergraduate majors and professionals to become effective K-12 STEM teachers and experienced, exemplary K-12 teachers to become STEM master teachers in high-need school districts. It also supports research on the persistence, retention, and effectiveness of K-12 STEM teachers in high-need school districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/22/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050669</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Wingate</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hannah Wingate</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hwingate@hbu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000806098</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/28/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angelia</FirstName>
<LastName>Durand</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angelia C Durand</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adurand@hbu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836669</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/28/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angelia</FirstName>
<LastName>Durand</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angelia C Durand</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adurand@hbu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836669</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul W Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[plewis@hbu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000870859</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Houston Baptist University</Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>770743200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137747661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7502 FONDREN RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZD5ZBMA99Z25</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HOUSTON BAPTIST UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Houston Baptist University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770743204</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7502 Fondren Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~122389</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Developing a Program to Meet the Need for Prepared and Diverse STEM Teachers in Houston&nbsp;</em></p> <div> <div> <div> <p>Houston Baptist University (HBU) has a strong STEM program through the College of Science and Engineering (COSE), offering eight different B.S. degrees while the College of Education and Behavioral Science (COEBS) has a well-established Master of Education (MEd) program. In order to meet the need for highly qualified and diverse STEM educators in the high-need Houston&nbsp;Independent School District (HISD), HBU successly developed a five-year BS-MEd pathway for STEM majors to earn their teaching licensure in a fifth year and enter the Houston workforce as STEM teachers. Through this project, HBU aimed to 1) increase capacity for student success in STEM; 2) expand capacity of the HBU curriculum to better support the STEM teaching licensure; and 3) strengthen the capacity for professional development for STEM educators. The university?s partnership with the Lone Star College System (LSCS) and Houston Community College (HCC) was expanded to streamline the recruitment and transfer of students with an Associate?s degree in Science to HBU. Work was completed to&nbsp;ensure the university?s STEM curricula is aligned to facilitate completion of a STEM bachelor?s degree for all transfer students from the Community College partners. Needs assessment were conducted with focus groups of undergraduate STEM majors to assess their interest in becoming STEM educators, as well as with current K-12 STEM teachers and administrators from the HISD&nbsp;to identify their reasons for becoming teachers and challenges to persisting in the profession. The unique cultural needs of the Hispanic population in Houston was also evaluated to ensure that students participating in the HBU SEED program will have both scientific and cultural knowledge and experience to be successful in teaching STEM in Houston ISD  K-12 schools, ultimately increasing the numbers of Hispanic STEM teachers in HISD (29.7% Hispanic) to reflect that of the local community (44.8% Hispanic). &nbsp;With support from Noyce project PI, Dr. Tim Scott, at Texas A&amp;M University and his team the project team successfully expanded the collaboration with Community college transfer students and expanded the BS-MEd program infrastructure through the creation of a STEM Teaching Resource Lab at HBU and development of the 4+1 Degree Plan. With the project success, HBU will continue work on&nbsp;the long-term goal of increasing the number, quality and diversity of leaders in STEM education throughout Houston.&nbsp;</p> </div> <div> <p>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp; This projectl identified evidence-based challenges that lead to the persistent shortage of qualified and diverse STEM educators in HISD. The needs of college students pursuing a STEM degree, STEM educators, and local school administrators were assessed to determine capacity for continuous growth of a SEED program with development of 4+ 1 Degree Plans in Science and Mathematics in both 4-8 and 7-12 teacher certifiations. This program has reduced the barriers for STEM students to pursue a career in teaching through development and implementation of a pathway to facilitate the transition of STEM majors to serve as highly qualified K-12 STEM teachers. Partnerships were established with HBU STEM and Education faculty, Lone Star College System and Houston Community College.&nbsp;and Houston ISD&nbsp;schools. &nbsp;</p> </div> <div> <p>Broader Impact: This project served to identify and develop plans to&nbsp;meet&nbsp;the increased shortage of&nbsp;quality and diversity in STEM teachers in high-need schools in Houston Independent School District.&nbsp;HBU is uniquely situated to be able to make impactful improvements in STEM education in the Houston community because of the demographics that are mirrored in HBU and HISD students. The newly developed SEED program can serve as a model for developing STEM teachers to support shortages in other urban school districts like HISD that serve predominantly underrepresented students. The 4+1 or 2+2+1 developed degree pathways from AA to B.S. to M.Ed. can&nbsp;be applied at other institutions to support&nbsp;students'&nbsp;decisions to remain in the community and serve through teaching, specifically in STEM classrooms.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Angelia&nbsp;C&nbsp;Durand</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Developing a Program to Meet the Need for Prepared and Diverse STEM Teachers in Houston      Houston Baptist University (HBU) has a strong STEM program through the College of Science and Engineering (COSE), offering eight different B.S. degrees while the College of Education and Behavioral Science (COEBS) has a well-established Master of Education (MEd) program. In order to meet the need for highly qualified and diverse STEM educators in the high-need Houston Independent School District (HISD), HBU successly developed a five-year BS-MEd pathway for STEM majors to earn their teaching licensure in a fifth year and enter the Houston workforce as STEM teachers. Through this project, HBU aimed to 1) increase capacity for student success in STEM; 2) expand capacity of the HBU curriculum to better support the STEM teaching licensure; and 3) strengthen the capacity for professional development for STEM educators. The university?s partnership with the Lone Star College System (LSCS) and Houston Community College (HCC) was expanded to streamline the recruitment and transfer of students with an Associate?s degree in Science to HBU. Work was completed to ensure the university?s STEM curricula is aligned to facilitate completion of a STEM bachelor?s degree for all transfer students from the Community College partners. Needs assessment were conducted with focus groups of undergraduate STEM majors to assess their interest in becoming STEM educators, as well as with current K-12 STEM teachers and administrators from the HISD to identify their reasons for becoming teachers and challenges to persisting in the profession. The unique cultural needs of the Hispanic population in Houston was also evaluated to ensure that students participating in the HBU SEED program will have both scientific and cultural knowledge and experience to be successful in teaching STEM in Houston ISD  K-12 schools, ultimately increasing the numbers of Hispanic STEM teachers in HISD (29.7% Hispanic) to reflect that of the local community (44.8% Hispanic).  With support from Noyce project PI, Dr. Tim Scott, at Texas A&amp;M University and his team the project team successfully expanded the collaboration with Community college transfer students and expanded the BS-MEd program infrastructure through the creation of a STEM Teaching Resource Lab at HBU and development of the 4+1 Degree Plan. With the project success, HBU will continue work on the long-term goal of increasing the number, quality and diversity of leaders in STEM education throughout Houston.     Intellectual Merit:  This projectl identified evidence-based challenges that lead to the persistent shortage of qualified and diverse STEM educators in HISD. The needs of college students pursuing a STEM degree, STEM educators, and local school administrators were assessed to determine capacity for continuous growth of a SEED program with development of 4+ 1 Degree Plans in Science and Mathematics in both 4-8 and 7-12 teacher certifiations. This program has reduced the barriers for STEM students to pursue a career in teaching through development and implementation of a pathway to facilitate the transition of STEM majors to serve as highly qualified K-12 STEM teachers. Partnerships were established with HBU STEM and Education faculty, Lone Star College System and Houston Community College. and Houston ISD schools.      Broader Impact: This project served to identify and develop plans to meet the increased shortage of quality and diversity in STEM teachers in high-need schools in Houston Independent School District. HBU is uniquely situated to be able to make impactful improvements in STEM education in the Houston community because of the demographics that are mirrored in HBU and HISD students. The newly developed SEED program can serve as a model for developing STEM teachers to support shortages in other urban school districts like HISD that serve predominantly underrepresented students. The 4+1 or 2+2+1 developed degree pathways from AA to B.S. to M.Ed. can be applied at other institutions to support students' decisions to remain in the community and serve through teaching, specifically in STEM classrooms.            Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Angelia C Durand]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
