<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[REU Site: Research Experience for Undergraduates in Genome Science and Computational Biology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>402562.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>402562</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Holgado</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aholgado@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927076</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This REU Site award to Sam Houston State University, located in Huntsville, TX, will support the training of 10 students for 10 weeks during the summers of 2021 – 2023. It is anticipated that a total of 30 students (sophomore/junior), primarily from schools with limited research opportunities or from an under-represented group will be trained in the program. Students will conduct interdisciplinary research in Genome Science and Computational Biology and analyze genome, transcriptome, and proteome data using high-throughput computational approaches and bioinformatics tools to validate biological hypotheses. Students will learn the comprehensive scientific process and present the results at regional/national scientific conferences. Students will be encouraged to pursue graduate studies and research careers in genomics and bioinformatics. Assessment of the program will be done thru the online SALG URSSA tool. Students will be tracked after the program in order to determine their career paths.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program will focus on education and research training in computational and bioinformatic approaches on genome, transcriptome, and proteome data analyses. Students will conduct full-time summer research with faculty members from Biological Sciences, Chemistry, and Computer Science. The research activity of each student will be co-mentored by a biologist/biochemist and/or a computer scientist. Research projects include a wide range of interdisciplinary topics that include genome analysis, microbiome, gene expression, genetic networks, and phylogenetic relationships. Students will learn and use various computational methods and tools. Students will attend weekly computing workshops and lectures/discussions on basic scientific methodology. The seminars will be supplemented with activities to enhance scientific communications. Educational field trips will allow students to visit basic research laboratories, genome sequencing centers, and supercomputer facilities. Many students will present their research findings at scientific conferences and prepare research reports and/or peer-reviewed articles. Participants will be selected by the Principal Investigator and potential faculty mentors after completing an online application. More information about the program is available by visiting the program webpage (https://www.shsu.edu/research/reu-gscb/) or by directly contacting the PI (Dr. Madhusudan Choudhary at mchoudhary@shsu.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Hyuk Cho at hyukcho@shsu.edu).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050232</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Madhusudan</FirstName>
<LastName>Choudhary</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Madhusudan Choudhary</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mchoudhary@shsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000521129</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hyuk</FirstName>
<LastName>Cho</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hyuk Cho</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hyukcho@shsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000619798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Sam Houston State University</Name>
<CityName>HUNTSVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>773410001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9362943621</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1806 AVE J</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DJPXLZAE9931</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAM HOUSTON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sam Houston State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>773412448</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[SHSU Box 2448]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~268055</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~134507</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
