<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Chicago STEM Teaching Collaborative: Developing a STEM Master Teachers Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>121211.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>121211</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julio Soto</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgsoto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922973</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to serve the national need for highly effective K-12 STEM teachers in high-need school districts.  It intends to do so by developing a STEM Master Teaching Fellowship (MTF) model designed to produce master teachers who are technically, culturally, and pedagogically proficient. Chicago faces a crisis in teacher retention, particularly for STEM teachers in high-need school districts. The average school in Chicago Public Schools turns over 50% of its teachers every five years. Each year almost a third of the 520 Chicago Public schools have trouble filling one or more teaching positions. The high attrition rate combined with the general scarcity of STEM teachers is creating an acute shortage of teachers in high-need schools. This project intends to design an MTF model that serves diverse, high-need communities and addresses the causes of teacher attrition. The project will identify, recruit, and select exemplary teachers to the MTF program. This project will extend the current mentoring of new STEM teachers from one year to beyond the third year, the point at which teacher attrition increases sharply. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Capacity Building project at Northeastern Illinois University includes partnerships with Chicago Public Schools, City Colleges of Chicago, and the New Teacher Center. Goals of the project are to (1) build the capacity of key stakeholders to share expertise and resources and to build a strong community of practice; (2) develop a mentorship and instructional coaching model rooted in culturally relevant, culturally sustaining, and community immersive STEM teaching; and (3) build capacity for in-person, hybrid, and virtual coaching and mentorship that addresses teachers’ ability to design instruction and facilitate learning remotely. The theoretical basis for the project’s design resides in research literature on teacher leader development.  It stresses activities and experiences that promote development of highly effective STEM teaching skills, knowledge of community, culturally relevant and culturally sustaining pedagogy, and the ability to skillfully deliver STEM content virtually.  The project anticipates that teacher leaders with these skills and knowledge will have the potential to transform high-need schools and ameliorate high turnover and remediation needs. The project intends to conduct a needs-analysis to identify gaps in current CPS teachers’ pedagogy and cultural competency and deficiencies in CPS STEM student learning outcomes. The MTF program will be designed to address the identified gaps. The analysis will also include remote and hybrid mentoring for new teachers. Potential contributions to the field are high as the project disseminates key findings locally, regionally, and nationally through STEM partnerships and conferences. This Capacity Building project is supported through the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce). The Noyce program supports talented STEM undergraduate majors and professionals to become effective K-12 STEM teachers and experienced, exemplary K-12 teachers to become STEM master teachers in high-need school districts. It also supports research on the persistence, retention, and effectiveness of K-12 STEM teachers in high-need school districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050564</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Wrinkle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy C Wrinkle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[N-Wrinkle@neiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000082499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Syreeta</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Syreeta L Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sbrown55@neiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Billie</FirstName>
<LastName>Diaz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Billie Diaz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[b-kersh@neiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833504</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Lopez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alberto Lopez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[a-lopez@neiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern Illinois University</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606254625</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7734424671</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5500 N SAINT LOUIS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MR73WF5SHRW4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern Illinois University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606254699</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~121211</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In close collaboration with the Chicago Public Schools and the New Teacher Center, The Chicago STEM Teaching Collaborative investigated practices in cross-cutting STEM pedagogy, culturally relevant and sustaining pedagogy, place-based programs, and distance-learning to inform the construction of a professional development model in STEM mentorship and leadership. The project allowed us to collect and synthesize data, through literature review, teacher interviews, and surveys, to understand the complex mentorship needs of STEM teachers in urban schools. The Chicago STEM Teaching Collaborative?s efforts resulted in the development of a five year training experience in STEM mentoring and leadership for highly-skilled STEM teachers who currently teach middle and high school and who hold a Master?s degree. As part of their preparation, a graduate level certificate in STEM Mentoring and Leadership was designed at Northeastern Illinois University that integrates coursework from across different colleges and links the selected STEM teachers with relevant community-based organizations. To strengthen community connections, we established partnerships with the Museum of Science and Industry (MSI), Math Circles of Chicago, and the Westside Bee Boyz. These groups were purposefully established to highlight a range of areas of STEM, integrate a public education mission, and to align with the project leadership team?s content background. <br /><br />Our intensive work with Chicago Public Schools revealed a need to support second year teachers at the middle school level. Accordingly, during their five years together, cohort members will mentor four early career middle school STEM teachers. A need for STEM-specific mentoring as well as a need to integrate STEM with other disciplines also arose through partner discussion and interviews with teachers. The benefits of the program will be felt by students, teachers and the surrounding community. The program that we have designed has the potential to enhance teaching practices in the STEM classroom to meet the needs of culturally diverse learners. Students from groups that have been historically underrepresented in STEM will feel a greater sense of inclusion in the classroom, demonstrate growth in academic performance, and ultimately, aspirations for STEM post-secondary programs. <br /><br />Most focus group respondents (early career and veteran STEM middle and high school teachers) shared the opinion that a learning community of equals discussing and sharing ideas is more effective than traditional mentorship, principally among second-career STEM teachers. Therefore, another core feature of the program will be centered on establishing an ongoing professional learning community wherein the cohort will develop mentoring practices, discuss advances in STEM education, and share curricular enhancements. During the project period, we have demonstrated the capacity for the Chicago STEM Teaching Collaborative to advance collaborative partnerships across organizations, build partnership among Chicago-based nonprofits, and pave the road for future leaders in STEM education. Cohort members will aim to advance into school district defined roles such as Lead Mentor, Lead Coach, Specialist on Teaching and Learning, or Instructional Support Leader.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/22/2023<br>      Modified by: Alberto&nbsp;Lopez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In close collaboration with the Chicago Public Schools and the New Teacher Center, The Chicago STEM Teaching Collaborative investigated practices in cross-cutting STEM pedagogy, culturally relevant and sustaining pedagogy, place-based programs, and distance-learning to inform the construction of a professional development model in STEM mentorship and leadership. The project allowed us to collect and synthesize data, through literature review, teacher interviews, and surveys, to understand the complex mentorship needs of STEM teachers in urban schools. The Chicago STEM Teaching Collaborative?s efforts resulted in the development of a five year training experience in STEM mentoring and leadership for highly-skilled STEM teachers who currently teach middle and high school and who hold a Master?s degree. As part of their preparation, a graduate level certificate in STEM Mentoring and Leadership was designed at Northeastern Illinois University that integrates coursework from across different colleges and links the selected STEM teachers with relevant community-based organizations. To strengthen community connections, we established partnerships with the Museum of Science and Industry (MSI), Math Circles of Chicago, and the Westside Bee Boyz. These groups were purposefully established to highlight a range of areas of STEM, integrate a public education mission, and to align with the project leadership team?s content background.   Our intensive work with Chicago Public Schools revealed a need to support second year teachers at the middle school level. Accordingly, during their five years together, cohort members will mentor four early career middle school STEM teachers. A need for STEM-specific mentoring as well as a need to integrate STEM with other disciplines also arose through partner discussion and interviews with teachers. The benefits of the program will be felt by students, teachers and the surrounding community. The program that we have designed has the potential to enhance teaching practices in the STEM classroom to meet the needs of culturally diverse learners. Students from groups that have been historically underrepresented in STEM will feel a greater sense of inclusion in the classroom, demonstrate growth in academic performance, and ultimately, aspirations for STEM post-secondary programs.   Most focus group respondents (early career and veteran STEM middle and high school teachers) shared the opinion that a learning community of equals discussing and sharing ideas is more effective than traditional mentorship, principally among second-career STEM teachers. Therefore, another core feature of the program will be centered on establishing an ongoing professional learning community wherein the cohort will develop mentoring practices, discuss advances in STEM education, and share curricular enhancements. During the project period, we have demonstrated the capacity for the Chicago STEM Teaching Collaborative to advance collaborative partnerships across organizations, build partnership among Chicago-based nonprofits, and pave the road for future leaders in STEM education. Cohort members will aim to advance into school district defined roles such as Lead Mentor, Lead Coach, Specialist on Teaching and Learning, or Instructional Support Leader.       Last Modified: 03/22/2023       Submitted by: Alberto Lopez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
