<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Trans-Atlantic Research and Development  Interchange on Sustainability 2021:  Sustainability and Resilience in the Face of Emergent Threats]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In the 21st Century, the dominant challenge to humanity is encapsulated in the concept of sustainability. This is at its core an effort to find ways that make it possible for civilization to prosper on Earth now and in the future. By itself, this is a formidable challenge given the 7.8 billion current human population. But this challenge must be met in the face of emergent threats such as the SARS-COV-2 pandemic, wars, climate change, and others. At the local level, these emergent global threats can manifest as major disruption events like floods, droughts, forest fires, high rates of hospitalization and death, and economic distress. Therefore, the theme for TARDIS 21 is "Sustainability and Resilience in the Face of Emergent Threats." To explore this theme and find feasible and actionable pathways to manage it, the following focus questions will be addressed at TARDIS 21: (1) What are the most critical threats facing the World in the 21st Century? (2) Which of these threats are critical challenges to achieving sustainability and promoting resilience locally as well as globally? (3) What may be the most practical and effective ways to mitigate these threats? (4) What is the most practical and useful path to resilience and sustainability in the face of these threats? The workshop will be conducted in October 2021 in Miskolc, Hungary. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The composition of the body of participants will be balanced to include representation with respect to discipline (engineering, physics, chemistry, economics, policy, etc.), institutions (academic, government, private sector) and regional and national representation, and (4) minorities and women. The participants will be from both the European and American communities, with the European participants being supported on non-NSF funds. The PI will work with the Technical University of Graz, the University of Miskolc, and the Austrian Federal Ministry of Science to prepare a final report resulting from the workshop. This report will be made available on public websites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050546</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Urmila</FirstName>
<LastName>Diwekar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Urmila M Diwekar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[urmila@vri-custom.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000059541</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vishwamitra Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>CRYSTAL LAKE</CityName>
<ZipCode>600122224</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6308863047</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2714 CRYSTAL WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YBB6XUPN9CG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VISHWAMITRA RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vishwamitra Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Crystal Lake</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>600122224</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2714 Crystal Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Trans-Atlantic Research and Development Interchange on Sustainability Workshop (TARDIS 2022) Workshop was a meeting on scientific topics related to sustainability. It was essentially a three-day study session stimulated by presentations and discussion. The workshop involved participants from the United States, India, and Europe in the multi-disciplinary field of sustainability. The group included experts from engineering, mathematical sciences, physics, ecology, economics, and political science fields. These include 29% women and 19% Hispanics. The theme of the workshop was "Sustainability and Resilience in the Face of Emergent Threats."&nbsp; We are preparing a journal paper for publication on the same topic.&nbsp;&nbsp; The paper focuses on the following questions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>What are the most critical threats facing the World in the 21st Century?</li> <li>Which of these threats are critical challenges to achieving sustainability and promoting resilience locally as well as globally?</li> <li>What may be the most practical and effective ways to mitigate these threats?</li> <li>What is the most practical and useful path to resilience and sustainability in the face of these threats?</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We proposed to focus TARDIS 21 on emergent local and global challenges to sustainability. This is important because, in the 21st Century, the World is highly urbanized, with more than 4 billion people living in urban areas . Due to efficient modern transportation by land, water, and air, there is a fast and reliable movement of people and goods between these urban centers across the globe. Besides, the World Wide Web has, in modern times, made the diffusion of information across the World almost instant and widespread, i.e., anyone with an internet connection can find almost any information. This gives rise to a hyperconnected world where any event tends to be amplified by being transmitted across the globe at the speed of modern communications and transportation. The recent SARS-COV-2 pandemic is a clear example of the modern form of this emergent phenomenon, but it is by no means the only or the last challenge that we will face in the 21st Century.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Urmila&nbsp;M&nbsp;Diwekar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Trans-Atlantic Research and Development Interchange on Sustainability Workshop (TARDIS 2022) Workshop was a meeting on scientific topics related to sustainability. It was essentially a three-day study session stimulated by presentations and discussion. The workshop involved participants from the United States, India, and Europe in the multi-disciplinary field of sustainability. The group included experts from engineering, mathematical sciences, physics, ecology, economics, and political science fields. These include 29% women and 19% Hispanics. The theme of the workshop was "Sustainability and Resilience in the Face of Emergent Threats."  We are preparing a journal paper for publication on the same topic.   The paper focuses on the following questions.     What are the most critical threats facing the World in the 21st Century? Which of these threats are critical challenges to achieving sustainability and promoting resilience locally as well as globally? What may be the most practical and effective ways to mitigate these threats? What is the most practical and useful path to resilience and sustainability in the face of these threats?         We proposed to focus TARDIS 21 on emergent local and global challenges to sustainability. This is important because, in the 21st Century, the World is highly urbanized, with more than 4 billion people living in urban areas . Due to efficient modern transportation by land, water, and air, there is a fast and reliable movement of people and goods between these urban centers across the globe. Besides, the World Wide Web has, in modern times, made the diffusion of information across the World almost instant and widespread, i.e., anyone with an internet connection can find almost any information. This gives rise to a hyperconnected world where any event tends to be amplified by being transmitted across the globe at the speed of modern communications and transportation. The recent SARS-COV-2 pandemic is a clear example of the modern form of this emergent phenomenon, but it is by no means the only or the last challenge that we will face in the 21st Century.       Last Modified: 04/06/2023       Submitted by: Urmila M Diwekar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
