<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building the Foundation for Noyce Master Teaching Fellowships in Mathematics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70535.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70535</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bonnie Green</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bongreen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924386</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project aims to serve the national need of developing master teachers in mathematics by building capacity for the creation of an online master’s degree in educational leadership and mathematics. This project will serve national interest and the Noyce program’s intent by developing and evaluating teaching and leadership skills in elementary, middle school, and high school teachers of mathematics. This is important because this program has the potential to provide teachers with the knowledge and skill to increase student achievement in mathematics from kindergarten to high school graduation. Significant to this project is the identification of how to best recruit teachers from high-need school districts and the revision of a current 25-month master's degree, Bank Street’s current Leadership in Mathematics Education program (LME), to a modified “14-month online master’s degree in Leadership in Mathematics Education.” As a capacity building project, the information garnered is proposed to be used in developing a Track 3 Master Teaching Fellowships Noyce proposal. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project at Bank Street College of Education, a private, master’s degree granting institution, in collaboration with Gonzaga University, a private comprehensive university, includes partnerships with the New York City Department of Education and the Chicago Public Schools. Five goals guide the execution of this Capacity Building project. First is to conduct a needs assessment to inform the design of a Master’s degree in Leadership in Mathematics Education for a Master Teaching Fellowships program. Second is to solidify program design, curriculum, and course offerings for the master’s degree. Third is to pilot-test recruitment strategies for a master’s teacher program. Fourth is to build partnerships with high-need school districts and professional learning organizations and fifth is to secure matching funds in support of a future Noyce Track 3 submission. Central to the project’s intellectual merit is the understanding that can be gained by conducting a needs assessment of mathematics teaching and teachers from a wide array of high-need school districts including rural and urban. The project’s broader impacts lie in the foundation that is being laid for the revision of an online master’s degree program that would eventually prepare master teachers in theoretically and empirically based pedagogical practices grounded in the constructivist’s approach, coupled with leadership skills that will enable the mathematics master teachers to have an impact on student learning in their classrooms and across their campuses. Bank Street has partnered with a team of evaluators who will be able to gather and analyze qualitative data through focus groups and interviews, as well as obtain data on market research and curricular effectiveness of a current, similar master's program at Bank Street. The findings of this project are intended to support the creation of a Noyce Track 3 proposal and will be disseminated through national channels, including organizations that focus on the teaching of mathematics. This Capacity Building project is supported through the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce). The Noyce program supports talented STEM undergraduate majors and professionals to become effective K-12 STEM teachers and experienced, exemplary K-12 teachers to become STEM master teachers in high-need school districts. It also supports research on the persistence, retention, and effectiveness of K-12 STEM teachers in high-need school districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050642</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Hummel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robin Hummel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rhummel@bankstreet.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644019</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Hogle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric K Hogle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hogle@gonzaga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000835141</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bank Street College of Education</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100251898</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128754400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>610 W 112TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JVQ7Z4NRQK16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BANK STREET COLLEGE OF EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bank Street College of Education]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100251898</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[610 West 112th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~70535</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c01432d1-7fff-2c50-4065-371a25cb8677"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Noyce Capacity Building grant gave us the time and space to thoughtfully write our application for a Track 3 Master Teaching Fellows grant (MTF), which we submitted in August 2022. In practical terms, we were able to redesign the Leadership in Mathematics Education (LME) master&rsquo;s degree program at Bank Street Graduate School of Education to align with the requirements of the MTF without compromise to our own deeply-held philosophy of developing progressive math teachers and leaders. The grant gave us the time to research and pursue underserved school districts that would benefit most from the MTF. Having the Capacity Building grant kept us focused. Going online created grandiose plans and going to the Noyce Summit in July 2022 to learn what others were doing, and getting advice and encouragement from those who came before, reminded us to keep our work focused and clear and doable. In addition, the grant gave us the time to thoughtfully plan out the four years of professional development that would follow the LME. This part was perhaps the heaviest lift and most significant outcome from the time and space the grant afforded. Through our planning and capacity building process, we have articulated and accomplished the following objectives and activities:</span></p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>We redesigned and reregistered the two-year hybrid (online and in-person) LME program into an intensive, 13-month, online master&rsquo;s degree program. While redesigning the program we had internal reviews, state reviews, and we convened a student-centered focus group of recent grads. We believed our application for the MTF would be stronger if we could recruit a pilot group to the redesigned LME program. We accepted a small group in the spring of 2022 and they will graduate in the summer of 2023. The pilot for the online program gave us the opportunity to assess and tweak the program as students go through it. One change we made because of the pilot was shifting the time frame of the program when the NSF removed the 13-month requirement. (The LME is now 16 months.) We also realized that it would be wise to shift the program to start in July instead of June, when teachers are finishing up their school year, which is always an exceptionally stressful time of year. The pilot has also allowed us to continue to plan and try out some of the professional development opportunities we wrote into the MTF grant.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Some of the content for the four-year professional learning opportunity for MTFs was influenced by a focus group of recent graduates, who gave feedback on what they would need if we continued their program through professional development. In January 2022, six graduates of the LME program participated in a 90-minute focus group. The goal was to learn about participants&rsquo; experiences in the program and to contribute to a needs assessment as Bank Street worked towards establishing a fully online version of the LME program. One question we asked of the focus group was, &ldquo;What do you still need?&rdquo; This prompt helped us zero in on the myriad choices we had to design the professional development piece. Attending the Noyce Summit gave us additional ideas that we incorporated into the MTF grant; for example, putting in the opportunity for the Fellows to lead a small math conference at Bank Street and the idea of including a principal/superintendent seminar as part of their professional development.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>We built a partnership with high-need schools in New York City and the New York Hall of Science to engage in the process of planning and delivering a quality, comprehensive and cohesive MTF program. We created a planning team and an Advisory Board to review and advise on the MTF program design, support effective marketing, recruitment, and retention strategies that will engage prospective MTFs, encourage their application to be MTFs, and once accepted, sustain them over the five-year term of the fellowship. In addition, we identified and raised matching funds for a full Noyce application.</span></p> </li> </ol></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Robin&nbsp;Hummel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Noyce Capacity Building grant gave us the time and space to thoughtfully write our application for a Track 3 Master Teaching Fellows grant (MTF), which we submitted in August 2022. In practical terms, we were able to redesign the Leadership in Mathematics Education (LME) master’s degree program at Bank Street Graduate School of Education to align with the requirements of the MTF without compromise to our own deeply-held philosophy of developing progressive math teachers and leaders. The grant gave us the time to research and pursue underserved school districts that would benefit most from the MTF. Having the Capacity Building grant kept us focused. Going online created grandiose plans and going to the Noyce Summit in July 2022 to learn what others were doing, and getting advice and encouragement from those who came before, reminded us to keep our work focused and clear and doable. In addition, the grant gave us the time to thoughtfully plan out the four years of professional development that would follow the LME. This part was perhaps the heaviest lift and most significant outcome from the time and space the grant afforded. Through our planning and capacity building process, we have articulated and accomplished the following objectives and activities:   We redesigned and reregistered the two-year hybrid (online and in-person) LME program into an intensive, 13-month, online master’s degree program. While redesigning the program we had internal reviews, state reviews, and we convened a student-centered focus group of recent grads. We believed our application for the MTF would be stronger if we could recruit a pilot group to the redesigned LME program. We accepted a small group in the spring of 2022 and they will graduate in the summer of 2023. The pilot for the online program gave us the opportunity to assess and tweak the program as students go through it. One change we made because of the pilot was shifting the time frame of the program when the NSF removed the 13-month requirement. (The LME is now 16 months.) We also realized that it would be wise to shift the program to start in July instead of June, when teachers are finishing up their school year, which is always an exceptionally stressful time of year. The pilot has also allowed us to continue to plan and try out some of the professional development opportunities we wrote into the MTF grant.   Some of the content for the four-year professional learning opportunity for MTFs was influenced by a focus group of recent graduates, who gave feedback on what they would need if we continued their program through professional development. In January 2022, six graduates of the LME program participated in a 90-minute focus group. The goal was to learn about participants’ experiences in the program and to contribute to a needs assessment as Bank Street worked towards establishing a fully online version of the LME program. One question we asked of the focus group was, "What do you still need?" This prompt helped us zero in on the myriad choices we had to design the professional development piece. Attending the Noyce Summit gave us additional ideas that we incorporated into the MTF grant; for example, putting in the opportunity for the Fellows to lead a small math conference at Bank Street and the idea of including a principal/superintendent seminar as part of their professional development.     We built a partnership with high-need schools in New York City and the New York Hall of Science to engage in the process of planning and delivering a quality, comprehensive and cohesive MTF program. We created a planning team and an Advisory Board to review and advise on the MTF program design, support effective marketing, recruitment, and retention strategies that will engage prospective MTFs, encourage their application to be MTFs, and once accepted, sustain them over the five-year term of the fellowship. In addition, we identified and raised matching funds for a full Noyce application.         Last Modified: 01/26/2023       Submitted by: Robin Hummel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
