<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Utah STEM Master Educator Institute]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74850.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74850</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bonnie Green</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This capacity building project will serve the national need for a well-prepared population of K-12 STEM teachers who can serve as leaders and role models within their schools.  In particular, the project will develop new partnerships to support high quality training and professional learning for master STEM teachers serving high-need school districts in Utah.  Working across the state, the project will bring together local education agencies, multiple colleges and universities, and local STEM industry partners to create a STEM teacher training institute.  The resulting STEM Master Educators Institute will support educators as they help to prepare students to work in Utah’s STEM industries. Specifically, the Institute is intended to increase leadership capacity within the Utah education community, promote innovative solutions to problems of practice in STEM education, and create a sustainable model for collaboration within and across schools.  To complete the project, the project leadership team will work with an experienced advisory board and representatives from multiple partners to design the Institute.  The Institute will incorporate a “think tank” design to address key challenges in STEM education. The solutions developed by the Institute will reflect the collective knowledge of experienced K-12 and college-level educators, subject matter experts, and partners in the educational technology sector. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project at Utah State University includes partnerships with Utah’s STEM Action Center, and several Utah institutions of higher education (Southern Utah University, Utah Valley University and University of Utah).  Additionally, the Utah State Board of Education will support the planning process with the project leadership team to build durable relationships with local education partners that will complement and strengthen the Board's STEM efforts. It is anticipated that master teachers and other Institute stakeholders will address challenges in distance learning, culturally aligned STEM content, integration of STEM across the disciplines, project-based learning, and K-12 science and math instruction.  Project goals include the development of a novel, industry-based STEM teacher professional learning institute model. The project’s research plan uses the lens of Cultural-Historical Activity Theory to explore interactions between statewide educational systems to better understand the relationships between stakeholders and teacher education programs. This Capacity Building project is supported through the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program (Noyce). The Noyce program supports talented STEM undergraduate majors and professionals to become effective K-12 STEM teachers and experienced, exemplary K-12 teachers to become STEM master teachers in high-need school districts. It also supports research on the persistence, retention, and effectiveness of K-12 STEM teachers in high-need school districts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050408</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tamara</FirstName>
<LastName>Goetz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tamara Goetz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tgoetz@utah.gov]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000750188</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susannah</FirstName>
<LastName>French</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susannah French</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sfrench@biology.usu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000555774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colby</FirstName>
<LastName>Tofel-Grehl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colby Tofel-Grehl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[colby.tg@usu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000664527</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>LOGAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 OLD MAIN HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPE2YDWHDYU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Utah State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843222805</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2805 Old Main Hill]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~74850</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Utah faces an issue like most states regarding meeting the existing and growing demand for STEM talent. Utah is a hotbed for STEM job growth (Utah Job Outlook, 2018), and there are not enough students choosing STEM education and career pathways (ACT, 2019). The attrition and completion rates in STEM degree areas compound this challenging situation as students struggle to succeed in their academic efforts. Further, the persistent and growing concern for lack of STEM access for all students exacerbates the problem. The growing digital divide in Utah is becoming more prevalent. It is most evident between residents along the Wasatch Front that comprise 80% of the state's population and the 10% who live in the rural areas of the state (U.S.Census Bureau, 2010). Those living in rural areas, which cover 97% of the state's geographic area, typically do not have reliable access to basic resources needed to interact digitally with their peers. Further, students in rural communities have limited access to STEM college preparation and career training during their standard years of formal education. The issues of student recruitment, retention and access can only be solved if STEM educators are prepared and confident to provide engaging and effective STEM experiences for all students.</p> <p>Findings from this project indicate that teacher education across Utah needs to reconsider it foci. &nbsp;The first stakeholder meeting, attended by IHE faculty and LEA leaders, (n = 27) examined general perceptions of the USMEIC program and identified key issues and items pertaining to the development of a survey to be administered to building level administrators. Specific topics included the characteristics of good teacher leaders, the content and curriculum structure of the USMEIC program, possible barriers to teacher participation in the USMEIC program, and incentive approaches for USMEIC program participants. After the survey was administered, a second stakeholder meeting was held. The second stakeholder meeting (n = 8) was conducted to discuss the results from the administrators&rsquo; survey. Several key opinions were identified by the participants concerning the structure of the USMEIC program: 1) A scaffolded set of learning experiences involving curriculum development, classroom implementation, action research, and conference presentation should be provided; 2) Research experiences (e.g., action research) should be both emphasized and fully supported; and 3) For conference trips, active participation (e.g., presentation delivery) rather than merely attendance should be required.&nbsp;</p> <p>A survey was then developed and administered to gather statewide data on key issues associated with the structure, implementation, and recruitment strategy for the USMEIC program. A total of 31 school administrators across the state participated in the survey (61%, non-rural districts; 29%, rural districts; 68%, elementary schools; 22%, secondary schools; 10%, charter schools).Survey results indicate that the majority of participants (94%) reported that "cross-curricular content development" should be a core component, followed by "national and state STEM content standard" (74%), "principles of effective collaboration with other teachers" (74%), and "principles and practice of three-dimensional learning" (65%). Regarding additional experiences that administrators would expect USMEIC to support, "classroom observations outside of their own district" (77%) and "conference attendance" (65%) were most frequently favored, while "national-level participation and leadership opportunities'' (19%) was least cited. In addition, many participants believed that master&rsquo;s degrees pursued through participation in the USMEIC program should be mixed-focus (74%), rather than either discipline-focused (19%) or pedagogy-focused (3%). For the survey question about the USMEIC program workload (i.e., hours worked on USMEIC-related activities per week), most of the participants reported 1-5 hours (87%) as more appropriate than 6-10 hours. Survey results also included participants&rsquo; perceptions of possible barriers for participation in the USMEIC program. "Insufficient time available after teaching responsibilities'' (90%) and "Lack of financial resources" (74%) were the most frequently reported barriers. Lastly, in terms of the recruitment strategy for the program, many participants believed that the USMEIC program participants should reflect the demographic distribution of all Utah teachers (58%) rather than prioritization of certain applicant groups such as rural teachers (35%) and female teachers (23%).</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Colby&nbsp;Tofel-Grehl</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Utah faces an issue like most states regarding meeting the existing and growing demand for STEM talent. Utah is a hotbed for STEM job growth (Utah Job Outlook, 2018), and there are not enough students choosing STEM education and career pathways (ACT, 2019). The attrition and completion rates in STEM degree areas compound this challenging situation as students struggle to succeed in their academic efforts. Further, the persistent and growing concern for lack of STEM access for all students exacerbates the problem. The growing digital divide in Utah is becoming more prevalent. It is most evident between residents along the Wasatch Front that comprise 80% of the state's population and the 10% who live in the rural areas of the state (U.S.Census Bureau, 2010). Those living in rural areas, which cover 97% of the state's geographic area, typically do not have reliable access to basic resources needed to interact digitally with their peers. Further, students in rural communities have limited access to STEM college preparation and career training during their standard years of formal education. The issues of student recruitment, retention and access can only be solved if STEM educators are prepared and confident to provide engaging and effective STEM experiences for all students.  Findings from this project indicate that teacher education across Utah needs to reconsider it foci.  The first stakeholder meeting, attended by IHE faculty and LEA leaders, (n = 27) examined general perceptions of the USMEIC program and identified key issues and items pertaining to the development of a survey to be administered to building level administrators. Specific topics included the characteristics of good teacher leaders, the content and curriculum structure of the USMEIC program, possible barriers to teacher participation in the USMEIC program, and incentive approaches for USMEIC program participants. After the survey was administered, a second stakeholder meeting was held. The second stakeholder meeting (n = 8) was conducted to discuss the results from the administrators’ survey. Several key opinions were identified by the participants concerning the structure of the USMEIC program: 1) A scaffolded set of learning experiences involving curriculum development, classroom implementation, action research, and conference presentation should be provided; 2) Research experiences (e.g., action research) should be both emphasized and fully supported; and 3) For conference trips, active participation (e.g., presentation delivery) rather than merely attendance should be required.   A survey was then developed and administered to gather statewide data on key issues associated with the structure, implementation, and recruitment strategy for the USMEIC program. A total of 31 school administrators across the state participated in the survey (61%, non-rural districts; 29%, rural districts; 68%, elementary schools; 22%, secondary schools; 10%, charter schools).Survey results indicate that the majority of participants (94%) reported that "cross-curricular content development" should be a core component, followed by "national and state STEM content standard" (74%), "principles of effective collaboration with other teachers" (74%), and "principles and practice of three-dimensional learning" (65%). Regarding additional experiences that administrators would expect USMEIC to support, "classroom observations outside of their own district" (77%) and "conference attendance" (65%) were most frequently favored, while "national-level participation and leadership opportunities'' (19%) was least cited. In addition, many participants believed that master’s degrees pursued through participation in the USMEIC program should be mixed-focus (74%), rather than either discipline-focused (19%) or pedagogy-focused (3%). For the survey question about the USMEIC program workload (i.e., hours worked on USMEIC-related activities per week), most of the participants reported 1-5 hours (87%) as more appropriate than 6-10 hours. Survey results also included participants’ perceptions of possible barriers for participation in the USMEIC program. "Insufficient time available after teaching responsibilities'' (90%) and "Lack of financial resources" (74%) were the most frequently reported barriers. Lastly, in terms of the recruitment strategy for the program, many participants believed that the USMEIC program participants should reflect the demographic distribution of all Utah teachers (58%) rather than prioritization of certain applicant groups such as rural teachers (35%) and female teachers (23%).          Last Modified: 05/04/2023       Submitted by: Colby Tofel-Grehl]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
