<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Liquid Oxygen (LOX) - Methane Engine for Small Satellite Launch Vehicles]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to significantly lower the capital barriers for new enterprises to participate as small satellite launchers and service providers, by offering high-performance rocket engines produced at the $100 K cost point.  On the production side, this change would lead to a restructuring of space launch and satellite sector supply chains from the current high cost/low volume to a low-cost/high volume configuration as in the aircraft or automotive industries.  Such a change could also provide a significant increase in high paying aerospace engineering and manufacturing jobs. On the customer end, once the small satellites reach the orbit, they could expand capabilities for military and civilian services in space, from surveillance and weather monitoring to completely new industries such as agricultural earth observation and climate change monitoring, or when combined into large constellations, provide wireless and mobile internet service globally to underserved populations.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will boost the development of American-made, high-performance, reliable, high thrust-to-weight and low maintenance liquid rocket engines of 1.5-metric-ton thrust for small 50-180 kg satellite launch vehicles to 700 km Low Earth Orbit (LEO), using low-cost liquid oxygen (LOX) / methane (or liquified natural gas) propellants. A two-stage rocket would be propelled by a cluster of six such engines on its 1st stage, and a single vacuum-version of this engine on its upper stage.  The small satellite business has been growing exponentially in the last few years, with the launch demand far outpacing supply.  The annual demand/supply launch gap is expected to be in the 200-700 satellite range by 2026. The primary objectives of Phase I are to design and build the preburner and thrust chamber assembly and to design the turbopump assembly. The results from Phase I will provide data on the initial engine weight, manufacturability, production cost, and define the pace, risk posture, and resource needs for engine development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/28/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/28/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050703</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maksud</FirstName>
<LastName>Ismailov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maksud Ismailov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[max@rocketpropulsionsystems.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000835368</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ROCKET PROPULSION SYSTEMS LLC</Name>
<CityName>KENT</CityName>
<ZipCode>980322116</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4255168677</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>19032 66TH AVE S, STE C102</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H12BCANKEW99</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROCKET PROPULSION SYSTEMS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rocket Propulsion Systems LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Renton</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>980595358</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6127 NE 2nd Ln]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~255993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Rocket Propulsion Systems LLC (RPS) pursues to develop the first low-cost reusable liquid rocket engine for small satellite space launch vehicles in this SBIR project, with a thrust of 3,307 lbf (1.5-ton, sea-level) and aggressive targets of $100,000 per engine unit production cost, 100:1 thrust-to-weight ratio and reusability for at least 100 space flights.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Major technical objectives for Phase I research were to demonstrate: (A) engine manufacturability and first complete fabricated prototype, (B) at the weight of 33 pounds (1/100<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;of 3,307 lbf thrust), and (C) cost to manufacture of $100,000.&nbsp; RPS succeeded in building its first prototype satisfying these metrics and named it "Centurion."&nbsp; &nbsp;The engine packages into compact 14" diameter x 24" height envelope, which is a convenient size for future rockets powered by these engines, in single-engine or multi-engine configurations.</p> <p>The small satellite launch vehicle market is anticipated to experience a large gap between launch demand and supply, approaching 200-700 unfulfilled space launches per year by 2026.&nbsp; This demand needs to close to enable the following urgently needed capabilities: climate sensing and tracking of change; security of domestic space infrastructure; acceleration of global trade by precision tracking for fleets of transport to prevent costly delays and accidents.&nbsp;</p> <p>To validate this idea, RPS participated in "Beat the Odds Bootcamp" and conducted customer discover interviews with highly regarded (35) people within the space launch industry.&nbsp; From these interviews it followed that<em>&nbsp;</em>at least (100) more small satellite rockets launching to dedicated orbit are needed per year, with 70/30 split between commercial and military small satellite customers, and very conservatively at least (2) engines per week for the next (10) years.&nbsp; At full production and sales level, (100) small rockets are projected to be equipped with 7 "Centurion" engines per rocket, each produced by RPS at a cost of $100K and sold at $150K.&nbsp; This amounts to the serviceable obtainable market&nbsp;<strong>SOM</strong>&nbsp;of $150K/engine x 7 engines/rocket x 100 rockets/year =&nbsp;<strong>$105M</strong>/year, representing roughly a 100/1 return on NSF SBIR investment of $1.256 M by 2029.</p> <p>From June 2022 onward, we started promoting the "Centurion" rocket engine to space launch companies, business accelerators, military and government organizations for support in Phases II and III.&nbsp; RPS was visited by NAVY, Mayor of Kent, Chase Bank, etc., to tour the facility and check on the engine prototype development.&nbsp; RPS also presented a briefing on the state of the engine to Air Force Research Laboratory at Edwards Air Force Base, in which they expressed enthusiastic support for this project and recommended several avenues to pursue funding within the Air Force/Space Force community.&nbsp; As a result, we received (5) letters of support from commercial and government entities for Phase II, including the first customer.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Maksud&nbsp;Ismailov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Rocket Propulsion Systems LLC (RPS) pursues to develop the first low-cost reusable liquid rocket engine for small satellite space launch vehicles in this SBIR project, with a thrust of 3,307 lbf (1.5-ton, sea-level) and aggressive targets of $100,000 per engine unit production cost, 100:1 thrust-to-weight ratio and reusability for at least 100 space flights.    Major technical objectives for Phase I research were to demonstrate: (A) engine manufacturability and first complete fabricated prototype, (B) at the weight of 33 pounds (1/100th of 3,307 lbf thrust), and (C) cost to manufacture of $100,000.  RPS succeeded in building its first prototype satisfying these metrics and named it "Centurion."   The engine packages into compact 14" diameter x 24" height envelope, which is a convenient size for future rockets powered by these engines, in single-engine or multi-engine configurations.  The small satellite launch vehicle market is anticipated to experience a large gap between launch demand and supply, approaching 200-700 unfulfilled space launches per year by 2026.  This demand needs to close to enable the following urgently needed capabilities: climate sensing and tracking of change; security of domestic space infrastructure; acceleration of global trade by precision tracking for fleets of transport to prevent costly delays and accidents.   To validate this idea, RPS participated in "Beat the Odds Bootcamp" and conducted customer discover interviews with highly regarded (35) people within the space launch industry.  From these interviews it followed that at least (100) more small satellite rockets launching to dedicated orbit are needed per year, with 70/30 split between commercial and military small satellite customers, and very conservatively at least (2) engines per week for the next (10) years.  At full production and sales level, (100) small rockets are projected to be equipped with 7 "Centurion" engines per rocket, each produced by RPS at a cost of $100K and sold at $150K.  This amounts to the serviceable obtainable market SOM of $150K/engine x 7 engines/rocket x 100 rockets/year = $105M/year, representing roughly a 100/1 return on NSF SBIR investment of $1.256 M by 2029.  From June 2022 onward, we started promoting the "Centurion" rocket engine to space launch companies, business accelerators, military and government organizations for support in Phases II and III.  RPS was visited by NAVY, Mayor of Kent, Chase Bank, etc., to tour the facility and check on the engine prototype development.  RPS also presented a briefing on the state of the engine to Air Force Research Laboratory at Edwards Air Force Base, in which they expressed enthusiastic support for this project and recommended several avenues to pursue funding within the Air Force/Space Force community.  As a result, we received (5) letters of support from commercial and government entities for Phase II, including the first customer.          Last Modified: 10/17/2022       Submitted by: Maksud Ismailov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
