<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Performance of Agricultural Storage Silos and Farm Bins in Nebraska and Iowa During the August 2020 Derecho]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>41934.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>41934</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This grant for Rapid Response Research (RAPID) will investigate the wind performance of agricultural storage silos and farm bins during the August 2020 Derecho. This high wind event left a path of structural damage exceeding 750 miles in length and crossing several Midwestern states, including Nebraska, Iowa, Illinois, and Indiana. This event presents a unique opportunity to evaluate the performance of agricultural storage silos and farm bins because of the unusually large area impacted in a predominantly agricultural region of the country and the wide range of wind speeds encountered (ranging from 60 – 130 mph). Despite the criticality of the agricultural industry to the U.S. economy and global food production, agricultural storage silos and farm bins have received relatively little attention with respect to natural hazards research. Furthermore, these structures are not designed to a consistent standard in the United States, which has led to a significant vulnerability in rural communities, and there is a critical need to understand the influence of design and construction parameters on the wind resistance of these structures. Findings from this study will advance fundamental knowledge regarding the performance of these structures in severe wind events and enable consideration of new design approaches and the evaluation of mitigation measures to safeguard U.S. food production and agricultural economies. Results generated in this project also will enable detailed studies of rural community resilience, which require an understanding of the unique structural typologies that comprise the built environment - a necessary step towards enhancing national resilience. This project will support a graduate student researcher, serving to train the next generation of STEM leadership, and will leverage an NSF-supported Research Experiences for Undergraduates Site to broaden participation of underrepresented groups in engineering. Data from this project will be archived and made publicly available in the NSF-supported National Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure (NHERI) Data Depot (https://www.DesignSafe-ci.org) for broad use within the engineering community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID grant seeks to answer fundamental research questions regarding the influence of key parameters on the wind resistance of agricultural storage silos and farm bins: (1) How do foundation type, anchorage depth (if present), and baseplate design influence the wind resistance of agricultural storage silos and farm bins?, and (2) How can the probability of failure for agricultural storage silos and farm bins be represented as a function of wind speed? These questions will be answered through a detailed investigation of the performance of agricultural storage silos and farm bins during the August 2020 Derecho. Specifically, perishable data will be collected documenting undamaged and damaged storage silos and farm bins in the path of the derecho. The team will document the design and construction of individual structures, estimated condition of the structure prior to the event, and current condition of the structure following the event. Aerial imagery and three-dimensional point clouds will be acquired for structures evidencing complex damage patterns. The typology and performance of nearby structures will also be documented to obtain more detailed estimates of wind speeds in the vicinity of the storage silos and farm bins. Data will be analyzed to generate empirical fragility curves to evaluate the influence of several design and construction parameters including foundation, anchorage, and baseplate design. The fragility curves can be used for subsequent research in rural community resilience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2050152</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Wittich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christine Wittich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cwittich@unl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805181</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>LINCOLN</CityName>
<ZipCode>685032427</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 VINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HTQ6K6NJFHA6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685830855</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 Vine St, 362L WHIT]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>073Y</Code>
<Text>ECI-Engineering for Civil Infr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7231</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~41934</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The August 10, 2020 Derecho was a very powerful storm that swept across much of the Midwest causing billions of dollars in damage and multiple casualties. The highest estimated wind speeds occurred in central and eastern Iowa, with significant damage in the predominantly rural and agricultural regions. Widespread damage to grain bins was observed, which presented a unique and important opportunity to investigate the performance of these structures in extreme wind events. Given that these structures are not designed and constructed to consistent standards in the United States, it became critical to understand the influence of various design and construction parameters. This project investigated these relationships through documentation and analysis of over 700 steel grain bins in the aftermath of the storm.</p> <p>Structural damage observations were combined with estimated wind speeds to understand how various parameters combine to impact wind performance. The study considered the performance of empty grain bins, only, given the known susceptibility. This study shows that the largest capacity bins, which tend to be both tall and wide, are more vulnerable than small bins; and, bins with highest exposure, such as those in open fields, are much more vulnerable than those located near other agricultural structures. Site-specific case studies were conducted in which nearby, similar grain bins that were exposed to similar wind speeds were compared. From this, it can be seen that vertical stiffeners can significantly enhance performance, while roof venting can similarly reduce performance.</p> <p>Over the span of the two-year project, four undergraduate students and two graduate students were directly mentored by the Principal Investigator in research and became knowledge in the advanced areas of wind, structural, agricultural, and hazards engineering. The research has yielded one peer-reviewed conference presentation, several presentations, and two peer-reviewed journal articles. This research has also been disseminated via mass media and is anticipated to be leveraged for standards development in future years. All data has been made publicly available via NHERI DesignSafe-CI. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Christine&nbsp;Wittich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The August 10, 2020 Derecho was a very powerful storm that swept across much of the Midwest causing billions of dollars in damage and multiple casualties. The highest estimated wind speeds occurred in central and eastern Iowa, with significant damage in the predominantly rural and agricultural regions. Widespread damage to grain bins was observed, which presented a unique and important opportunity to investigate the performance of these structures in extreme wind events. Given that these structures are not designed and constructed to consistent standards in the United States, it became critical to understand the influence of various design and construction parameters. This project investigated these relationships through documentation and analysis of over 700 steel grain bins in the aftermath of the storm.  Structural damage observations were combined with estimated wind speeds to understand how various parameters combine to impact wind performance. The study considered the performance of empty grain bins, only, given the known susceptibility. This study shows that the largest capacity bins, which tend to be both tall and wide, are more vulnerable than small bins; and, bins with highest exposure, such as those in open fields, are much more vulnerable than those located near other agricultural structures. Site-specific case studies were conducted in which nearby, similar grain bins that were exposed to similar wind speeds were compared. From this, it can be seen that vertical stiffeners can significantly enhance performance, while roof venting can similarly reduce performance.  Over the span of the two-year project, four undergraduate students and two graduate students were directly mentored by the Principal Investigator in research and became knowledge in the advanced areas of wind, structural, agricultural, and hazards engineering. The research has yielded one peer-reviewed conference presentation, several presentations, and two peer-reviewed journal articles. This research has also been disseminated via mass media and is anticipated to be leveraged for standards development in future years. All data has been made publicly available via NHERI DesignSafe-CI.         Last Modified: 12/30/2022       Submitted by: Christine Wittich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
