<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Integrated Manufacturing of Artificial Valves for Medical Use]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255619.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255619</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to improve clinical outcomes for patients needing valves for vascular (veins) or urinary systems.  It is difficult to make artificial versions of the fluid control elements, such as valves, that are biocompatible and withstand the physical forces associated with their function, as well as the changing environment associated with aging. The proposed project advances a system to make artificial sutureless devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will optimize the materials and variables of manufacturing a polymer valve integrated with durable polymer encapsulation of a structural Nitinol frame. This Nitinol-polymer structure must withstand long-term challenging in vivo conditions while maintaining a physical interface that does not experience premature delamination and loss of device functionality. Polyurethane materials have excellent mechanical properties for rigorous applications and history of use in implants. This project explores the phase space of relevant parameters for manufacturing and deployment of these valves at scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051102</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>JANET</FirstName>
<LastName>Galtes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>JANET Galtes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jburpee@venarummedical.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000781736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>VENARUM MEDICAL, LLC</Name>
<CityName>EATONTOWN</CityName>
<ZipCode>077242267</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7329968513</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>20 MERIDIAN RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UNIT 9A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>P6KYJ2ERJXH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VENARUM MEDICAL LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E6TEEKPCEH43</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[VENARUM MEDICAL, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Eatontown</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>077242270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[20 Meridian Road, Unit 9A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255619</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The proliferation of medical devices to treat challenging diseases and conditions has led to broad improvements in the health and quality of life of people and pets worldwide. The advancement of the manufacturing technologies, such as Venarum?s proprietary integrated valve manufacturing process (?<strong>IV-Process</strong>?), has enabled creation of devices that previously were too complex to consistently manufacture.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Venarum?s intended first commercial device using the IV-Process is its Canine INCONTrol Urethral Valve system (?<strong>K9&#8208;ICT?</strong>).&nbsp; The K9-ICT is a novel urethral implant solution for the treatment of urinary incontinence (?<strong>UI?</strong>) in canines.&nbsp; The transurethral, catheter&#8208;delivered K9&#8208;ICT is intended to work with the natural voiding initiation mechanism to control the flow of urine in order to reduce urine leakage and other complications of UI.&nbsp; Treating canine UI in a durable single treatment would give both dogs and dog owners a significant, cost-effective and lasting improvement to quality of life<em>.</em><strong> </strong>Successful development, demonstration and commercialization of a durable and biomimetic treatment for canine UI will provide valuable understanding for the treatment of urinary flow disorders.&nbsp;</p> <p>Soon after the onset of this Phase I development, the K9-ICT valve mechanism design was changed from a complex inverted valve with hysteresis to a relief valve, and with this, prong features were added to the frame.&nbsp; The goals under the NSF funding were met and the new design and manufacturing development allowed each aspect of the flow performance to be controlled and adjusted as needed to meet device requirements. &nbsp;The implemented improvements and controls reduced variability in orifice cut quality and dimensions, prong heat treatment and design, and valve coating thickness, which all contribute to overall device delivery, implantation, and flow performance.&nbsp; The mechanical aspects of the K9-ICT implant were demonstrated through simulated-use bench testing, a holistic flow performance bench test, and later verified in chronic animal testing. The bench flow testing showed significant improvement in valve control and repeatability as a result of the completed grant work.&nbsp; The development work culminated with a single chronic animal study in a model canine to preliminarily verify the device improvements and functionality of the implant and associated system as intended for the commercial use of the K9-ICT device. The sterilized system was successfully used to implant a single K9-ICT implant device into the urethra as intended. The canine exhibited normal urination over 3 days, as intended for the total in-life study duration.</p> <p>While the current product is focused on canine patients, we expect the outcomes will contribute to a path forward for a similar UI device for treatments of humans.&nbsp; In general, the IV-Process provides the ability to make novel three dimensional fully encapsulated devices with an integrated centric valve, and ability to be implanted by minimally invasive procedure.&nbsp; With the IV-Process, Venarum hopes to offer the medical device community implantable products where optimization of bodily fluid flow is paramount to success.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/06/2022<br>      Modified by: Janet&nbsp;Burpee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The proliferation of medical devices to treat challenging diseases and conditions has led to broad improvements in the health and quality of life of people and pets worldwide. The advancement of the manufacturing technologies, such as Venarum?s proprietary integrated valve manufacturing process (?IV-Process?), has enabled creation of devices that previously were too complex to consistently manufacture.  Venarum?s intended first commercial device using the IV-Process is its Canine INCONTrol Urethral Valve system (?K9&#8208;ICT?).  The K9-ICT is a novel urethral implant solution for the treatment of urinary incontinence (?UI?) in canines.  The transurethral, catheter&#8208;delivered K9&#8208;ICT is intended to work with the natural voiding initiation mechanism to control the flow of urine in order to reduce urine leakage and other complications of UI.  Treating canine UI in a durable single treatment would give both dogs and dog owners a significant, cost-effective and lasting improvement to quality of life. Successful development, demonstration and commercialization of a durable and biomimetic treatment for canine UI will provide valuable understanding for the treatment of urinary flow disorders.   Soon after the onset of this Phase I development, the K9-ICT valve mechanism design was changed from a complex inverted valve with hysteresis to a relief valve, and with this, prong features were added to the frame.  The goals under the NSF funding were met and the new design and manufacturing development allowed each aspect of the flow performance to be controlled and adjusted as needed to meet device requirements.  The implemented improvements and controls reduced variability in orifice cut quality and dimensions, prong heat treatment and design, and valve coating thickness, which all contribute to overall device delivery, implantation, and flow performance.  The mechanical aspects of the K9-ICT implant were demonstrated through simulated-use bench testing, a holistic flow performance bench test, and later verified in chronic animal testing. The bench flow testing showed significant improvement in valve control and repeatability as a result of the completed grant work.  The development work culminated with a single chronic animal study in a model canine to preliminarily verify the device improvements and functionality of the implant and associated system as intended for the commercial use of the K9-ICT device. The sterilized system was successfully used to implant a single K9-ICT implant device into the urethra as intended. The canine exhibited normal urination over 3 days, as intended for the total in-life study duration.  While the current product is focused on canine patients, we expect the outcomes will contribute to a path forward for a similar UI device for treatments of humans.  In general, the IV-Process provides the ability to make novel three dimensional fully encapsulated devices with an integrated centric valve, and ability to be implanted by minimally invasive procedure.  With the IV-Process, Venarum hopes to offer the medical device community implantable products where optimization of bodily fluid flow is paramount to success.           Last Modified: 10/06/2022       Submitted by: Janet Burpee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
