<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Genetically Engineered Dendritic Cell to Activate SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein specific-T Cell (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact /commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a specific immunoprotective cell therapy using the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (Sp) to boost immunity against COVID-19, especially with comorbidities. A durable competitive advantage reflects immune cell engineering with novel coronavirus Sp as a new technological advancement for stem cell-based immunotherapy (SCT) to treat viral diseases, diabetes, autoimmune disorders, or cancer. Use of SCT against SARS-CoV-2 or new virus strains will prevent COVID-19 and post-infection complications, reduce the chance of future pandemics, and strengthen the local and national economy.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop a "DC-COV19" probe system to eradicate severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), which killed more than 400,000 people in the United States. Our long-term goal is to develop a potent COVID-19 T cell-based immunotherapy (vaccine-like) for high-risk populations to stop or reduce SARS-CoV-2 infections. The SARS-CoV-2 vaccines target neutralizing antibodies but only rely on the endogenous production of T cells.  Major Gap: COVID-19 patients showed a significant reduction in the number and function of T cells and required robust vaccine or immunotherapeutic strategies to boost SARS-CoV-2-specific CD4+ and CD8+ T cells. NeyroblastGX LLC (NGL) proposes to develop a probe from dendritic cells (DCs) derived from established genetically engineered human embryonic stem cells (hESC) transfected with SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (Sp). This "DC-COV19" probe will be used to produce high numbers of functional SARS-CoV-2-specific CD4+ and CD8+ T cells ex vivo. Autologous immune T cells will be transferred into COVID-19 patients as a rapid and robust adaptive T cell-based immunotherapy. NGL works with world-class immunologists and clinicians to develop several Sp constructs engineered to transfect DCs to selectively activate SARS-CoV-2-specific CD4+ and CD8+ T cells to fight COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051522</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aynun</FirstName>
<LastName>Begum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aynun N Begum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aynunbegum@live.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826468</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NEYROBLASTGX LLC</Name>
<CityName>MURRIETA</CityName>
<ZipCode>925627022</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8183573018</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>26442 BECKMAN CT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>48</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA48</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>D7H1LWMAP6J3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEYROBLASTGX LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NEYROBLASTGX LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Murrieta</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925627022</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[26442 Beckman Ct.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>48</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA48</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NeyroblastGX LLC (NGL) developed genetically engineered dendritic cells (DC)s, which can successfully produce a DC-COV19 probe that activates significant levels of CD4<sup>+ </sup>and CD8<sup>+ </sup>T cells to generate protective T cell therapy against new and existing SARS-CoV-2 variants and chronic infections. To develop a highly efficient genetically engineered DC epitope (eDC), we first generated fully functional DCs from human induced pluripotent stem cells (HiPSCs) under good manufacturing practice (cGMP) conditions which can be used for training Sp-specific T cells from the patient. Our DC is generated from HiPSCs on a robust and cGMP scale. We established that our DC is highly functional and can phagocytose the beads with a capability of over 90%. Immature and mature DC markers were established to determine DC&rsquo;s extensive functional activity and morphological characteristics with CD209<sup>+</sup>,<sup> </sup>CD11C<sup>+</sup>, CD40<sup>+</sup>, CD86<sup>+</sup>, HLA-DRA<sup>+,</sup> and MHC Class II<sup>+</sup> (MHCII) expressing cells with &gt;85% efficiency. Moreover, HLA-DRA<sup>+</sup> and MHCII<sup>+</sup> expression was over 90%, crucial molecules for antigen-presenting cells like DCs to bind with T cell receptor (TCR) to activate CD4<sup>+ </sup>and CD8<sup>+ </sup>T cells. These highly functional DCs were then ready to genetically engineer with Sp constructs. We found our DCs transduced with various Sp epitopes with 80% efficiency.</p> <p>With our eDC epitope&rsquo;s robust response to activating functional T cells, we understand eDCs are not limited to Sp-specific as current SARS-CoV-2 vaccines but can be used for membrane (M) and nucleocapsid (N) or other viral protein-specific immunity. So, we also exposed various other pathogenic viral proteins to our DC. We found a robust and significant response (<em>p&lt;0.05</em>) in the Long COVID patient&rsquo;s CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells with increased levels of IFN-&gamma; secretion that can be used for treating Long COVID and other chronic viral infections.</p> <p>In this context, DC-COV19 can provide their autologous T cells to protect them from SARS-CoV-2, and other pathogenic viruses, reducing the risk of multiple infections and saving lives. Therefore, our DC-COV19 will provide immediate treatment against viral and pathogen infection for autoimmune disorders, Long COVID, and chronic conditions where traditional vaccination poses a greater risk. We plan to disseminate these results through journal publications and trade association conference presentations to attract investors and customers and globally promote public awareness. Building this technology will involve workforce development for hospitals and local health centers. It will also engage the community to supply economic benefits and overall social impacts.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Aynun&nbsp;N&nbsp;Begum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NeyroblastGX LLC (NGL) developed genetically engineered dendritic cells (DC)s, which can successfully produce a DC-COV19 probe that activates significant levels of CD4+ and CD8+ T cells to generate protective T cell therapy against new and existing SARS-CoV-2 variants and chronic infections. To develop a highly efficient genetically engineered DC epitope (eDC), we first generated fully functional DCs from human induced pluripotent stem cells (HiPSCs) under good manufacturing practice (cGMP) conditions which can be used for training Sp-specific T cells from the patient. Our DC is generated from HiPSCs on a robust and cGMP scale. We established that our DC is highly functional and can phagocytose the beads with a capability of over 90%. Immature and mature DC markers were established to determine DC’s extensive functional activity and morphological characteristics with CD209+, CD11C+, CD40+, CD86+, HLA-DRA+, and MHC Class II+ (MHCII) expressing cells with &gt;85% efficiency. Moreover, HLA-DRA+ and MHCII+ expression was over 90%, crucial molecules for antigen-presenting cells like DCs to bind with T cell receptor (TCR) to activate CD4+ and CD8+ T cells. These highly functional DCs were then ready to genetically engineer with Sp constructs. We found our DCs transduced with various Sp epitopes with 80% efficiency.  With our eDC epitope’s robust response to activating functional T cells, we understand eDCs are not limited to Sp-specific as current SARS-CoV-2 vaccines but can be used for membrane (M) and nucleocapsid (N) or other viral protein-specific immunity. So, we also exposed various other pathogenic viral proteins to our DC. We found a robust and significant response (p&lt;0.05) in the Long COVID patient’s CD4+ T cells with increased levels of IFN-&gamma; secretion that can be used for treating Long COVID and other chronic viral infections.  In this context, DC-COV19 can provide their autologous T cells to protect them from SARS-CoV-2, and other pathogenic viruses, reducing the risk of multiple infections and saving lives. Therefore, our DC-COV19 will provide immediate treatment against viral and pathogen infection for autoimmune disorders, Long COVID, and chronic conditions where traditional vaccination poses a greater risk. We plan to disseminate these results through journal publications and trade association conference presentations to attract investors and customers and globally promote public awareness. Building this technology will involve workforce development for hospitals and local health centers. It will also engage the community to supply economic benefits and overall social impacts.           Last Modified: 04/01/2023       Submitted by: Aynun N Begum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
