<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Novel System for Diagnosis of Vision Disorders]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to rapidly screen for binocular vision disorders that impact over 20% of the general population. Unlike simple vision problems that can be corrected for with glasses, binocular vision disorders take longer to treat, and are typically underdiagnosed. Childhood diagnosis of these vision disorders is correlated with attention disorders and poor performance in school, so early detection and treatment is vital to student success.The proposed project advances development of a virtual reality system for diagnosis of vision problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will develop a virtual reality screening platform for a variety of binocular vision disorders. It will take advantage of eye-tracking technology to precisely measure the eye movements of the wearer in response to specifically designed visual stimuli. Software will rapidly and automatically quantify recorded eye movements and correlate them to real-world values, which optometrists can use to make meaningful diagnostic decisions. The technology described in this proposal will be tested on many users to verify its ability to screen for a wide variety of disorders in a diverse population.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051797</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Migle</FirstName>
<LastName>Surblyte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Migle Surblyte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[migle@omtvr.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000902479</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John Vito</FirstName>
<LastName>d'Antonio-Bertagnolli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Vito d'Antonio-Bertagnolli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ceo@oculomotortechnologies.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779344</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/21/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>OCULOMOTOR TECHNOLOGIES INC.</Name>
<CityName>PRINCETON</CityName>
<ZipCode>085405765</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735585456</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>155 VILLAGE BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 130]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XJ17ZWMBBKV9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OCULOMOTOR TECHNOLOGIES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[OculoMotor Technologies]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071033568</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[211 Warren Street, Suite 412]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project aims to develop a pilot-scale production system called Screening Protocol for Oculomotor Telemedicine (SPOT). SPOT, an eye-tracking enabled virtual reality-based tool, will allow optometrists to overcome the multitude of shortfalls of traditional diagnostic screening for binocular vision disorders. By condensing a full binocular vision screening process, which can require as many as a dozen tests and up to twenty minutes, into a single device capable of rapidly performing the same screening processes in under 5 minutes with greater precision, the optometrist gains not only valuable diagnostic data, but also invaluable face-to-face time with the patient. This decreases the total appointment time, allowing additional patients to be scheduled. Use of this tool will enable the optometrist to easily generate and document the objective screening results necessary in their medical chart to appropriately support use of higher-level reimbursement codes.</span></p> <p><br /><span>The broader/commercial impacts of this project will be the potential to provide a low-cost, high-volume process to identify binocular disfunctions. This system can potentially be used in school systems around the country to screen for visual dysfunctions and refer school-aged students to nearby optometrists or ophthalmologists. Finally, this tool can help rural areas without specialized personnel identify the care pathway necessary to improve ones visual quality of life.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Migle&nbsp;Surblyte</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project aims to develop a pilot-scale production system called Screening Protocol for Oculomotor Telemedicine (SPOT). SPOT, an eye-tracking enabled virtual reality-based tool, will allow optometrists to overcome the multitude of shortfalls of traditional diagnostic screening for binocular vision disorders. By condensing a full binocular vision screening process, which can require as many as a dozen tests and up to twenty minutes, into a single device capable of rapidly performing the same screening processes in under 5 minutes with greater precision, the optometrist gains not only valuable diagnostic data, but also invaluable face-to-face time with the patient. This decreases the total appointment time, allowing additional patients to be scheduled. Use of this tool will enable the optometrist to easily generate and document the objective screening results necessary in their medical chart to appropriately support use of higher-level reimbursement codes.   The broader/commercial impacts of this project will be the potential to provide a low-cost, high-volume process to identify binocular disfunctions. This system can potentially be used in school systems around the country to screen for visual dysfunctions and refer school-aged students to nearby optometrists or ophthalmologists. Finally, this tool can help rural areas without specialized personnel identify the care pathway necessary to improve ones visual quality of life.       Last Modified: 07/03/2023       Submitted by: Migle Surblyte]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
