<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A novel, microfluidic device to improve collection and analysis of biopsy samples from ocular paracentesis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to improve diagnosis of eye conditions with a better tool for ocular fluid biopsies. Ocular fluid biopsies are important in diagnosis and treatment, but this procedure is under-utilized due to flaws with the current method for collecting fluid; furthermore, the fluid in the eye is isolated from the rest of the body, so blood work does not help in diagnosis. Because of this, most ocular infections are diagnosed and treated based on their clinical appearance without additional data from fluid testing. This research will advance a new tool to collect ocular fluid safely and effectively. This will aid in diagnosis of sight-threatening conditions including macular degeneration, glaucoma and ocular infections, enabling earlier diagnosis and improving patient outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) I Project will advance a new medical device for ocular fluid biopsies. Ocular fluid biopsies can be used for conditions beyond infections in the eye. The proposed instrument will be designed specifically for collection of fluid from the front of the eye. Tasks include: (1) optimization of the needle to decrease the force of entry to enhance the surgeon’s control and decrease risk of injury; (2) investigation of the fluid dynamics of collection with the integration of a microfluidic chamber and specialized collection system designed to handle small fluid volumes because the current method leads to fluid loss and inaccurate results. Additional work will evaluate advanced engineering features to enhance safety for this procedure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051962</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
<LastName>Gorsuch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alex Gorsuch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aegorsuch@magpiinnovations.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779444</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/21/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Mental</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Mental</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rickmental@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000851892</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>VISIONAIRE PRODUCTS, INC</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152382239</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4123271114</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>218 FIELD CLUB RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CUKAFNSRJWJ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VISIONAIRE PRODUCTS, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Visionaire Products]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207460</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[60 Hazelwood Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ocular fluid biopsy is an important procedure in ophthalmology. It is currently used to aid in the diagnosis of ocular inflammation caused by infection and some eye cancers.<sup> </sup>It is also used in emergency situations to relieve high pressure from the eye.<sup> </sup>Currently, the tools used for ocular fluid biopsy are limited because they are not specifically designed for ocular use. This research addressed those limitations by creating a customized tool that improves the ability to perform ocular fluid biopsies with a safer, more efficient, and effective system for collection. <em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>The result of this research is a novel, hand-held surgical tool that can be used to obtain a sample of fluid from the front of the eye. We created a customized needle for insertion through the cornea that would limit injury to surrounding tissue. With advanced engineering concepts, we redesigned the collection chamber and fluid channel using microfluidic principles and vacuum assisted devices. Needle force testing was performed first on standard foil, then on bovine and porcine eyes, which are the most like human eyes. Based on the results, the needle characteristics were honed to obtain the optimal fluid extraction while minimizing entry force and subsequent wound leaks. &nbsp;</p> <p>We engaged experts in fluid flow dynamics and modeling microfluidic channels to understand the pressure gradient required to design a system for fluid capture of this small volume of fluid in an appropriate time window. From this work, a novel fluid collection system using a vacuum-assisted chamber was developed. The levers and buttons that control the device were engineered to be intuitive to the end-user. The design of the hand-held base was created using a multidisciplinary approach that combined input from industrial design experts, ophthalmologists, and production managers so that the final design included aspects of ease of use, functionality, and manufacturability. Early models were sent to end users for design feedback and interactions.</p> <p>The result of this work is a device that improves safety and handling for this procedure. This will increase use of this procedure which will change the standard of care in ophthalmology for ocular fluid biopsies. This can open the possibility to have access to more objective data when treating patients. This objective data can be obtained from testing of the fluid obtained from the biopsy. This can guide care, standardize treatment approaches, and improve patient outcomes. In cases of ocular inflammation, this tool can help to save vision in patients with infectious causes of ocular inflammation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;Mental</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ocular fluid biopsy is an important procedure in ophthalmology. It is currently used to aid in the diagnosis of ocular inflammation caused by infection and some eye cancers. It is also used in emergency situations to relieve high pressure from the eye. Currently, the tools used for ocular fluid biopsy are limited because they are not specifically designed for ocular use. This research addressed those limitations by creating a customized tool that improves the ability to perform ocular fluid biopsies with a safer, more efficient, and effective system for collection.    The result of this research is a novel, hand-held surgical tool that can be used to obtain a sample of fluid from the front of the eye. We created a customized needle for insertion through the cornea that would limit injury to surrounding tissue. With advanced engineering concepts, we redesigned the collection chamber and fluid channel using microfluidic principles and vacuum assisted devices. Needle force testing was performed first on standard foil, then on bovine and porcine eyes, which are the most like human eyes. Based on the results, the needle characteristics were honed to obtain the optimal fluid extraction while minimizing entry force and subsequent wound leaks.    We engaged experts in fluid flow dynamics and modeling microfluidic channels to understand the pressure gradient required to design a system for fluid capture of this small volume of fluid in an appropriate time window. From this work, a novel fluid collection system using a vacuum-assisted chamber was developed. The levers and buttons that control the device were engineered to be intuitive to the end-user. The design of the hand-held base was created using a multidisciplinary approach that combined input from industrial design experts, ophthalmologists, and production managers so that the final design included aspects of ease of use, functionality, and manufacturability. Early models were sent to end users for design feedback and interactions.  The result of this work is a device that improves safety and handling for this procedure. This will increase use of this procedure which will change the standard of care in ophthalmology for ocular fluid biopsies. This can open the possibility to have access to more objective data when treating patients. This objective data can be obtained from testing of the fluid obtained from the biopsy. This can guide care, standardize treatment approaches, and improve patient outcomes. In cases of ocular inflammation, this tool can help to save vision in patients with infectious causes of ocular inflammation.          Last Modified: 09/21/2021       Submitted by: Richard Mental]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
