<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Hydrogen from Hydrogen Sulfide]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>254400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>254400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is advancing a technology that allows the economically advantageous reduction of carbon emissions in many different fields of the energy sector. Sour sulfur-rich gases are often a byproduct in settings including biorefineries, gas processing facilities, petrochemical and fuel refineries, landfills, pulp and paper manufacturing, and waste processing facilities. The proposed technology has potential to provide a low cost and low carbon hydrogen product. This hydrogen can be used locally to displace current fossil fuel-based hydrogen feedstocks or sold as an additional alternative hydrogen product.  The technology has potential to both enable market incumbents to meet their aggressive carbon emission reduction goals and facilitate new technologies that require hydrogen as either a chemical feedstock or as an energy source. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to optimize a thermochemical hydrogen production technology based on a novel sulfur-iodine cycle. Reducing the carbon intensity of hydrogen manufacturing while keeping production costs commercially relevant has remained elusive despite significant interest. The proposed project advances a new process with significant reductions in energy requirements, improvements in heat integration, and more facile process stream separations compared to predecessor technologies. It also utilizes a low value waste stream as the principal feedstock. Technical tasks include optimizing the mass transfer qualities of the gas-liquid contactor by varying nozzle configuration, packing material, and reactor geometry, preparing a highly detailed process and techno-economic model at both the demonstration and commercial scale, and the design of a pilot demonstration unit for use at a sour associated gas well-site.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051995</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gillis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan J Gillis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ryan@thiozen.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000835031</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>THIOZEN INC.</Name>
<CityName>BEVERLY</CityName>
<ZipCode>019156132</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798249108</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 CUMMINGS CTR STE 451C</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RBD3WJQKJNJ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THIOZEN INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[THIOZEN INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Belmont</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024783903</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[35 Becket Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~254400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Hydrogen is an important feedstock in the production of fuels and chemicals but its production is polluting and carbon-intensive, generating approximately 2% of all anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions. Hydrogen demand is dominated by large cost-sensitive commodity chemical manufacturers who are simultaneously facing an increased need for hydrogen to raise profits and meet environmental standards but also rising regulatory and societal pressure limiting the construction of additional carbon-intensive hydrogen production infrastructure. The patented chemical cycle for the production of hydrogen from hydrogen sulfide studied in this SBIR Phase I project, by replacing traditional hydrogen production, will reduce global greenhouse gas emissions by over 500 million metric tons per year and improve the air quality and respiratory health of communities living near current hydrogen infrastructure. All while providing cost-sensitive firms a path to both procuring additional hydrogen and lowering the carbon intensity of their products.</p> <p>The objective of the SBIR Phase I project was the preparation of this novel hydrogen from hydrogen sulfide chemical cycle for piloting in natural gas processing markets. This included experimental campaigns testing raw natural gas mixtures in the chemical cycle and process modeling predicting the costs and carbon intensity of hydrogen production. The project concluded successfully and because of the project Thiozen was able to secure a site for the demonstration of the technology at a natural gas collection facility. The processing unit is expected to begin operation in 2023 as a result of the Phase I project.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project was comprised of 7 activities and their associated deliverables, 4 focused on technoeconomic evaluation and 3 focused on experimental validation and process unit design.&nbsp; Specifically, this involved the creation of detailed technoeconomic models for the Thiozen Cycle implemented at scales of (a) 0.05 tons per day (b) 3.5 tons per day and (c) 150 tons per day. (d) An estimator to predict the costs and carbon intensity of the technology at a variety of scales was produced. Experimental validation of (e) binary and (f) natural gas surrogate mixtures in the Thiozen reactive absorber were performed. Finally, based on the results of the experimental campaigns (g) a reactive absorber for a natural gas pilot was sized and designed. Each of these activities was successfully completed enabling the further commercialization of the technology into natural gas markets and paving the way for validation in other hydrogen sulfide-rich markets.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Ryan&nbsp;J&nbsp;Gillis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051995/2051995_10775567_1668018597290_OutcomesReportFigure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051995/2051995_10775567_1668018597290_OutcomesReportFigure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hydrogen From Hydrogen Sulfide"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051995/2051995_10775567_1668018597290_OutcomesReportFigure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hydrogen From Hydrogen Sulfide"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This figure shows the advantages of the developed hydrogen from hydrogen sulfide cycle compared to traditional hydrogen manufacturing.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Thiozen Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ryan&nbsp;J&nbsp;Gillis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hydrogen From Hydrogen Sulfide</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Hydrogen is an important feedstock in the production of fuels and chemicals but its production is polluting and carbon-intensive, generating approximately 2% of all anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions. Hydrogen demand is dominated by large cost-sensitive commodity chemical manufacturers who are simultaneously facing an increased need for hydrogen to raise profits and meet environmental standards but also rising regulatory and societal pressure limiting the construction of additional carbon-intensive hydrogen production infrastructure. The patented chemical cycle for the production of hydrogen from hydrogen sulfide studied in this SBIR Phase I project, by replacing traditional hydrogen production, will reduce global greenhouse gas emissions by over 500 million metric tons per year and improve the air quality and respiratory health of communities living near current hydrogen infrastructure. All while providing cost-sensitive firms a path to both procuring additional hydrogen and lowering the carbon intensity of their products.  The objective of the SBIR Phase I project was the preparation of this novel hydrogen from hydrogen sulfide chemical cycle for piloting in natural gas processing markets. This included experimental campaigns testing raw natural gas mixtures in the chemical cycle and process modeling predicting the costs and carbon intensity of hydrogen production. The project concluded successfully and because of the project Thiozen was able to secure a site for the demonstration of the technology at a natural gas collection facility. The processing unit is expected to begin operation in 2023 as a result of the Phase I project.   The project was comprised of 7 activities and their associated deliverables, 4 focused on technoeconomic evaluation and 3 focused on experimental validation and process unit design.  Specifically, this involved the creation of detailed technoeconomic models for the Thiozen Cycle implemented at scales of (a) 0.05 tons per day (b) 3.5 tons per day and (c) 150 tons per day. (d) An estimator to predict the costs and carbon intensity of the technology at a variety of scales was produced. Experimental validation of (e) binary and (f) natural gas surrogate mixtures in the Thiozen reactive absorber were performed. Finally, based on the results of the experimental campaigns (g) a reactive absorber for a natural gas pilot was sized and designed. Each of these activities was successfully completed enabling the further commercialization of the technology into natural gas markets and paving the way for validation in other hydrogen sulfide-rich markets.          Last Modified: 11/09/2022       Submitted by: Ryan J Gillis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
