<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Nanocellulose-based Adjuvant for Reducing Herbicide Drift]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255913.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275913</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer Research (STTR) Phase I project is in addressing the pressing problem of herbicide drift. For years, farmers growing organic, non-genetically modified (non-GM) and specialty crops have incurred crop damage and financial losses due to drift of volatile herbicides, such as dicamba. The EPA estimates that up to 70 million pounds of pesticides, including herbicides, are lost to the environment due to drift each year. In 2017 alone, 3.6 million acres of soybeans were destroyed due to dicamba drifting away from its site of application. This project addresses the problem with a novel technology that reduces herbicide volatility and drift. This technology will help farmers growing GM-crops who face litigation because they spray drifting dicamba, and those who grow non-GM-crops and do not want drifted dicamba to impact their produce. Agrochemical companies currently facing EPA restrictions, product bans, and billions of dollars in lawsuits, can use this technology to improve the application efficiency of their products. This technology offers significant environmental benefits. Furthermore, beyond its agricultural use, the bio-based formulation is a platform technology that may be used to develop other applications from food to pharmaceuticals to cosmetics.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The innovation proposed in this STTR Phase I project is a bio-based emulsion adjuvant, derived from renewable resources, with the combined functionality of a drift control agent, buffering agent, and surfactant, to reduce the volatility and off-target movement of herbicides, and improve their efficacy. The proposed adjuvant offers encapsulating, environmental and financial benefits relative to the state of practice.  The project has the following objectives to evaluate and demonstrate the technical feasibility of the innovation: 1) develop and optimize the composition of the formulation, 2) characterize properties important for its use in herbicide spray mixtures, such as surface tension, thermal stability, fluid flow, water conditioning and defoaming behavior,  3) conduct humidome tests and field trials to validate the effectiveness of the formulation with respect to fine spray droplets suspended in the air  and herbicide activity against pigweed (Palmer amaranth), using dicamba as the model herbicide, and 4) determine the biodegradability profile of the formulation in soil and water environments and its aquatic toxicity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051607</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Batta-Mpouma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph Batta-Mpouma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[josephbmp19@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CELLUDOT LLC</Name>
<CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>727016069</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4792000570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>123 W MOUNTAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G43RHY4PX1R8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CELLUDOT LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CELLUDOT LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727016069</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[123 W Mountain St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255913</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The innovative research conducted by CelluDot LLC for this NSF STTR Phase I project was to develop a bio-based emulsion adjuvant, using cellulosic nanomaterials derived from renewable resources as core components, to solve the pressing problem of herbicide drift. The nanocellulose-based adjuvant (NA), a patent-pending technology, minimizes the off-target movement (drift) of volatile herbicides, including but not limited to dicamba. The NA can be commercialized as a stand-alone or an all-in-one product due to its multiple functionalities, including those of a surfactant, drift reducing agent (DRA) and volatility reducing agent (VRA).</p> <p>CelluDot?s key findings for this STTR Phase I project are as follows: a) the bio-based adjuvant has a shear thinning behavior, which is suitable for easy flow through commercial nozzles typically used for pesticide (including herbicide) application, b) its surface tension is in the target range (30-50 mN/m), and hence sticking/spreading capability is comparable to that of commercial surfactants commonly used with herbicides, c) the formulation can be tuned to act like a non-ionic surfactant or an anionic surfactant for use with herbicides, d) droplet distribution of dicamba fell in the ultra-coarse category and hence showed DRA characteristics, as per low-speed wind tunnel testing, e) compared to the current commercial standard VRA, humidome testing showed 50% reduction in dicamba volatility, f) the adjuvant formulation was found to be as efficacious as the current commercial standard VRA in terms of pigweed control (validated by 90-100% plant injury in green house testing), and this was verified with two pigweed accessions differing in their sensitivity to dicamba, g) the adjuvant can be paired with any agrochemical, and finally, h) it is inherently biodegradable and does not have any toxic effects on freshwater and micro-organisms based on OECD 302B and OECD 201 tests, respectively.</p> <p>For years, farmers growing organic, non-genetically modified (non-GM) \ crops have been incurring damage and financial losses due to drift of volatile herbicides such as dicamba. The EPA estimates that up to 70 million pounds of pesticides, including herbicides, are lost to the environment due to drift each year. Volatility of herbicides such as dicamba and the resulting overspray is a significant problem today, as is evident in daily news reports. The adverse effects of drift have been felt across the country by farmers growing sensitive and specialty crops. Moreover, by pitting farmer against farmer and embroiling them in legal battles, herbicide drift has caused severe social tensions in farming communities. CelluDot?s product (BioGrip<sup>TM</sup>) will enable farmers growing GM crops to continue using dicamba without worrying about the financial and legal implications associated with herbicides drifting to neighboring farms and damaging non-GM or any sensitive crops and landscapes, thus restoring, and maintaining the social fabric of the farming community and boosting agricultural productivity.</p> <p>CelluDot participated in the NSF SBIR/STTR I-Corps and conducted 100+ interviews across the stakeholder spectrum to further assess the commercialization potential of their technology. With these customer interviews, CelluDot was able to identify a ?beachhead? market, as well as key partners needed to achieve a product-market fit. It was confirmed that manufacturers and/or distributors of agrochemical and/or adjuvants that constantly face EPA restrictions, product bans, and potentially billions of dollars in lawsuits, will benefit from the innovation and use this technology to improve their sales as they can demonstrate the use of their herbicide in combination with CelluDot?s adjuvant reduces drifting events. The biodegradable nature of BioGrip and its ability to reduce herbicide volatility is crucial to advance the use of this novel product in agriculture and reduce the negative impacts of herbicide drift on&nbsp; society and the environment, including air, water, soil, and bee populations. Widespread use of dicamba throughout the growing season harms other crops as well as wild and native plants, degrading food sources for wildlife and bee pollinators. After market penetration of BioGrip, we anticipate, there will be less devastating economic impacts on rural life and dicamba will no longer be a threat to the natural ecosystem as the herbicide will stick to the plant and not propagate in the environment. This STTR Phase I project and research plan reflect NSF?s statutory mission of improving US national economy and health, as well as protecting the environment for the well-being of individuals.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;Batta-Mpouma</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051607/2051607_10729047_1659197553368_CelluDotPOR--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051607/2051607_10729047_1659197553368_CelluDotPOR--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CelluDot's adjuvant: how it works"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051607/2051607_10729047_1659197553368_CelluDotPOR--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CelluDot's adjuvant: how it works"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Greenhouse Pigweed Efficacy</div> <div class="imageCredit">Excellent</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;Batta-Mpouma</div> <div class="imageTitle">CelluDot's adjuvant: how it works</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The innovative research conducted by CelluDot LLC for this NSF STTR Phase I project was to develop a bio-based emulsion adjuvant, using cellulosic nanomaterials derived from renewable resources as core components, to solve the pressing problem of herbicide drift. The nanocellulose-based adjuvant (NA), a patent-pending technology, minimizes the off-target movement (drift) of volatile herbicides, including but not limited to dicamba. The NA can be commercialized as a stand-alone or an all-in-one product due to its multiple functionalities, including those of a surfactant, drift reducing agent (DRA) and volatility reducing agent (VRA).  CelluDot?s key findings for this STTR Phase I project are as follows: a) the bio-based adjuvant has a shear thinning behavior, which is suitable for easy flow through commercial nozzles typically used for pesticide (including herbicide) application, b) its surface tension is in the target range (30-50 mN/m), and hence sticking/spreading capability is comparable to that of commercial surfactants commonly used with herbicides, c) the formulation can be tuned to act like a non-ionic surfactant or an anionic surfactant for use with herbicides, d) droplet distribution of dicamba fell in the ultra-coarse category and hence showed DRA characteristics, as per low-speed wind tunnel testing, e) compared to the current commercial standard VRA, humidome testing showed 50% reduction in dicamba volatility, f) the adjuvant formulation was found to be as efficacious as the current commercial standard VRA in terms of pigweed control (validated by 90-100% plant injury in green house testing), and this was verified with two pigweed accessions differing in their sensitivity to dicamba, g) the adjuvant can be paired with any agrochemical, and finally, h) it is inherently biodegradable and does not have any toxic effects on freshwater and micro-organisms based on OECD 302B and OECD 201 tests, respectively.  For years, farmers growing organic, non-genetically modified (non-GM) \ crops have been incurring damage and financial losses due to drift of volatile herbicides such as dicamba. The EPA estimates that up to 70 million pounds of pesticides, including herbicides, are lost to the environment due to drift each year. Volatility of herbicides such as dicamba and the resulting overspray is a significant problem today, as is evident in daily news reports. The adverse effects of drift have been felt across the country by farmers growing sensitive and specialty crops. Moreover, by pitting farmer against farmer and embroiling them in legal battles, herbicide drift has caused severe social tensions in farming communities. CelluDot?s product (BioGripTM) will enable farmers growing GM crops to continue using dicamba without worrying about the financial and legal implications associated with herbicides drifting to neighboring farms and damaging non-GM or any sensitive crops and landscapes, thus restoring, and maintaining the social fabric of the farming community and boosting agricultural productivity.  CelluDot participated in the NSF SBIR/STTR I-Corps and conducted 100+ interviews across the stakeholder spectrum to further assess the commercialization potential of their technology. With these customer interviews, CelluDot was able to identify a ?beachhead? market, as well as key partners needed to achieve a product-market fit. It was confirmed that manufacturers and/or distributors of agrochemical and/or adjuvants that constantly face EPA restrictions, product bans, and potentially billions of dollars in lawsuits, will benefit from the innovation and use this technology to improve their sales as they can demonstrate the use of their herbicide in combination with CelluDot?s adjuvant reduces drifting events. The biodegradable nature of BioGrip and its ability to reduce herbicide volatility is crucial to advance the use of this novel product in agriculture and reduce the negative impacts of herbicide drift on  society and the environment, including air, water, soil, and bee populations. Widespread use of dicamba throughout the growing season harms other crops as well as wild and native plants, degrading food sources for wildlife and bee pollinators. After market penetration of BioGrip, we anticipate, there will be less devastating economic impacts on rural life and dicamba will no longer be a threat to the natural ecosystem as the herbicide will stick to the plant and not propagate in the environment. This STTR Phase I project and research plan reflect NSF?s statutory mission of improving US national economy and health, as well as protecting the environment for the well-being of individuals.           Last Modified: 07/30/2022       Submitted by: Joseph Batta-Mpouma]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
