<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Large nanostructured changes in refractive index in any 3D geometry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255687.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255687</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to enable an alternative to traditional nanofabrication which relies on structuring material in two-dimensional layers. These processes often limit the current design-space and prototyping/manufacturing methods with not only what can be made, but also the time and resources required for development, relegating viable commercial applications to only high-volume markets. These shortcomings will be addressed by developing a new form of nanofabrication 3D-printing capable of rapid-prototyping and mass-manufacturing photonic components with cheaper systems enabling the mass-customization of components that can more rapidly address market needs in both low- and high-volume markets. Products developed using this nanofabrication process for photonics components may address inefficiencies in datacenters with low-loss optical interconnects, as well as enabling complex optical filters, near-eye displays, and ultracompact lenses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project develops a nanofabrication process for optical and photonic components to be fabricated with large changes in refractive index at nanoscale resolutions into any 3D geometry with graded control. The process uses volumetric deposition of nanomaterials consisting of high refractive index dielectrics into a patterned polyelectrolyte gel scaffold which, once shrunken, improves both resolution and density of the patterned materials. By utilizing two-photon lithography and linear shrink factors the process can achieve feature sizes below 25nm while allowing for the creation of gradient patterns in any 3D geometry. Combining this patterning and shrink strategy with a method to volumetrically deposit high refractive index dielectric nanomaterials will allow for a degree of control over refractive index never before possible; allowing light to be sculpted in 3D with unprecedented control.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051956</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Oran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Oran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[danoran@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Irradiant Technologies Inc.</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021382036</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5083149127</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4 SHADY HILL SQ</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HUMHFFBEHJZ8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IRRADIANT TECHNOLOGIES INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Irradiant Technologies Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021381976</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4 Shady Hill Square]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255687</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The development of the planar nanofabrication of semiconductor materials over the past half a century has revolutionized the world and now serves as a foundation for modern civilization. However, after decades of rapid progress, electronics are beginning to test the limits in terms of speed, size, and power efficiency. Optical and photonic technologies are being used more and more to supplement or replace electronics. With the replacement of electronic wires with fiber optic cables, high-quality cameras being built into most computers, and the development of the silicon photonics for photonic integrated circuits becoming commonplace. This new frontier is being limited by relying on yesterday&rsquo;s technologies, whether it&rsquo;s using silicon nanofabrication processes developed over the past few decades, or traditional refractive optics developed in the 1600s.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The&nbsp;Implosion Fabrication platform developed by Irradiant Technologies unleashes the true potential of photonics and optics by allowing for full control of gradients of refractive index in arbitrary 3D geometries at deeply sub-wavelength scales. We believe this will revolutionize the ways that light is controlled and used, and will replace existing solutions while enabling a tremendous number of new applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With support from this NSF SBIR, Irradiant Technologies is commercializing the Implosion Fabrication platform for optics/photonic components. We have identified the Passive Optical Component Market ($62B in 2022, 25.2% CAGR) as the biggest initial market opportunity. Through hundreds of conversations with industry experts we have learned that coupling light into and out from optical/photonic components is a critical market pain-point across the industry, and this pain is not well-addressed by existing planar or refractive solutions.&nbsp; Our Implosion Fabrication platform is uniquely suited to address this major market opportunity.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The lack of existing solutions to this pain-point is demonstrated by our success in finding initial customers willing to contribute significant amounts of up-front research and development funds for us to develop their custom solutions. To date we have secured one customer partnership and are developing a second. Both of these customers have a shared pain-point with similar technical requirements for the solution that we can provide. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Our first partnership, with Fujikura (~$4.5 billion USD annual revenue in 2021), is to develop and manufacture an optical component for fiber-endoscopy that allows for imaging at much higher resolution in a smaller package. This partnership has yielded $100k in revenue in 2022 and will continue into 2023 with a newly signed agreement for $180k.</span> The second partnership is with Fathom Radiant to develop and manufacture an optical component for their product line of dense optical interconnects for datacenters. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">We anticipate signing an agreement with Fathom Radiant for ~$215k in early November 2022.</span> Both applications involve creating a nanostructured 3D optical component that projects light into an optical fiber in a precisely designed way. These two customers exemplify the way we are able to easily address multiple customers with a shared pain-point in a facile way using our technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This initial foundation of commercial traction and customer revenue has helped Irradiant grow quickly and develop our platform technology over the past year. However, further funding is needed to rapidly scale our solutions. The additional funds from NSF, other grants, customer revenue, and VC investment will enable Irradiant to deliver initial prototypes to customers within the next year and begin scaling up manufacturing in 2024. With the ability to design and create a wide variety of 3D photonics and optics solutions, we anticipate being able to gain significant market share in the many billion-dollar passive optical component market and eventually in the overall trillion-dollar optics/photonics enabled marketplace.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/07/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Oran</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The development of the planar nanofabrication of semiconductor materials over the past half a century has revolutionized the world and now serves as a foundation for modern civilization. However, after decades of rapid progress, electronics are beginning to test the limits in terms of speed, size, and power efficiency. Optical and photonic technologies are being used more and more to supplement or replace electronics. With the replacement of electronic wires with fiber optic cables, high-quality cameras being built into most computers, and the development of the silicon photonics for photonic integrated circuits becoming commonplace. This new frontier is being limited by relying on yesterday’s technologies, whether it’s using silicon nanofabrication processes developed over the past few decades, or traditional refractive optics developed in the 1600s.     The Implosion Fabrication platform developed by Irradiant Technologies unleashes the true potential of photonics and optics by allowing for full control of gradients of refractive index in arbitrary 3D geometries at deeply sub-wavelength scales. We believe this will revolutionize the ways that light is controlled and used, and will replace existing solutions while enabling a tremendous number of new applications.     With support from this NSF SBIR, Irradiant Technologies is commercializing the Implosion Fabrication platform for optics/photonic components. We have identified the Passive Optical Component Market ($62B in 2022, 25.2% CAGR) as the biggest initial market opportunity. Through hundreds of conversations with industry experts we have learned that coupling light into and out from optical/photonic components is a critical market pain-point across the industry, and this pain is not well-addressed by existing planar or refractive solutions.  Our Implosion Fabrication platform is uniquely suited to address this major market opportunity.     The lack of existing solutions to this pain-point is demonstrated by our success in finding initial customers willing to contribute significant amounts of up-front research and development funds for us to develop their custom solutions. To date we have secured one customer partnership and are developing a second. Both of these customers have a shared pain-point with similar technical requirements for the solution that we can provide. Our first partnership, with Fujikura (~$4.5 billion USD annual revenue in 2021), is to develop and manufacture an optical component for fiber-endoscopy that allows for imaging at much higher resolution in a smaller package. This partnership has yielded $100k in revenue in 2022 and will continue into 2023 with a newly signed agreement for $180k. The second partnership is with Fathom Radiant to develop and manufacture an optical component for their product line of dense optical interconnects for datacenters. We anticipate signing an agreement with Fathom Radiant for ~$215k in early November 2022. Both applications involve creating a nanostructured 3D optical component that projects light into an optical fiber in a precisely designed way. These two customers exemplify the way we are able to easily address multiple customers with a shared pain-point in a facile way using our technology.     This initial foundation of commercial traction and customer revenue has helped Irradiant grow quickly and develop our platform technology over the past year. However, further funding is needed to rapidly scale our solutions. The additional funds from NSF, other grants, customer revenue, and VC investment will enable Irradiant to deliver initial prototypes to customers within the next year and begin scaling up manufacturing in 2024. With the ability to design and create a wide variety of 3D photonics and optics solutions, we anticipate being able to gain significant market share in the many billion-dollar passive optical component market and eventually in the overall trillion-dollar optics/photonics enabled marketplace.       Last Modified: 08/07/2023       Submitted by: Daniel Oran]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
