<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Linking behavior and transport of larvae using waves and turbulence as cues]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15178.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15178</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Suchman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>csuchman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922092</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many bottom-dwelling marine species have larvae whose behavior in the water column impacts dispersal and adult distributions.  Snail larvae swim up with more effort or sink in response to cues from waves and turbulence, and it remains unclear whether larvae can use these physical cues for retention within or navigation among habitats.  Larvae that swim up under waves may be retained over the continental shelf by wave-induced shoreward drift in surface waters. However, ocean warming causes larvae to be released earlier in spring when waves are larger and coastal upwelling is weaker, potentially carrying larvae into shallower waters that exceed the adults' temperature tolerance. The investigators will use a physical model of the Middle Atlantic Bight and adjacent estuaries to test hypotheses about how waves and turbulence affect transport patterns, retention near adult habitats, and climate-induced shifts in adult distributions. The project will produce simulations of ocean circulation and larval tracking codes that include waves both as behavior cues and as a transport mechanism; these products will be made publicly available. A graduate student will do a related dissertation. Undergraduate students will be involved through an NSF-funded REU program, the Aresty Program, which engages Rutgers' diverse undergraduates in research to boost retention in STEM majors, the Rutgers Research in Science and Engineering program, which targets underrepresented minorities, and the Skidmore Summer Research program. Model outputs will be used to develop learning materials for undergraduates, packaged as a case study for distribution through the National Center for Case Study Teaching in Science. Research results will also be presented to adult (55 and over) learners through the Skidmore Encore lecture series.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Waves are unique in providing planktonic larvae with a behavior cue directly tied to a horizontal transport mechanism, and newly discovered larval responses to waves could have counter-intuitive impacts on larval transport and species distributions.  Wave climates differ in the adjacent habitats of two congeneric snails: Tritia obsoleta occupies turbulent inlets and estuaries where waves are small, while Tritia trivittata occupies the continental shelf where waves are much larger. These two species' larvae sense waves and turbulence separately as acceleration and vorticity-induced body rotation, respectively. Late-stage estuarine larvae mainly exhibit turbulence-induced sinking that could reduce transport out of inlets and estuaries, whereas shelf larvae also exhibit wave-induced upward swimming that could aid retention over the shelf via Stokes drift.  Since the 1960s, the shelf species' range has shifted into warmer water, opposite to predictions based on thermal tolerance. This shift may be driven by wave-induced larval transport; as ocean warming induces earlier spawning, larvae will encounter larger waves and weaker upwelling in spring, intensifying Stokes drift and onshore transport toward warmer, shallower waters of the inner shelf. The project will use numerical models to test hypotheses linking flow-induced larval behaviors to transport pathways, local retention, and climate-driven range shifts. Waves will be included as a source of both behavior cues and advection through acceleration and Stokes drift, respectively.  Results will help resolve uncertainties about how Stokes drift, Eulerian return flow, and upwelling interact to transport larvae. Numerical experiments will describe how climate-driven changes in spawning phenology affect larval transport, potentially identifying the mechanism behind perplexing range shifts of shelf species into warmer water.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051795</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Gerbi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory Gerbi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gregory.gerbi@maine.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000638290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 CORBETT HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PB3AJE5ZEJ59</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MAINE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5717 Corbett Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1174</Code>
<Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~20474</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We studied how water motions affect larval behavior and dispersal in two related snail species in the Northeastern Atlantic Ocean. The species are similar but occupy different zones: &ldquo;inlet snails&rdquo; live in turbulent coastal inlets and estuaries, and &ldquo;shelf snails&rdquo; live offshore on the wavy continental shelf. &nbsp;How do the species stay separated? The snails cannot move far as adults but disperse as tiny larvae that are carried by ocean currents for weeks or months before settling to the sea floor. &nbsp;Dispersal varies when larvae move vertically (swimming or sinking) in response to cues in their environment, including small-scale motions caused by water waves (shaking) and turbulence (rotating).&nbsp; In a previous laboratory study, we found that both species of larvae react to strong turbulence by sinking more frequently, but only shelf larvae also react to waves by swimming strongly upward.&nbsp; These different responses to water motion could enable larvae of closely related species to disperse different distances and directions. We hypothesized that the observed behaviors enable the two species&rsquo; larvae to remain and settle near their adult habitats and help to keep the adult distributions separate.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We did numerical experiments to test how larval reactions to water motions affect local retention, dispersal, and settlement patterns in an estuary and on the continental shelf.&nbsp; The experiments used virtual larvae released and tracked in model simulations of the Northeast Atlantic Ocean, focusing on the area around Delaware Bay. Virtual larvae were given either generic behaviors or responses to turbulence and waves matching those observed in inlet snails and shelf snails. &nbsp;One experiment focused on dispersal and settlement of larvae released from Delaware Bay. Results showed that the observed turbulence-induced sinking of inlet snails improves their survival by keeping them near release sites, enabling them to grow faster, and helping them to settle sooner. A second experiment focused on larvae released from the continental shelf. Results showed that wave-induced upward swimming, observed in the shelf snails, promotes larval survival on the shelf by helping them to grow quickly and settle before reaching the Gulf Stream.&nbsp; A third experiment focused on exchange of water and material between the continental shelf and Delaware Bay. These experiments confirmed that even generic behaviors strongly affect transport direction and retention time in the Bay.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We also studied whether larval dispersal could explain confusing effects of climate change on the distributions of bottom-dwelling species on the continental shelf. &nbsp;Mobile species such as fish have adapted to a warming ocean by moving their ranges toward the poles, remaining in water temperatures they can tolerate.&nbsp; Unexpectedly, shelf snails have instead moved to the southwest, into warmer water where they are less likely to survive. We analyzed historical distributions of 50 invertebrates including snails, clams, worms, and sea stars, and found that &ndash; like the shelf snails &ndash; most have unexpectedly moved their ranges to the southwest, into warmer water.&nbsp; We analyzed historical bottom water temperatures and concluded that the &ldquo;wrong-way&rdquo; range shifts could be explained by larvae being released earlier in spring, exposing them to faster currents to the southwest.&nbsp; To test this hypothesis, we also did a numerical experiment in which larval release times were set by bottom temperatures in the current, warmer ocean and the past, colder ocean. Preliminary results are consistent with the observed range shifts and suggest that over the last 50 years, ocean warming has reduced or eliminated the supply of larvae to deeper parts of the continental shelf.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our numerical experiments required us to create a new ocean simulation and to develop new software (ROMSPath), based on an older model (LTRANS), for tracking virtual particles.&nbsp; The ocean simulation includes a hydrodynamic model (ROMS) and a wave model (SWAN).&nbsp; The simulation spans 6 years (2009-2015), extends from North Carolina to Nova Scotia, and includes a higher-resolution region of Delaware Bay and the nearby shelf.&nbsp; The simulation setup files and outputs have been made publicly available for other researchers to use.&nbsp; The particle tracking software ROMSPath is also freely available and has already been used in other studies of harmful algal blooms, ocean acidification, microplastic transport, and estuarine residence times.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong> This project provided training to a postdoctoral investigator, Jessica Garwood, who has recently begun a faculty position at Oregon State University. Four undergraduate students (3 at Skidmore and 1 at Rutgers) received training in numerical modeling and analysis.&nbsp; Research results have been shared through peer-reviewed publications, conference presentations, and invited seminars. Products of the ocean model have been distribution online, including model source codes, setup files, and simulation outputs. Particle models have been included in an undergraduate and graduate coursework at Rutgers. Our modeling work supported Rutgers' shared computing cluster, Amarel, which provides researchers with high-powered computing resources at a reasonable cost.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;Gerbi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We studied how water motions affect larval behavior and dispersal in two related snail species in the Northeastern Atlantic Ocean. The species are similar but occupy different zones: "inlet snails" live in turbulent coastal inlets and estuaries, and "shelf snails" live offshore on the wavy continental shelf.  How do the species stay separated? The snails cannot move far as adults but disperse as tiny larvae that are carried by ocean currents for weeks or months before settling to the sea floor.  Dispersal varies when larvae move vertically (swimming or sinking) in response to cues in their environment, including small-scale motions caused by water waves (shaking) and turbulence (rotating).  In a previous laboratory study, we found that both species of larvae react to strong turbulence by sinking more frequently, but only shelf larvae also react to waves by swimming strongly upward.  These different responses to water motion could enable larvae of closely related species to disperse different distances and directions. We hypothesized that the observed behaviors enable the two species’ larvae to remain and settle near their adult habitats and help to keep the adult distributions separate.        We did numerical experiments to test how larval reactions to water motions affect local retention, dispersal, and settlement patterns in an estuary and on the continental shelf.  The experiments used virtual larvae released and tracked in model simulations of the Northeast Atlantic Ocean, focusing on the area around Delaware Bay. Virtual larvae were given either generic behaviors or responses to turbulence and waves matching those observed in inlet snails and shelf snails.  One experiment focused on dispersal and settlement of larvae released from Delaware Bay. Results showed that the observed turbulence-induced sinking of inlet snails improves their survival by keeping them near release sites, enabling them to grow faster, and helping them to settle sooner. A second experiment focused on larvae released from the continental shelf. Results showed that wave-induced upward swimming, observed in the shelf snails, promotes larval survival on the shelf by helping them to grow quickly and settle before reaching the Gulf Stream.  A third experiment focused on exchange of water and material between the continental shelf and Delaware Bay. These experiments confirmed that even generic behaviors strongly affect transport direction and retention time in the Bay.     We also studied whether larval dispersal could explain confusing effects of climate change on the distributions of bottom-dwelling species on the continental shelf.  Mobile species such as fish have adapted to a warming ocean by moving their ranges toward the poles, remaining in water temperatures they can tolerate.  Unexpectedly, shelf snails have instead moved to the southwest, into warmer water where they are less likely to survive. We analyzed historical distributions of 50 invertebrates including snails, clams, worms, and sea stars, and found that &ndash; like the shelf snails &ndash; most have unexpectedly moved their ranges to the southwest, into warmer water.  We analyzed historical bottom water temperatures and concluded that the "wrong-way" range shifts could be explained by larvae being released earlier in spring, exposing them to faster currents to the southwest.  To test this hypothesis, we also did a numerical experiment in which larval release times were set by bottom temperatures in the current, warmer ocean and the past, colder ocean. Preliminary results are consistent with the observed range shifts and suggest that over the last 50 years, ocean warming has reduced or eliminated the supply of larvae to deeper parts of the continental shelf.     Our numerical experiments required us to create a new ocean simulation and to develop new software (ROMSPath), based on an older model (LTRANS), for tracking virtual particles.  The ocean simulation includes a hydrodynamic model (ROMS) and a wave model (SWAN).  The simulation spans 6 years (2009-2015), extends from North Carolina to Nova Scotia, and includes a higher-resolution region of Delaware Bay and the nearby shelf.  The simulation setup files and outputs have been made publicly available for other researchers to use.  The particle tracking software ROMSPath is also freely available and has already been used in other studies of harmful algal blooms, ocean acidification, microplastic transport, and estuarine residence times.     Broader Impacts: This project provided training to a postdoctoral investigator, Jessica Garwood, who has recently begun a faculty position at Oregon State University. Four undergraduate students (3 at Skidmore and 1 at Rutgers) received training in numerical modeling and analysis.  Research results have been shared through peer-reviewed publications, conference presentations, and invited seminars. Products of the ocean model have been distribution online, including model source codes, setup files, and simulation outputs. Particle models have been included in an undergraduate and graduate coursework at Rutgers. Our modeling work supported Rutgers' shared computing cluster, Amarel, which provides researchers with high-powered computing resources at a reasonable cost.          Last Modified: 08/31/2023       Submitted by: Gregory Gerbi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
