<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  On-chip integration of sample preparation and monitoring with dielectrophoretic cell isolation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255986.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255986</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is a platform to isolate cells based on their biophysical properties. The platform will help isolate cells that are not abundant and enable study of their role in biological function and diseases such as cancer. Specifically, a single chip platform will carry out sample preparation, manipulation, and monitoring, greatly reducing the sample handling steps and thereby ensuring the maintenance of cell viability and improvement in sample consistency. This recovered sample is essential for the development of cell-based therapies in regenerative medicine and cancer management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will develop an electrically functional microfluidic sample manipulation platform for phenotype-selective recovery of cells, based on their biophysical attributes that allow discrimination between distinct electrophysiological properties for the cells of interest within the sample media. Specifically, microfluidic designs will be developed to swap cells from complex biological matrices into an optimized buffer for enabling cell manipulation, and the instrumentation will be developed for on-chip monitoring of the sample during various stages of the phenotype-selective cell recovery process. The designs will be optimized for enhanced levels of selection purity, while maintaining high cell collection efficiencies, so that the recovered sample is enriched for cell phenotypes of interest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051652</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Hyler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexandra R Hyler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ahyler@cytorecovery.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836428</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Swami</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan S Swami</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nathanswami@virginia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000486590</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CYTORECOVERY, INC.</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240606322</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5409617871</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1872 PRATT DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 1350]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YE7LS83NPML7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CYTORECOVERY INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CytoRecovery]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240600005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1872 Pratt Dr, Suite 1350]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255986</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Tissue, blood, and other biological samples are used throughout medical research, diagnostics, treatment selection, and patient monitoring. They are inherently multifaceted and heterogeneous, but this poses challenges for identifying the role of each cell type in disease initiation and progression. These ever-complex biological samples are critical in moving medical research and treatment towards personalized care. Truly personalized medicine requires precision cell recovery and discovery.</p> <p>Based upon these research challenges, CytoRecovery has developed a benchtop cell sorting system, The Cyto R1 Platform (Image 1), that recovers live cell populations with a small footprint to provide capabilities within an individual research lab. The key benefits of the Cyto R1 Platform include: label-free sorting, disposable and sterile experimental kits, enrichments on the order of minutes, cost savings per system and per experimental run, and a benchtop integrated system. The core of the platform is our microfluidic devices, Cyto Chips, that load and sort samples in our proprietary Cyto Buffer reagent. This work demonstrated an added feature of on-system buffer exchange to allow direct sample inputs onto the Cyto R1. The on-chip buffer exchange is critical to removing preparation upstream and ensuring further sample viability and quality. To address the need for swapping biological cells from their native media into a media with a low conductivity and flow rate level that is optimized for dielectrophoretic manipulation, we developed two successful microfluidic devices with a buffer swap stage. The microfluidic designs and flow conditions were optimized using flow and particle tracing simulations to achieve ultra-low conductivity and reasonable flow rates for downstream use. Our first device design was used to demonstrate that RBCs entering the buffer swap can be diluted ~100-fold in media conductivity after the buffer swap stage (Image 2). Similarly, the second device design was used to demonstrate the ovarian cancer tumor-initiating cells entering the buffer swap device can be swapped to achieve an outlet conductivity into Cyto Buffer of improved 100-fold conductivity reduction (Image 3).</p> <p>Furthermore, features were developed for on-system quantification in order to garner customer confidence in the efficacy and repeatability of subpopulation sorting and recovery. Adding quantification elements to the system is also a highly critical feature for adoption for our beachhead users. Customers want to feel sure that their sorting and enrichment of cell subpopulations achieves a threshold for consistent experimental performances. An optical quantification method was prototyped to accurately count the number of cells entering the DEP region for sorting and enrichment (Image 4). Lastly, the on-chip monitoring was initiated by fabrication of sidewall electrodes in the microchannel for real-time tracking of the media conductivity after the buffer swap stage. Design strategies for follow-up work are underway for integrating the buffer swap stage, DEP separation stage, and in-line monitoring operations effectively into the Cyto R1 Platform in order to characterize the outlet sample media conductivity, cell numbers, cell velocity, cell viability, and the position of cell streamlines adding on-system performance parameters.</p> <p>This work supported 7 employees and 3 graduate students with collaborative contributions from CytoRecovery, Inc. and the University of Virginia. This work led to 3 publications, 4 conference presentations, and 2 patent filings. As a result of this work, CytoRecovery is positioned to integrate and launch added features to its Cyto R1 Platform. Proof-of-concept data has been provided to our potential beta test locations, and they are very eager to see these features refined and integrated for use by customers. Our early customer discussions indicate native sample behavior post sorting is valuable for their downstream analyses. While microfluidics-based technologies are still a very small segment of the biotechnology markets, these types of features developed in this work for addition to our microfluidics-based cell sorting technology are leading to gained confidence with the market for their repeatable and consistent use. Translating cell sorting technologies is critical to the future of personalized medicine. To begin truly treating individual diseases, diagnosing each patient's conditions earlier, and honing personalized care, precision cell sorting research is needed to unlock these continued medical mysteries spanning oncology, immunology, stem cells, and beyond. The foundation of this work with added microfluidic features will continue providing customer confidence to launch the novel Cyto R1 cell sorting, enrichment, and recovery platform for biomedical research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Alexandra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Hyler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269688871_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269688871_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cyto R1 Platform"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269688871_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cyto R1 Platform"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CytoRecovery?s Cyto Chips (A) are the core of the Cyto R1. Cyto Chips are integrated using a plug-n-play interfacing system (B) and visualized on any microscope. The platform also contains an electronics generator and fluidic pumps (C), with everything controlled by Cyto Software.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Hyler</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexandra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Hyler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cyto R1 Platform</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269789155_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269789155_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Buffer Exchange Prototype Device"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269789155_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Buffer Exchange Prototype Device"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(A) Schematic of the sample buffer swap and dielectrophoretic (DEP) separation stages. (B) Buffer swap occurs over the cell focusing region by ion diffusion. (C) Negative DEP and positive DEP of collected RBCs after buffer swap stage.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nathan Swami</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexandra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Hyler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Buffer Exchange Prototype Device</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269863924_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269863924_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Prototyped Buffer Exchange Device (2)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269863924_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Prototyped Buffer Exchange Device (2)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(A) Alternative buffer exchange device for further improved buffer exchange, lowered conductivity, and improved cell retention (no filtering pillars). (B) Demonstrated flow exchange in a fabricated device with added filtering pillars. Red is cells? native media and clear fluid is Cyto Buffer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Hyler</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexandra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Hyler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Prototyped Buffer Exchange Device (2)</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269936990_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269936990_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Optical Quantification Chip Prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051652/2051652_10720341_1647269936990_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Optical Quantification Chip Prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prototyped on-chip optical cell detection using fiber optics and a photo diode for single-cell (arrows) number quantification entering the downstream DEP sorting region.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Hyler</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexandra&nbsp;R&nbsp;Hyler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Optical Quantification Chip Prototype</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Tissue, blood, and other biological samples are used throughout medical research, diagnostics, treatment selection, and patient monitoring. They are inherently multifaceted and heterogeneous, but this poses challenges for identifying the role of each cell type in disease initiation and progression. These ever-complex biological samples are critical in moving medical research and treatment towards personalized care. Truly personalized medicine requires precision cell recovery and discovery.  Based upon these research challenges, CytoRecovery has developed a benchtop cell sorting system, The Cyto R1 Platform (Image 1), that recovers live cell populations with a small footprint to provide capabilities within an individual research lab. The key benefits of the Cyto R1 Platform include: label-free sorting, disposable and sterile experimental kits, enrichments on the order of minutes, cost savings per system and per experimental run, and a benchtop integrated system. The core of the platform is our microfluidic devices, Cyto Chips, that load and sort samples in our proprietary Cyto Buffer reagent. This work demonstrated an added feature of on-system buffer exchange to allow direct sample inputs onto the Cyto R1. The on-chip buffer exchange is critical to removing preparation upstream and ensuring further sample viability and quality. To address the need for swapping biological cells from their native media into a media with a low conductivity and flow rate level that is optimized for dielectrophoretic manipulation, we developed two successful microfluidic devices with a buffer swap stage. The microfluidic designs and flow conditions were optimized using flow and particle tracing simulations to achieve ultra-low conductivity and reasonable flow rates for downstream use. Our first device design was used to demonstrate that RBCs entering the buffer swap can be diluted ~100-fold in media conductivity after the buffer swap stage (Image 2). Similarly, the second device design was used to demonstrate the ovarian cancer tumor-initiating cells entering the buffer swap device can be swapped to achieve an outlet conductivity into Cyto Buffer of improved 100-fold conductivity reduction (Image 3).  Furthermore, features were developed for on-system quantification in order to garner customer confidence in the efficacy and repeatability of subpopulation sorting and recovery. Adding quantification elements to the system is also a highly critical feature for adoption for our beachhead users. Customers want to feel sure that their sorting and enrichment of cell subpopulations achieves a threshold for consistent experimental performances. An optical quantification method was prototyped to accurately count the number of cells entering the DEP region for sorting and enrichment (Image 4). Lastly, the on-chip monitoring was initiated by fabrication of sidewall electrodes in the microchannel for real-time tracking of the media conductivity after the buffer swap stage. Design strategies for follow-up work are underway for integrating the buffer swap stage, DEP separation stage, and in-line monitoring operations effectively into the Cyto R1 Platform in order to characterize the outlet sample media conductivity, cell numbers, cell velocity, cell viability, and the position of cell streamlines adding on-system performance parameters.  This work supported 7 employees and 3 graduate students with collaborative contributions from CytoRecovery, Inc. and the University of Virginia. This work led to 3 publications, 4 conference presentations, and 2 patent filings. As a result of this work, CytoRecovery is positioned to integrate and launch added features to its Cyto R1 Platform. Proof-of-concept data has been provided to our potential beta test locations, and they are very eager to see these features refined and integrated for use by customers. Our early customer discussions indicate native sample behavior post sorting is valuable for their downstream analyses. While microfluidics-based technologies are still a very small segment of the biotechnology markets, these types of features developed in this work for addition to our microfluidics-based cell sorting technology are leading to gained confidence with the market for their repeatable and consistent use. Translating cell sorting technologies is critical to the future of personalized medicine. To begin truly treating individual diseases, diagnosing each patient's conditions earlier, and honing personalized care, precision cell sorting research is needed to unlock these continued medical mysteries spanning oncology, immunology, stem cells, and beyond. The foundation of this work with added microfluidic features will continue providing customer confidence to launch the novel Cyto R1 cell sorting, enrichment, and recovery platform for biomedical research.       Last Modified: 03/14/2022       Submitted by: Alexandra R Hyler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
