<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Endocrine disruptors and developmental programming in humans]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is funded in whole or in part under the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (Public Law 117-2). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the role of the natural and cultural environments in early life growth and development is important for advancing knowledge about human biological variation and plasticity. This doctoral dissertation project utilizes a biocultural framework to investigate early life exposure to endocrine disrupting chemicals (EDCs), which may have longer-term consequences for human physiological function. The investigator is examining the impacts of EDC exposure on infant hormonal profiles, adding to an understanding of global and temporal patterns in exposure to EDCs as well as the sensitivity of the developing endocrine system to EDCs. The project provides training in a STEM field to a female graduate student and involves outreach in a local community. The researcher is also creating informational reports to deliver to stakeholders and is collaborating with local organizations to generate recommendations for policy change based on the results of the study. The project also includes science outreach to middle school students and the general public through various science communication initiatives. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary aim of this study is to quantify the effect of EDC exposure on infant hormonal profiles in different environments. Using a novel, nontargeted metabolomics approach, the investigator is quantifying EDC exposures across three biological matrices and two environmental sampling methods from mother-infant dyads. The investigator is drawing upon theoretical frameworks employed in biocultural research to understand and interpret the impacts of EDC exposure. The project builds on the Developmental Origins of Health and Disease Hypothesis by investigating the sensitivity of the developing endocrine system to EDCs using hormonal and exposure profiles. From an Evolutionary Medicine perspective, the project also addresses whether current sources and levels of EDCs overwhelm evolved defenses to environmental exposures, creating an evolutionary mismatch. Incorporating the concept of Locally Situated Biologies, the project includes collection of qualitative data to contextualize how patterns of exposure to EDCs as well as their health consequences are influenced by aspects of the local context.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051220</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claudia</FirstName>
<LastName>Valeggia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claudia R Valeggia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[claudia.valeggia@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000533505</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlye</FirstName>
<LastName>Chaney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlye Chaney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[carlye.chaney@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208277</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10 Sachem Street, Rm 224]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~25200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award funded a project to investigate environmental contaminant exposure among mothers and infants in New Haven, CT, USA, and Formosa, Argentina. The project found that environmental contaminants in the water supply, human milk, and urine were associated with similar metabolic pathway outcomes, namely amino acid metabolism, carbohydrate metabolism, and energy metabolism for infants and mothers in both the United States and Argentina. These results suggest that mixtures of environmental contaminants may have similar physiological effects when assessed globally. The project also found that the exposure profiles of mothers from the US and Argentina had numerous statistically significant differences, as the study team had predicted given the environments of the two communities. However, infants from the US and Argentina demonstrated unexpectedly similar exposure profiles, which may suggest that maternal biology is buffering infant exposure through human milk.</p> <p>The project also involved several broader impacts. It provided training in a STEM field to a female PhD student, who is a first-generation college student. The project also provided training for two female undergraduate students and a female Indigenous research assistant. The project resulted in one doctoral dissertation, three scientific conference presentations, and a Three Minute Thesis presentation. It has alsi produced one manuscript that is under review in a peer-reviewed journal; two other manuscripts are in progress. The study team provided information about environmental contaminants and preliminary reports of the results to the community in Argentina through presentations on the local radio station and home visits. Participants in the United States also received personalized exposure reports and information about environmental contaminants. The study team is currently developing reports and presentations for local community organizations and local governments in both study sites.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Carlye&nbsp;Chaney</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award funded a project to investigate environmental contaminant exposure among mothers and infants in New Haven, CT, USA, and Formosa, Argentina. The project found that environmental contaminants in the water supply, human milk, and urine were associated with similar metabolic pathway outcomes, namely amino acid metabolism, carbohydrate metabolism, and energy metabolism for infants and mothers in both the United States and Argentina. These results suggest that mixtures of environmental contaminants may have similar physiological effects when assessed globally. The project also found that the exposure profiles of mothers from the US and Argentina had numerous statistically significant differences, as the study team had predicted given the environments of the two communities. However, infants from the US and Argentina demonstrated unexpectedly similar exposure profiles, which may suggest that maternal biology is buffering infant exposure through human milk.  The project also involved several broader impacts. It provided training in a STEM field to a female PhD student, who is a first-generation college student. The project also provided training for two female undergraduate students and a female Indigenous research assistant. The project resulted in one doctoral dissertation, three scientific conference presentations, and a Three Minute Thesis presentation. It has alsi produced one manuscript that is under review in a peer-reviewed journal; two other manuscripts are in progress. The study team provided information about environmental contaminants and preliminary reports of the results to the community in Argentina through presentations on the local radio station and home visits. Participants in the United States also received personalized exposure reports and information about environmental contaminants. The study team is currently developing reports and presentations for local community organizations and local governments in both study sites.          Last Modified: 07/10/2023       Submitted by: Carlye Chaney]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
