<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Orchard Transpiration Irrigation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to improve the water usage in agricultural operations. With growing water scarcity from the lack of natural rainfall and depleted groundwater tables, the need to maintain agricultural wells and agricultural production is dramatic. The proposed subsurface irrigation technology will reduce irrigated water by 50% over drip irrigation.  This could enable significant reduction in water use and allow the groundwater tables to recover and perform as water reservoirs during drought years. It potentially can raise farm yields, improve weed control for organic farmers, and promote better uptake of fertilizers - thereby minimizing the pollution of underground aquifers. The proposed technology also can lead to energy cost reductions and increased flexibility in scheduling power usage. At a systems level, it offers a new paradigm for a resilient and sustainable irrigation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is focused on the development of an easy-to-use moisture plume simulation calculator that enables farmers to self-analyze how their soil type will react when installing a virtual water table irrigation system. The latter is designed to eliminate water lost by surface evaporation and deep percolation. The research approach taken is an interdisciplinary collaboration to mathematically model the physics of how liquid transports from the subsurface feed pipes through the porous soil to the roots of the plants in an efficient manner with adequate accuracy. The predictions will be compared with more comprehensive industry-standard hydrological model predictions and also with the experimentally collected moisture data from the field. The technical risks lie in determining whether the basic soil properties collected by the non-scientist farmers would be adequate as inputs to generate an accurate prediction of moisture plume profile across many soil types.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051966</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Gallegos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph D Gallegos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Joseph@droughtdietproducts.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000726183</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drought Diet Products</Name>
<CityName>FRESNO</CityName>
<ZipCode>937400001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5623015598</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2911 E BARSTOW AVE MS 144</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QKLGMJH5AL74</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DROUGHT DIET PRODUCTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Drought Diet Products]]></Name>
<CityName>Fresno</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>908142211</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5370 N Chestnut Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>42</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA42</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research was to investigate the feasibility in developing a Soil Moisture Calculator (SMC) that farmers could use prior to installing an innovative subsurface virtual water table irrigation system. The SMC goal is to equip farmers with what the subsurface virtual water table moisture plume (capillary fringe) would look like in their soil type. There is no known research literature on the introduction of a virtual water table and its moisture plume, so this research on hydrological movement was fundamental in nature, and the research outcomes presented some unexpected beneficial anomalies. These anomalies also changed our SMC hypothesis on how the subsurface moisture plume would develop and behave under a crop.</p> <p>The impact of this SMC fundamental research will lead to advancement in crop irrigation utilization to the point of transpiration only irrigation, eliminating water losses to environmental leakages of evaporation and deep percolation.</p> <p>In brief, the anomalies are moisture stratification layers within the soil profile (Fig1) that accumulate moisture content. The top stratification is especially interesting, which is caused by agricultural compaction. A compaction layer is common on agricultural land and creates issues that limit surface irrigation percolation. This compaction layer is acting like a cap limiting water losses to atmospheric evaporation. We expected the capillary fringe to plume out from the virtual water table with a gradual reduction in moisture content the farther away the moisture plume moves. Instead, the capillary fringe goes through a gradual reduction for about two feet, then drops off rapidly for about one foot, and then a spike in volumetric moisture content appears about 6 to 12 inches below the surface, which happens to be at and below the compaction cap. In addition, the water vapor plume hits the cap from below and is apparently rolling out along the cap, similar to smoke rolling along the ceiling in a fire.</p> <p>There are a couple of unanswered questions related to the SMC that would need to be addressed in phase II. One question is how far the rolling water vapor flows out along the underside of the compaction layer. Our experiments were designed for orchard spacing of the virtual water table irrigation system, which put the farthest expected measurements at 5 feet. We did not collect data all the way out to 20 feet where two moisture plumes from each replication overlapped. The second question is if cover crops that break up the compaction layer will have an effect on this rolling vapor flow.</p> <p><strong>Accomplishments:</strong> By far the two biggest accomplishments were unexpected discoveries: 1) how compaction layers in agricultural fields can cap subsurface moisture, and 2) that this compaction layer allowed for an 80% reduction in applied water in growing an orchard crop. The accomplishments related to the original question of an SMC are abundant in understanding the moisture plume dynamics created with a virtual water table irrigation system. Collaborating with a team of interdisciplinary scientists, we were able to take the research into new discovery areas, leaning on the skill sets across the different disciplines to open up new paths of thinking and hydrological modeling. This interdisciplinary cross-thinking gave the project some depth and breadth across skills and knowledge. Challenges presented themselves when the data was not consistent with hydrology properties and agricultural assumptions. The team regrouped a few times to theorize the reasons of the moisture dynamic presented in the data collection, then tested these theories with computer modeling run on supercomputer time and built lab test models, which all led to a better understanding of SMC foundation and water irrigation utilization for growing crops. <strong><br /> <br /> </strong></p> <p><strong>Impact:</strong> This research to develop the SMC for farmers who are interested in adopting virtual water table irrigation practices has resulted in a very large impact for the USA and the world. The calculator goes beyond just the soil moisture plume representation, but also leads to transpiration only irrigation model, a strategy to eliminate all environmental losses to evaporation and deep percolation when irrigating crops. Our research has led us to demonstrate that the traditional recommended evapotranspiration irrigation can be reduced by 80%, meaning that up to 80% of all water applied to crops today is lost to environmental leakages.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Groundwater sustainability:</span>&nbsp;An 80% reduction in applied water is at or below most natural groundwater recharge sustainability volumes. The SMC developed under this NSF award will allow farmers to analyze what changes in irrigation management will occur, how the subsurface moisture will respond, and best of all the sharp reduction of water needed when using a virtual water table irrigation system. The impact is that agriculture production, will have enough water for food security under increasing water scarcity.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/19/2022<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;D&nbsp;Gallegos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943366836_2021MoistureMeter3Dview--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943366836_2021MoistureMeter3Dview--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Water Moisture Layers in Orchard"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943366836_2021MoistureMeter3Dview--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Water Moisture Layers in Orchard"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Water moisture layers subsurface in almond orchard during research. Notice the high moisture content near the surface.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Drought Diet Products</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;D&nbsp;Gallegos</div> <div class="imageTitle">Water Moisture Layers in Orchard</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943227243_NeutronverseCapacatorMoistureVapor--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943227243_NeutronverseCapacatorMoistureVapor--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Moisture vapor trap under a compaction layer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943227243_NeutronverseCapacatorMoistureVapor--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Moisture vapor trap under a compaction layer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Moisture vapor trap under a compaction layer, preventing water losses to evaporation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Drought Diet Products</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;D&nbsp;Gallegos</div> <div class="imageTitle">Moisture vapor trap under a compaction layer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943034418_NeutronverseCapacatorplumever2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943034418_NeutronverseCapacatorplumever2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051966/2051966_10729015_1660943034418_NeutronverseCapacatorplumever2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Changes in subsurface moisture plume / virtual capillary fringe. Left side shows moisture layers under a compaction soil layer</div> <div class="imageCredit">Drought Diet Products</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;D&nbsp;Gallegos</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research was to investigate the feasibility in developing a Soil Moisture Calculator (SMC) that farmers could use prior to installing an innovative subsurface virtual water table irrigation system. The SMC goal is to equip farmers with what the subsurface virtual water table moisture plume (capillary fringe) would look like in their soil type. There is no known research literature on the introduction of a virtual water table and its moisture plume, so this research on hydrological movement was fundamental in nature, and the research outcomes presented some unexpected beneficial anomalies. These anomalies also changed our SMC hypothesis on how the subsurface moisture plume would develop and behave under a crop.  The impact of this SMC fundamental research will lead to advancement in crop irrigation utilization to the point of transpiration only irrigation, eliminating water losses to environmental leakages of evaporation and deep percolation.  In brief, the anomalies are moisture stratification layers within the soil profile (Fig1) that accumulate moisture content. The top stratification is especially interesting, which is caused by agricultural compaction. A compaction layer is common on agricultural land and creates issues that limit surface irrigation percolation. This compaction layer is acting like a cap limiting water losses to atmospheric evaporation. We expected the capillary fringe to plume out from the virtual water table with a gradual reduction in moisture content the farther away the moisture plume moves. Instead, the capillary fringe goes through a gradual reduction for about two feet, then drops off rapidly for about one foot, and then a spike in volumetric moisture content appears about 6 to 12 inches below the surface, which happens to be at and below the compaction cap. In addition, the water vapor plume hits the cap from below and is apparently rolling out along the cap, similar to smoke rolling along the ceiling in a fire.  There are a couple of unanswered questions related to the SMC that would need to be addressed in phase II. One question is how far the rolling water vapor flows out along the underside of the compaction layer. Our experiments were designed for orchard spacing of the virtual water table irrigation system, which put the farthest expected measurements at 5 feet. We did not collect data all the way out to 20 feet where two moisture plumes from each replication overlapped. The second question is if cover crops that break up the compaction layer will have an effect on this rolling vapor flow.  Accomplishments: By far the two biggest accomplishments were unexpected discoveries: 1) how compaction layers in agricultural fields can cap subsurface moisture, and 2) that this compaction layer allowed for an 80% reduction in applied water in growing an orchard crop. The accomplishments related to the original question of an SMC are abundant in understanding the moisture plume dynamics created with a virtual water table irrigation system. Collaborating with a team of interdisciplinary scientists, we were able to take the research into new discovery areas, leaning on the skill sets across the different disciplines to open up new paths of thinking and hydrological modeling. This interdisciplinary cross-thinking gave the project some depth and breadth across skills and knowledge. Challenges presented themselves when the data was not consistent with hydrology properties and agricultural assumptions. The team regrouped a few times to theorize the reasons of the moisture dynamic presented in the data collection, then tested these theories with computer modeling run on supercomputer time and built lab test models, which all led to a better understanding of SMC foundation and water irrigation utilization for growing crops.       Impact: This research to develop the SMC for farmers who are interested in adopting virtual water table irrigation practices has resulted in a very large impact for the USA and the world. The calculator goes beyond just the soil moisture plume representation, but also leads to transpiration only irrigation model, a strategy to eliminate all environmental losses to evaporation and deep percolation when irrigating crops. Our research has led us to demonstrate that the traditional recommended evapotranspiration irrigation can be reduced by 80%, meaning that up to 80% of all water applied to crops today is lost to environmental leakages.  Groundwater sustainability: An 80% reduction in applied water is at or below most natural groundwater recharge sustainability volumes. The SMC developed under this NSF award will allow farmers to analyze what changes in irrigation management will occur, how the subsurface moisture will respond, and best of all the sharp reduction of water needed when using a virtual water table irrigation system. The impact is that agriculture production, will have enough water for food security under increasing water scarcity.       Last Modified: 08/19/2022       Submitted by: Joseph D Gallegos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
