<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Online Hazard Communication in the Terse Regime:  Measurement, Modeling, and Dynamics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/30/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14634.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>80000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin L. Dillon-Merrill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rdillonm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Social media use by emergency management organizations has surged in the past five years, reflecting both the increasing use of social media technologies by the general population and the potential for social media to facilitate key emergency response tasks.  These tasks include diffusion of emergency warnings and alerts; establishing and maintaining networks of communication among responding organizations; and collecting information on public needs as the crisis unfolds.  While social media encompasses a diverse array of technologies and practices, particular interest has converged on the practices and processes of short text message exchange under time constrained and dynamic conditions - a communication context known as the "terse regime."  Though social media are an increasingly important fixture of the emergency management landscape, the study of online communication in response to extreme events is still quite young and theory development has lagged.  This research will fill this gap by advancing our ability to measure and model the processes governing terse-regime communication in emergency settings, and by linking these to the tasks required of emergency management organizations.  This research has the potential to fundamentally transform our understanding of and theoretical orientation to terse hazard communication processes at a particularly critical time in the disaster life cycle. Importantly, the findings from this research will provide the empirical basis necessary to inform future decision making strategies to utilize social media for warnings and public risk communication across all hazards and will be transferable to multiple channels; will lead to greater understanding of the networked patterns of communication among the public; and will enable the prediction of how organizations themselves will act in a distributed, online environment.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To accomplish this, this research will develop novel measurement techniques and formal theoretical models for understanding the dynamics of online communicative behavior in the terse regime.  The research will address the following questions:  What governs the allocation of attention of the online public to specific organizations and messages during disaster, and how does this affect retransmission of terse messages? What governs the dynamics of organizations' online terse-regime communications and how does their behavior evolve in response to hazard stimuli, public behavior, or their own interactions?  How does informal online response vary across time and space in terms of both message production and message transmission?  And how can we better recognize, detect, and measure online communicative processes in response to hazard events?  To answer these questions, the research will pursue several linked activities including the collection of a systematic, baseline controlled longitudinal backbone sample of hazard-related communication from a prominent micro-blogging site over a three year period, supplemented by demographic and other information on hazards, online warnings and alerts, and the impacted populations; collection of detailed data on online communication by and interactions among organizations involved in emergency response activities in a major U.S. metropolitan area; development of agent-based and other theory-driven models for terse message transmission, organizational interaction and communication behavior, and allocation of attention to official communications online; and development of novel techniques for measuring the public's online response to hazard events and for distinguishing between responses generation by specific social processes or by particular sub-populations.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051902</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeannette</FirstName>
<LastName>Sutton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeannette Sutton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jsutton@albany.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000671333</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
<CityName>ALBANY</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184374974</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NHH3T1Z96H29</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GMZUKXFDJMA9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Albany]]></Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 Washington Ave MSC 100A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>U242</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001516DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021RB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~0</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project outcomes reported here focus on the supplemental funding that was attached to an existing award that examined hazard risk messaging.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;This research&nbsp;draws from theories of warning response (Mileti &amp; Sorensen, 1990; Sutton et al., 2020; Wood et al., 2018) to measure individual understanding, believing, personalizing, deciding, and milling in response to Earthquake Early Warning messages.&nbsp; We also investigate public perceptions of credibility and trust to assess perceptions of the ShakeAlert EEW system and source effectiveness, especially in light of false alerts that may be sent&nbsp; prior to or following an earthquake event.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;In this mixed methods study, we conducted two rounds of virtual focus groups; one with members of the public who experienced a false earthquake early warning alert followed by a post-alert message.&nbsp; This population also had prior experience of a significant earthquake event. The second round of focus groups were conducted with members of the public in CA to discuss variations in post-alert message contents.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>We also conducted one public survey with two samples.&nbsp; Sample 1 (n = 1007), drawn from Southern California, and sample 2 (n = 390), drawn from zip codes that experienced shaking during the 7/5/19 Ridgecrest, CA earthquake.&nbsp; Survey items were designed to&nbsp;document baseline levels of knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, perceived efficacy, experience, and behavior related to earthquake self-protective actions, ShakeAlert, and other earthquake alerting apps.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The specific objectives of this study were to:&nbsp;</p> <p>1.Document baseline levels of knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, perceived efficacy, experience, and behavior related to earthquake self-protective actions and ShakeAlert (and other earthquake alerting apps) across Southern California, with a large enough sample to enable longitudinal data collection over the next three years.</p> <p>2.Understand reactions to the 7/5/19 Ridgecrest earthquake and the subsequent false alert, to help optimize future communications about false positives, false negatives, delayed warning, and other technology limitations.</p> <p>3.Document baseline levels of knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, perceived efficacy, experience, and behavior related to earthquake self-protective actions and ShakeAlert (and other earthquake alerting apps) among people who live in areas that experienced MMI IV or greater intensity during the 7/5/19 Ridgecrest earthquake, with a specific focus on actions taken in relation to ShakeAlert.</p> <p>While data are still being analyzed, the investigators intend to develop several manuscripts for publication including one focused on the survey results reporting on public trust in automated earthquake early warnings, examining the differences between those who have experienced an earthquake followed by a false alert and post-alert message vs. those who have not. A second manuscript will draw from the focus group interviews on post-alert messages, their perceived purpose and the contents that are perceived to be most to participants who have experienced a false alert and to those who have not.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Preliminary findings suggest that trust in automated systems, such as earthquake early warnings, is likely to be moderated by prior hazard experience as well as prior false alerting experience.&nbsp; Those who experience a false alert perceive this as a response cost, affecting perceptions of the overall system and trust in future warnings.&nbsp;&nbsp; Furthermore, post-alert messages that are designed to follow a false or inaccurate alert need to provide assurance of safety to message receivers, especially for to those who are unfamiliar with earthquake hazards and/or the nature of the automated detection and warning system.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>This research is the first to examine the effect of a false earthquake early warning on a population that had previously experienced a significant earthquake event.&nbsp; The findings from this research will provide insight into warnings, false alerts, inaccurate alerts, and post-alert/cancellation messages for all hazards and for automated systems that deliver hazard warning messages to persons at risk.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeannette&nbsp;Sutton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project outcomes reported here focus on the supplemental funding that was attached to an existing award that examined hazard risk messaging.      This research draws from theories of warning response (Mileti &amp; Sorensen, 1990; Sutton et al., 2020; Wood et al., 2018) to measure individual understanding, believing, personalizing, deciding, and milling in response to Earthquake Early Warning messages.  We also investigate public perceptions of credibility and trust to assess perceptions of the ShakeAlert EEW system and source effectiveness, especially in light of false alerts that may be sent  prior to or following an earthquake event.    In this mixed methods study, we conducted two rounds of virtual focus groups; one with members of the public who experienced a false earthquake early warning alert followed by a post-alert message.  This population also had prior experience of a significant earthquake event. The second round of focus groups were conducted with members of the public in CA to discuss variations in post-alert message contents.     We also conducted one public survey with two samples.  Sample 1 (n = 1007), drawn from Southern California, and sample 2 (n = 390), drawn from zip codes that experienced shaking during the 7/5/19 Ridgecrest, CA earthquake.  Survey items were designed to document baseline levels of knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, perceived efficacy, experience, and behavior related to earthquake self-protective actions, ShakeAlert, and other earthquake alerting apps.     The specific objectives of this study were to:   1.Document baseline levels of knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, perceived efficacy, experience, and behavior related to earthquake self-protective actions and ShakeAlert (and other earthquake alerting apps) across Southern California, with a large enough sample to enable longitudinal data collection over the next three years.  2.Understand reactions to the 7/5/19 Ridgecrest earthquake and the subsequent false alert, to help optimize future communications about false positives, false negatives, delayed warning, and other technology limitations.  3.Document baseline levels of knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, perceived efficacy, experience, and behavior related to earthquake self-protective actions and ShakeAlert (and other earthquake alerting apps) among people who live in areas that experienced MMI IV or greater intensity during the 7/5/19 Ridgecrest earthquake, with a specific focus on actions taken in relation to ShakeAlert.  While data are still being analyzed, the investigators intend to develop several manuscripts for publication including one focused on the survey results reporting on public trust in automated earthquake early warnings, examining the differences between those who have experienced an earthquake followed by a false alert and post-alert message vs. those who have not. A second manuscript will draw from the focus group interviews on post-alert messages, their perceived purpose and the contents that are perceived to be most to participants who have experienced a false alert and to those who have not.    Preliminary findings suggest that trust in automated systems, such as earthquake early warnings, is likely to be moderated by prior hazard experience as well as prior false alerting experience.  Those who experience a false alert perceive this as a response cost, affecting perceptions of the overall system and trust in future warnings.   Furthermore, post-alert messages that are designed to follow a false or inaccurate alert need to provide assurance of safety to message receivers, especially for to those who are unfamiliar with earthquake hazards and/or the nature of the automated detection and warning system.     This research is the first to examine the effect of a false earthquake early warning on a population that had previously experienced a significant earthquake event.  The findings from this research will provide insight into warnings, false alerts, inaccurate alerts, and post-alert/cancellation messages for all hazards and for automated systems that deliver hazard warning messages to persons at risk.            Last Modified: 04/29/2022       Submitted by: Jeannette Sutton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
