<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[IUCRC Planning Grant University of Michigan – Ann Arbor (UM): Center for Secured Computation for Drug Discovery and Repurposing (SCDDR)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Behrooz Shirazi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bshirazi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928343</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Pharmaceutical development has a large impact on the nation’s economy and public health. Despite substantial annual outlays for pharmaceutical development, many drugs fail in clinical trial, while the majority of those making it to market fail to yield a profit. These costs and low returns hinder additional development. The Center for Secured Computation for Drug Discovery and Repurposing (SCDDR), through the pursuit of its research thrusts, has the potential to greatly enhance the national research infrastructure by increasing the capacity of the engineering/scientific workforce. In particular, SCDDR will produce new methodologies and infrastructure for industry-wide collaborative drug discovery, yielding new medicines at reduced cost.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center will focus on three main areas of unmet/underserved research needs within the (bio)pharmaceutical sector, with the goal of significantly accelerating the pace of drug discovery while reducing research costs: 1) the development, testing, and validation of machine learning methods for drug discovery and repurposing; 2) providing an industry-wide and vendor-agnostic Secure Data Hub for pharmaceutical and patient data with third-party private search capabilities; and 3) enable federated machine learning for drug repositioning over encrypted databases. Enabling these research thrusts are new developments in efficient fully homomorphic encryption and applications of coupled tensor-matrix and tensor-tensor completion methods to drug discovery and repurposing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project brings together data scientists, mathematicians, biomedical researchers, and healthcare providers to produce reproducible methodologies that will make a broad impact on drug discovery and biomedical applications of data science. SCCDR will build a world-class data science community that is inclusive and promotes diversity at all stages of the academic pipeline. The Center will support programs to educate the next generation of data science workforce members, research leaders, and citizens. By forming collaborations with industry, government, and community partners, the project will enable the dissemination and translation of research into impactful products and services for the betterment of society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A single Center-wide project repository, including published results, presentations, developed code, and educational materials, will be maintained and disseminated through the Center website – https://midas.umich.edu/scddr/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051997</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>H</FirstName>
<LastName>Jagadish</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>H V Jagadish</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jag@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000461011</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kayvan</FirstName>
<LastName>Najarian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kayvan Najarian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kayvan@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000399897</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gryak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Gryak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jgryak@qc.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788382</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Note:</strong> The proposed center was named Center for Secured Computation for Drug Discovery and Repurposing (SCDDR) in the planning phase but based on industry partner feedback the name was changed to the Center for Data-Driven Drug Development and Treatment Assessment (DATA), as described in the section Revisions to DATA?s Vision Due to Interactions with Partners.<br /><br /><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong><br />Before, during, and after the Planning Workshop, the DATA team had intensive interactions with potential partners that allowed us to revise our vision for the Center and collectively arrive to the current definition of DATA. Before the planning meeting, the DATA team conducted interviews with 30 individuals from 29 companies and organizations that span a wide range in size and focus. The faculty responded to questions, comments, and suggestions by the attendees. The primary lessons learned from interactions with industry partners were: 1) Industry partners emphasized the importance of focusing on drug assessment by analyzing the data collected by healthcare systems when drugs are used for treatment in clinical settings. It became evident that both pharmaceuticals and healthcare systems would put high priority on the use of machine learning and artificial intelligence methods on analyzing patient data to investigate potential drug adverse events and toxicity, and to identify patient phenotypes with respect to treatment response. Following the comments and feedback from the industry partners, we modified the vision of the Center to have a greater focus on using data-driven methods for drug assessment and changed the name of the proposed center to the Center for Data-Driven Drug Development and Treatment Assessment (DATA).<br /><br /><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong><br />The project brought together data scientists, mathematicians, biomedical researchers, and healthcare providers to devise methodologies that can be replicated to make a broad impact on drug discovery and biomedical applications of data science. A postdoctoral research fellow received training as part of this project, enabling them to engage in discussions and be exposed to potential fields of study and research directions. DATA PIs have planned an annual Data Science Summer Camp for High School Students, in which participants learn the basic mathematics behind data science and work on team projects with classmates using real life examples. In anticipation of funding, DATA PIs have developed course curricula at both the undergraduate and graduate levels to facilitate the usage of Center data and research methodologies in student projects.<br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Gryak</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Note: The proposed center was named Center for Secured Computation for Drug Discovery and Repurposing (SCDDR) in the planning phase but based on industry partner feedback the name was changed to the Center for Data-Driven Drug Development and Treatment Assessment (DATA), as described in the section Revisions to DATA?s Vision Due to Interactions with Partners.  Intellectual Merit: Before, during, and after the Planning Workshop, the DATA team had intensive interactions with potential partners that allowed us to revise our vision for the Center and collectively arrive to the current definition of DATA. Before the planning meeting, the DATA team conducted interviews with 30 individuals from 29 companies and organizations that span a wide range in size and focus. The faculty responded to questions, comments, and suggestions by the attendees. The primary lessons learned from interactions with industry partners were: 1) Industry partners emphasized the importance of focusing on drug assessment by analyzing the data collected by healthcare systems when drugs are used for treatment in clinical settings. It became evident that both pharmaceuticals and healthcare systems would put high priority on the use of machine learning and artificial intelligence methods on analyzing patient data to investigate potential drug adverse events and toxicity, and to identify patient phenotypes with respect to treatment response. Following the comments and feedback from the industry partners, we modified the vision of the Center to have a greater focus on using data-driven methods for drug assessment and changed the name of the proposed center to the Center for Data-Driven Drug Development and Treatment Assessment (DATA).  Broader Impacts: The project brought together data scientists, mathematicians, biomedical researchers, and healthcare providers to devise methodologies that can be replicated to make a broad impact on drug discovery and biomedical applications of data science. A postdoctoral research fellow received training as part of this project, enabling them to engage in discussions and be exposed to potential fields of study and research directions. DATA PIs have planned an annual Data Science Summer Camp for High School Students, in which participants learn the basic mathematics behind data science and work on team projects with classmates using real life examples. In anticipation of funding, DATA PIs have developed course curricula at both the undergraduate and graduate levels to facilitate the usage of Center data and research methodologies in student projects.          Last Modified: 06/09/2022       Submitted by: Jonathan Gryak]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
