<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Solvent-based Roll-to-Roll Nanoimprinting for Large Area Nanopatterning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79310.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>87310</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Nanostructured materials exhibit extraordinary optical, electrical, mechanical and chemical properties that enable novel devices with enhanced performance and functionality. Nanostructures are frequently utilized in numerous applications including photovoltaics, chemical and biological sensing, biotechnology, solid-state lighting, hydrogen production via photocatalytic water splitting and other uses. These various areas of nanotechnology demand nanofabrication techniques that are cost effective and practical while maintaining quality control and process flexibility. The nanofabrication techniques must also be scalable in order to be seamlessly applied to real-world applications beyond the laboratory. Despite progress having been made, a versatile nanofabrication technology that can meets all necessary requirements is lacking. This research will open up a new nanomanufacturing process pathway that can be applied to speed-up laboratory and pilot-scale device development and also be scaled-up for large-area, high-throughput product manufacturing. This research will make significant impacts on the fields of nanotechnology, nanomanufacturing, plasmonics, optoelectronics and nanophotonics. Plans are for graduate and undergraduate students from underrepresented groups to receive training, participate in this highly interdisciplinary research and conduct experiments in the new Washington Clean Energy Testbeds facility.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nanoimprint lithography is a simple, low-cost, high-resolution and high-throughput nanofabrication technique with compatibility for large-scale roll-to-roll manufacturing. However, current roll-to-roll nanoimprint lithography processes are all based on either thermal or ultraviolet-based curing techniques that require either high temperature or special photopolymer resists. In addition, roller molds are typically made by time-consuming and costly fabrication processes. The research team aims to design and develop a new roll-to-roll nanoimprint lithography process using environmentally friendly polymer resists and a high-resolution composite belt mold. The research is accomplished through fundamental understanding of mechanics and fluid dynamics of mold cavity filling under solvent-assisted conditions to produce quality nanostructures on large area flexible substrates with high resolution and high throughput. Solvent-assisted nanoimprinting offers a low temperature and low pressure process, which eliminates issues resulting from thermal expansion variations between the mold, substrate and resist and reduces energy input costs while increasing processing speed. New composite elastomeric belt molds are easily and affordably replicated for rapid prototyping while providing high-resolution. The high quality nanostructures on flexible substrates are fabricated using this method and integrated in to novel flexible optoelectronic devices to demonstrate its capabilities.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051617</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Qiuming</FirstName>
<LastName>Yu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Qiuming Yu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[qy10@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000168532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1788</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>081E</Code>
<Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~79310</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nanostructured materials exhibit extraordinary optical, electrical, mechanical and chemical properties that enable novel devices with enhanced performance and functionality. Nanostructures are more frequently being utilized in numerous applications including photovoltaics, chemical and biological sensing, biotechnology, solid-state lighting, hydrogen production via photocatalytic water splitting and other uses. These various areas of nanotechnology demand novel nanofabrication techniques that are cost effective and practical while maintaining quality control and process flexibility. The nanofabrication techniques must also be scalable in order to be seamlessly applied to real-world applications beyond the laboratory. Despite progress having been made, a versatile nanofabrication technology that can meet all necessary requirements is lacking.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> In this work, we designed and developed a new roll-to-roll nanoimprint lithography process using environmentally friendly polymer resists and a high-resolution composite belt mold. We used nanosphere lithography method to generate nanosphere patterns, transferred the nanopatterns onto PDMS and then used flexible PDMS as belt mold to transfer nanopatterns to polymer photoresisters and even directly to semiconducting polymer films via solvent-assisted nanoimprinting. Solvent-assisted nanoimprinting offers a low temperature and low-pressure process, which eliminates issues resulting from thermal expansion variations between the mold, substrate and resist and reduces energy input costs while increasing processing speed. The composite elastomeric belt molds based on PDMS are easily and cheaply replicated for rapid prototyping while providing high-resolution. We analyzed viscosity of photoresisters as a function of molecular weight of photoresister, photoresister concentration in acetone, pressure, and temperature to gain fundamental understanding of mechanics and fluid dynamics of mold cavity filling under solvent-assisted conditions. Besides photoresisters, we also synthesized conducting polymers with functional groups and organic-inorganic halide perovskites quantum dots, which are compatible with roll-to-roll processing for manufacturing biosensors and optoelectronic devices. We demonstrated the successful incorporation of nanopatterns into biosesnors and photovoltaic devices and photodetectors with enhanced performance.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact:</strong> The fundamental understanding of mechanics and fluid dynamics of mold cavity filling under solvent-assisted conditions and the large area nanoimprinting techniques developed in this project open up a new nanomanufacturing process pathway that can be applied to speed-up laboratory and pilot-scale device development and also be scaled-up for large-area, high-throughput product manufacturing. Results from this project could make significant impact on the fields of nanotechnology, nanomanufacturing, plasmonics, optoelectronics, nanophotonics, and biosensing. Graduate, undergraduate, and community college students and postdocs received training and participated in this highly interdisciplinary research project, especially students from underrepresented groups such as female. They had opportunities conducting experiments in the facilities of Washington Clean Energy Testbeds and the Center for Functional Nanomaterials at the Brookhaven National Laboratory. The knowledge gained from this work have been disseminated through the new course the PI developed, the Pilot REU in Data-enabled Science and Engineering (PRDSE) for community college students, the ?Introduce a Girl? series outreach program, and the Engineering Discovery Days on the UW campus,</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Qiuming&nbsp;Yu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651463627462_Image1Solvetn-assistedR2RNIL--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651463627462_Image1Solvetn-assistedR2RNIL--rgov-800width.jpg" title="R2R NIL"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651463627462_Image1Solvetn-assistedR2RNIL--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="R2R NIL"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Illustration of roll-to-roll nanoimprinting experimental setup and fundamental understanding of mechanics and and fluid dynamics of mold cavity filling under solvent-assisted conditions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Qiuming Yu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Qiuming&nbsp;Yu</div> <div class="imageTitle">R2R NIL</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651463795434_Image2nanobumpsinUVphotodetectors--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651463795434_Image2nanobumpsinUVphotodetectors--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanobumps in UV Photodetectors"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651463795434_Image2nanobumpsinUVphotodetectors--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanobumps in UV Photodetectors"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nanofabrication of nano-hemispheres on top of polymer active layer of photodetectors and its enhancement in photodetector performance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Monica Esopi and Qiuming Yu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Qiuming&nbsp;Yu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanobumps in UV Photodetectors</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651464024377_Image3NanoholeforUVphotodetector--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651464024377_Image3NanoholeforUVphotodetector--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanohole in UV photodetectors"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2051617/2051617_10484876_1651464024377_Image3NanoholeforUVphotodetector--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanohole in UV photodetectors"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Illustration of nanosphere lithography and nanoimpriting for making aluminum nanoholes as anode in UV photodetectors and its effect in manipulator photoresponse via bias.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Monica Esopi and Qiuming Yu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Qiuming&nbsp;Yu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanohole in UV photodetectors</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nanostructured materials exhibit extraordinary optical, electrical, mechanical and chemical properties that enable novel devices with enhanced performance and functionality. Nanostructures are more frequently being utilized in numerous applications including photovoltaics, chemical and biological sensing, biotechnology, solid-state lighting, hydrogen production via photocatalytic water splitting and other uses. These various areas of nanotechnology demand novel nanofabrication techniques that are cost effective and practical while maintaining quality control and process flexibility. The nanofabrication techniques must also be scalable in order to be seamlessly applied to real-world applications beyond the laboratory. Despite progress having been made, a versatile nanofabrication technology that can meet all necessary requirements is lacking.  Intellectual Merit: In this work, we designed and developed a new roll-to-roll nanoimprint lithography process using environmentally friendly polymer resists and a high-resolution composite belt mold. We used nanosphere lithography method to generate nanosphere patterns, transferred the nanopatterns onto PDMS and then used flexible PDMS as belt mold to transfer nanopatterns to polymer photoresisters and even directly to semiconducting polymer films via solvent-assisted nanoimprinting. Solvent-assisted nanoimprinting offers a low temperature and low-pressure process, which eliminates issues resulting from thermal expansion variations between the mold, substrate and resist and reduces energy input costs while increasing processing speed. The composite elastomeric belt molds based on PDMS are easily and cheaply replicated for rapid prototyping while providing high-resolution. We analyzed viscosity of photoresisters as a function of molecular weight of photoresister, photoresister concentration in acetone, pressure, and temperature to gain fundamental understanding of mechanics and fluid dynamics of mold cavity filling under solvent-assisted conditions. Besides photoresisters, we also synthesized conducting polymers with functional groups and organic-inorganic halide perovskites quantum dots, which are compatible with roll-to-roll processing for manufacturing biosensors and optoelectronic devices. We demonstrated the successful incorporation of nanopatterns into biosesnors and photovoltaic devices and photodetectors with enhanced performance.  Broader Impact: The fundamental understanding of mechanics and fluid dynamics of mold cavity filling under solvent-assisted conditions and the large area nanoimprinting techniques developed in this project open up a new nanomanufacturing process pathway that can be applied to speed-up laboratory and pilot-scale device development and also be scaled-up for large-area, high-throughput product manufacturing. Results from this project could make significant impact on the fields of nanotechnology, nanomanufacturing, plasmonics, optoelectronics, nanophotonics, and biosensing. Graduate, undergraduate, and community college students and postdocs received training and participated in this highly interdisciplinary research project, especially students from underrepresented groups such as female. They had opportunities conducting experiments in the facilities of Washington Clean Energy Testbeds and the Center for Functional Nanomaterials at the Brookhaven National Laboratory. The knowledge gained from this work have been disseminated through the new course the PI developed, the Pilot REU in Data-enabled Science and Engineering (PRDSE) for community college students, the ?Introduce a Girl? series outreach program, and the Engineering Discovery Days on the UW campus,          Last Modified: 05/02/2022       Submitted by: Qiuming Yu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
