<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Autonomous Living Assistant]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samir M. Iqbal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smiqbal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927529</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is a wider adoption of autonomous technologies among residential buildings. This research proposes evaluating the use of advanced sensor technologies and machine learning algorithms to enable inexpensive hardware infrastructures to control the conditions in indoor space autonomously. This technology fits well within the capacity of residential buildings. One main benefit of indoor automation is deep energy savings. The Department of Energy estimates a 5% reduction of the country's total energy bill if existing residential buildings save 25% of their energy consumption. The autonomous controller evaluated in this project has the potential to reach this goal, saving the nation up to $63 billion and the planet 284 million metric tons of carbon dioxide emissions. Alongside energy efficiency, the associated societal benefits of the proposed project can potentially save lives. The technologies may spur a higher level of security protection among many unprotected residential spaces. Additionally, tracking occupants’ habits may enable alerts to caregivers or family members in critical emergency situations. This can be beneficial for the aging population that wants to stay within the comfort of their own home.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance the scientific knowledge required to approach full autonomous control in indoor spaces. The use of advanced perception sensors in buildings will be evaluated. Their rich data stream will be utilized to develop advanced algorithms for autonomous control of indoor spaces. Advances in sensing technologies and machine learning algorithms will be used to instigate technological evolution in autonomous building systems.  A proof of concept will be developed to mitigate the unique risks associated caused by applying autonomous control in indoor spaces, specifically: achieving advanced perception, self-programmability, and reliability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051981</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mustafa</FirstName>
<LastName>Homsi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mustafa Homsi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mustafa.homsi@rivieh.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000830908</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>RIVIEH, INC.</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900172580</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6144046367</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1050 INGRAHAM ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[APT 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RNLHNT2V1C54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RIVIEH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RIVIEH, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900172580</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1050 INGRAHAM ST, APT 240]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4097</Code>
<Text>NETWORKING RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Small Business Innovation Research, SBIR, Phase 1 project researched the feasibility of using a new sensing technology to approach an advanced level of spatial awareness in indoor spaces. A building automation system with an advanced level of localization perception can significantly improve buildings' energy efficiency, comfort, security, and safety. To achieve this goal, a unique signal processing pipeline was developed. This was needed to accommodate the new sensing data format that is uncommon in the built environment. The newly developed pipeline processes raw high-bandwidth signals through multiple blocks until occupants' locations within the space are identified. Once this level of awareness has been achieved, higher-level algorithms use this perception insight to effectively optimize the conditions within buildings.</p> <p><br />To prove the feasibility of the entire solution and mitigate associated technical risks, the system was tested in real-life use cases to evaluate and address the unique challenges of using advanced sensors in indoor spaces. The test plan was divided into five objectives spread across nine tasks. Each task was responsible for developing the hardware and software associated with a given testing objective. In conclusion, the results gathered during this research project proved the technical feasibility of the proposed solution and its potential to offer practical and valuable automation benefits in the built environment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Mustafa&nbsp;Homsi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovation Research, SBIR, Phase 1 project researched the feasibility of using a new sensing technology to approach an advanced level of spatial awareness in indoor spaces. A building automation system with an advanced level of localization perception can significantly improve buildings' energy efficiency, comfort, security, and safety. To achieve this goal, a unique signal processing pipeline was developed. This was needed to accommodate the new sensing data format that is uncommon in the built environment. The newly developed pipeline processes raw high-bandwidth signals through multiple blocks until occupants' locations within the space are identified. Once this level of awareness has been achieved, higher-level algorithms use this perception insight to effectively optimize the conditions within buildings.   To prove the feasibility of the entire solution and mitigate associated technical risks, the system was tested in real-life use cases to evaluate and address the unique challenges of using advanced sensors in indoor spaces. The test plan was divided into five objectives spread across nine tasks. Each task was responsible for developing the hardware and software associated with a given testing objective. In conclusion, the results gathered during this research project proved the technical feasibility of the proposed solution and its potential to offer practical and valuable automation benefits in the built environment.          Last Modified: 03/31/2023       Submitted by: Mustafa Homsi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
