<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:Development of a Multi-Robot System to Reduce End-to-End Labor Automation Costs in Local Food Production]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255147.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255147</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this SBIR Phase I project lie in the greater availability of healthy, local, and affordable produce for all levels of society through new methods of end-to-end labor automation and energy management in urban agriculture. Through a low-footprint vertical greenhouse design, this technology will enable individuals to grow produce on small areas of available space for their community. The produce will be an attractive alternative to large-scale industrial agriculture and foreign food imports, not only for sustainability concerns, but through its superior freshness, quality, and taste. This project will have an impact on the advancement of local farming technologies to further the viability of commercial food production in urban communities. Creating an economically viable urban farm will have lasting impacts on the U.S. food system and environment as it will provide a means for sustainable food production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Phase I effort will be used to design, build, and demonstrate a subscale vertical farm prototype that demonstrates cost-effective methods for all aspects of the farm’s end-to-end labor automation. This will advance the implementation of robotics in food production by addressing the labor and energy barriers that local controlled environmental agriculture systems currently face. To achieve this objective, key challenges include (1) automation to completely remove human labor over extended durations, (2) low-cost design for setup and ongoing operations, and (3) the ability to adjust product outputs in real-time to market demands. Human interaction with the grow process will be limited through high degree of system automation, including computer vision for plant inspections and self-cleaning processes. Novel plant growth and handling processes will allow for virtually any type of produce. A variety of sensors are used to carefully monitor conditions and adjust the system, allowing fresh produce in areas without suitable agricultural opportunities. The prototype robotic farming system being developed in the Phase I effort will demonstrate the end-to-end labor automation and energy management technologies necessary to the expansion of urban agriculture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051419</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ashton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David L Ashton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dashton@canopii.us]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829251</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CANOPII INC.</Name>
<CityName>SILVERTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>973811942</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9162139550</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>191 IOWA ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LX2YMERKNBL3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CANOPII INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ASHTON, DAVID]]></Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972151737</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4730 SE Belmont Street - Unit 5]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255147</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Recent years have shown the severe impact that environmental, political, social, and health issues can have on the United States produce supply. Record weather events have caused agricultural losses, Covid-19 and foreign conflicts significantly disrupted supply chains, and labor shortages have impacted virtually every American business sector. The traditional U.S. agricultural system is unprepared to deal with the challenges that modern society is facing. The technology developed by Canopii Inc. in this NSF Phase I SBIR project is a fully automated vertical greenhouse designed to reduce the environmental footprint of traditional agriculture, increase supply chain security, and alleviate labor shortage problems.</p> <p>This NSF Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project successfully advanced the application of robotics in greenhouses through a novel system design. Though this system design, the complexity associated with current greenhouse robotics such as navigation systems, can be mitigated. This system?s robust, easy-to-use, and cost-effective features will increase the accessibility of automation technology in agriculture. The technical accomplishments in this project enabled difficult greenhouse tasks such as seeding, transplanting, harvesting, root removal, sorting, and self-cleaning to be fully automated. The extent of the Phase I accomplishments in farm robotics sets the foundation of complete farm autonomy for a month at a time, a level of automation that is unmet in the industry.</p> <p>The technology developed through this Phase I SBIR can provide an alternative solution for food production. Complete labor automation, combined with a controlled environment and a vertical farming approach, will incentivize growing food closer to the consumer. A distributed model for food production will reduce greenhouse gas emissions associated current farming and supply chain practices.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/03/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;L&nbsp;Ashton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Recent years have shown the severe impact that environmental, political, social, and health issues can have on the United States produce supply. Record weather events have caused agricultural losses, Covid-19 and foreign conflicts significantly disrupted supply chains, and labor shortages have impacted virtually every American business sector. The traditional U.S. agricultural system is unprepared to deal with the challenges that modern society is facing. The technology developed by Canopii Inc. in this NSF Phase I SBIR project is a fully automated vertical greenhouse designed to reduce the environmental footprint of traditional agriculture, increase supply chain security, and alleviate labor shortage problems.  This NSF Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project successfully advanced the application of robotics in greenhouses through a novel system design. Though this system design, the complexity associated with current greenhouse robotics such as navigation systems, can be mitigated. This system?s robust, easy-to-use, and cost-effective features will increase the accessibility of automation technology in agriculture. The technical accomplishments in this project enabled difficult greenhouse tasks such as seeding, transplanting, harvesting, root removal, sorting, and self-cleaning to be fully automated. The extent of the Phase I accomplishments in farm robotics sets the foundation of complete farm autonomy for a month at a time, a level of automation that is unmet in the industry.  The technology developed through this Phase I SBIR can provide an alternative solution for food production. Complete labor automation, combined with a controlled environment and a vertical farming approach, will incentivize growing food closer to the consumer. A distributed model for food production will reduce greenhouse gas emissions associated current farming and supply chain practices.          Last Modified: 05/03/2022       Submitted by: David L Ashton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
