<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Production of Low-Cost Ti Alloys by Direct Reduction and Alloying]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>252648.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>252648</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to address the shortage or lack of the U.S.'s supply chain for primary titanium metal production, for which the U.S. relies on imports almost entirely, by developing new low-cost process technology for making titanium alloys. Titanium alloys are critical materials to the nation's aerospace, defense, transportation, energy, chemical, and biomedical industries. This project will enhance the competitiveness of the U.S. titanium manufacturing industry. Furthermore, low-cost titanium will expand its use in vehicles, contributing to reducing fuel (or power) consumption of vehicles and carbon emissions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conventionally, titanium (Ti) alloys are made by melting pure Ti sponge with alloying additives using vacuum arc remelting (VAR). Ti sponge is made by the Kroll process, which is a multi-step process involving chlorination of titanium dioxide (TiO2) to form titanium tetrachloride (TiCl4), the reduction of TiCl4 by magnesium (Mg). The cost of Ti alloy ingot depends on the cost of Ti sponge and the melt-refining (e.g., VAR) process. Typically, Ti sponge accounts for more than 70% of the cost of Ti alloy ingot. The melt-refining process is also a significant cost contributor because Ti alloy ingot has to be melted for two or more times to achieve the required purity and compositional homogeneity. This project proposes to develop a low-cost melt-less process for the production of titanium alloys by direct reduction and alloying (DRA). If successful, the DRA process can reduce the cost of Ti mill products significantly. The product of the proposed process can be used for many applications, including as Ti alloy powder, or as feedstock for manufacturing Ti mill products, or as consolidated near-net-shape components.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051641</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pei</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pei Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pei.sun@blacksandtechllc.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000696809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Blacksand Technology LLC</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841192010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8014143251</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1784 W 2300 S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UNIT 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LLKDKJEWRBC1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BLACKSAND TECHNOLOGY LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Blacksand Technology LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>West Valley City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841192010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1784 W 2300 S. Unit 3]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~252648</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this NSF SBIR Phase I project, Blacksand Technology demonstrated the feasibility of the production of titanium alloy powders (specifically, Ti-6Al-4V, the most commonly used Ti alloy in industries) by the Direct Reduction and Alloying (DRA) process. The DRA process consists of two major steps for removing oxygen from the oxides and the metal:(1) Co-reduction of sintered oxides with Mg under hydrogen. After reduction, the oxygen content in the alloy is approximately 1.0-2.0 wt.% compared to 40.9 wt.% in the oxides.(2) Deoxygenation of co-reduced Ti-6Al-4V-(1.0-2.0) O with Mg under hydrogen to less than 0.20 wt.% oxygen.</p> <p>A heat-treatment step is designed to close the surface porosities created by Mg-reduction to lower specific surface area and thus decrease the oxygen in the final powder. Ti-6Al-4V alloy powder produced from the DRA process has low oxygen content (&lt;0.18%), which meets the typical requirement for industrial applications (max. 0.20 wt.% for ASTM Grade 5). In addition, spherical Ti-6Al-4V powder can be also produced for additive manufacturing applications by adding a spray-drying step.</p> <p>At the core of the proposed process is our breakthrough discovery that enables the removal of oxygen in Ti by leveraging the effects of both Mg and hydrogen on the stability of Ti-O synergistically. Simple reduction of TiO<sub>2</sub> by Mg cannot produce low-oxygen Ti because Ti-O solid solution is more stable than MgO. However, we discovered that hydrogen can destabilize Ti-O solid solutions, thus enabling Mg, in the presence of hydrogen, to extract oxygen out of the Ti to very low level. This discovery was unknown and has not been exploited by the research or the industrial community. DRA process is designed to exploit this thermodynamic phenomenon for the production of low oxygen Ti alloys without resorting to Kroll and melting processes.</p> <p>Based our techno-economic analysis, DRA can produce Ti alloy powders not only at a lower cost but also with fewer carbon emissions than Ti alloy powder made from the Kroll process. At a large scale, the energy consumption per kilogram of spherical Ti alloy powder made from DRA can potentially be 67% less than that made from the Kroll process. Furthermore, DRA's proprietary process can take metal oxides as feedstock and produces a higher yield than commercially available alternatives. The low-carbon component of the value proposition was demonstrated, at the laboratory scale, by improving process efficiencies, reducing the quantity and intensity of furnace/melt process steps, removing carbon as an input, and eliminating the high-emissions chlorination step. DRA consumes substantially less energy than the competing Kroll and gas atomization method for producing metal powders, thereby reducing carbon emissions. In addition, if successful, the effort will be a pathway to reshoring the titanium supply chain from titanium ores to titanium components for the U.S. The development and commercialization of the proposed technology domestically will contribute to not only the manufacturing competitiveness but also the national security of the U.S.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Pei&nbsp;Sun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this NSF SBIR Phase I project, Blacksand Technology demonstrated the feasibility of the production of titanium alloy powders (specifically, Ti-6Al-4V, the most commonly used Ti alloy in industries) by the Direct Reduction and Alloying (DRA) process. The DRA process consists of two major steps for removing oxygen from the oxides and the metal:(1) Co-reduction of sintered oxides with Mg under hydrogen. After reduction, the oxygen content in the alloy is approximately 1.0-2.0 wt.% compared to 40.9 wt.% in the oxides.(2) Deoxygenation of co-reduced Ti-6Al-4V-(1.0-2.0) O with Mg under hydrogen to less than 0.20 wt.% oxygen.  A heat-treatment step is designed to close the surface porosities created by Mg-reduction to lower specific surface area and thus decrease the oxygen in the final powder. Ti-6Al-4V alloy powder produced from the DRA process has low oxygen content (&lt;0.18%), which meets the typical requirement for industrial applications (max. 0.20 wt.% for ASTM Grade 5). In addition, spherical Ti-6Al-4V powder can be also produced for additive manufacturing applications by adding a spray-drying step.  At the core of the proposed process is our breakthrough discovery that enables the removal of oxygen in Ti by leveraging the effects of both Mg and hydrogen on the stability of Ti-O synergistically. Simple reduction of TiO2 by Mg cannot produce low-oxygen Ti because Ti-O solid solution is more stable than MgO. However, we discovered that hydrogen can destabilize Ti-O solid solutions, thus enabling Mg, in the presence of hydrogen, to extract oxygen out of the Ti to very low level. This discovery was unknown and has not been exploited by the research or the industrial community. DRA process is designed to exploit this thermodynamic phenomenon for the production of low oxygen Ti alloys without resorting to Kroll and melting processes.  Based our techno-economic analysis, DRA can produce Ti alloy powders not only at a lower cost but also with fewer carbon emissions than Ti alloy powder made from the Kroll process. At a large scale, the energy consumption per kilogram of spherical Ti alloy powder made from DRA can potentially be 67% less than that made from the Kroll process. Furthermore, DRA's proprietary process can take metal oxides as feedstock and produces a higher yield than commercially available alternatives. The low-carbon component of the value proposition was demonstrated, at the laboratory scale, by improving process efficiencies, reducing the quantity and intensity of furnace/melt process steps, removing carbon as an input, and eliminating the high-emissions chlorination step. DRA consumes substantially less energy than the competing Kroll and gas atomization method for producing metal powders, thereby reducing carbon emissions. In addition, if successful, the effort will be a pathway to reshoring the titanium supply chain from titanium ores to titanium components for the U.S. The development and commercialization of the proposed technology domestically will contribute to not only the manufacturing competitiveness but also the national security of the U.S.          Last Modified: 09/20/2022       Submitted by: Pei Sun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
