<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Ultrasonic Measurement Instrument for Pharmaceutical Tablet Design, Development, and Continuous Manufacturing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255962.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255962</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to improve quality control in pharmaceutical manufacturing. The compressed tablet is the most popular pharmaceutical dosage form in use worldwide. Despite its well-established manufacturing processes, issues with tablet quality are frequent. Issues in its design and manufacturing have the potential to make significant medical and financial impacts as failures in quality may result in harm to patients, product recalls, and medicine shortages. The proposed Ultrasonic Measurement Instrument (UMI) unit will substantially shorten drug tablet design/development cycles and detect/identify manufacturing and quality problems before release. Its utilization in modern continuous manufacturing lines will minimize the risk of defective tablet production/disposition and costly product recalls/disposals. The UMI unit will lead to two distinct solutions: (i) a real-time preventive quality monitoring device for continuous manufacturing production line and (ii) a stand-alone laboratory equipment for characterizing tablet physical properties. The target users for our UMI-based products include pharmaceutical manufacturers; equipment providers; generic drug manufacturers; R&amp;D groups and drug development teams in corporations and universities; and compounding pharmacies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project and its ultrasonic approach have several critical advantages over the competing quality assessment and monitoring technologies for pharmaceutical manufacturing. Unlike other detection techniques, ultrasound directly interacts with the mass density, material elasticity/viscoelasticity, defects/cracks, and inhomogeneities of a medium and piezoelectric transducers are the most sensitive devices for transient strain sensing. Operating in MHz frequency, ultrasonic techniques make rapid (micro-seconds scale) measurements at relevant wavelengths for tablet and defect sizes (micrometer to millimeter scales). Challenges to be addressed include: (i) existing wave propagation models for viscoelastic tablet materials with microstructures are inadequate for accurate materials characterization/valuation with ultrasound, and (ii) a precise handling and positioning apparatus for tablets is needed, as for machine learning and data analytics/mining, the repeatable acquisition and processing of large data sets are required. The main outcome of the project is a proof-of-concept testing/measurement unit (UMI) with a precise tablet handling sub-system and its accompanying mathematical algorithms for the formation of large data sets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaochi</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaochi Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xiaxu@clarkson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000837106</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/24/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cetin</FirstName>
<LastName>Cetinkaya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cetin Cetinkaya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[info@pharmacoustics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000314747</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Bazzocchi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael C Bazzocchi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbazzocc@clarkson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000845575</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/24/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PHARMACOUSTICS TECHNOLOGIES LLC</Name>
<CityName>POTSDAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>136763202</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3152768051</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6 CIRCLE DR.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q3MXF165G6H9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PHARMACOUSTICS TECHNOLOGIES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pharmacoustics Technologies, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>POTSDAM</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>136763202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6 CIRCLE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255962</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The quality of pharmaceutical products is the foundation that allows patients and consumers to have confidence in the safety and effectiveness of their medications. Nearly 70% of US patients and consumers are on at least one prescription drug, and more than half take two. Vulnerabilities in the supply of drugs, including generics, have been linked to drug quality and safety concerns, and notably geography-based concerns, including weather-related events impacting domestic production and controversies involving international trade provisions among foreign manufacturers. High costs and price volatilities have also been noted among specific generic prescription drugs in the USA, often related to supply or quality concerns. The recent coronavirus (Covid-19) pandemic has heightened concerns regarding USA's reliance on foreign drugs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As of 2020, 74% of all active pharmaceutical ingredients (APIs) and 54% of all finished dosage form human drug products were manufactured at production facilities outside the US. About 78% of API manufacturers are located outside of the USA.<strong>&nbsp;</strong>In addition, most pharmaceutical manufacturing equipment makers are headquartered outside the USA. Among the top five equipment makers, there is no U.S.-based company.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The compressed drug tablet is the most popular oral solid dosage (OSD) form in use worldwide. However, compared to many other industries, the unit operation-based Batch Manufacturing (BM) approach currently employed in the pharmaceutical manufacturing industry is often outdated. In the past decade, a handful of large companies have adopted a new paradigm to replace the current BM with Continuous Manufacturing (CM). However, the transformation process has been sluggish, as smaller and generic manufacturers have been slow to adopt for various reasons, such as high cost, lack of expertise, and lack of regulations and standards. One cost-saving component in the process is the Real-Time Release (RTR) of OSD forms, which will eliminate or minimize costly, time-consuming manual release processes. In this&nbsp;<em>STTR Phase I</em>&nbsp;project, we developed a set of mathematical analysis methods and experimental techniques to be used in the ultrasonic viscoelastic and microstructure characterization of OSD forms in the RTR of OSD forms in CM. Our findings target to support two distinct product groups: (i<span style="text-decoration: underline;">)</span>&nbsp;RTR and a real-time quality monitoring unit for CM production lines&nbsp;and (ii) a stand-alone laboratory device for characterizing tablet physical properties to be used in drug design and development laboratories.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our most significant result is that we have demonstrated that we can accurately sense and characterize the defect state, shape, viscoelastic, granular scattering, and anisotropic properties of tablets using our ultrasonic proof-of-concept platform. Specifically, our accomplishments and project outcomes are as follows:</p> <p>+ A proof-of-concept platform with automation has been built and utilized to acquire data published or submitted for publication in the form of peer-reviewed journal articles in leading journals. Its robotic tablet handling system for consistent and repeatable tablet testing and characterization has been demonstrated.</p> <p>+ A characterization technique for micro-viscoelastic materials with a machine learning approach has been developed, and a proof-of-concept study has been conducted.</p> <p>+ For the first time, we have demonstrated that the characterization of&nbsp;viscoelastic media and granularity simultaneously&nbsp;can be extracted.&nbsp;</p> <p>+ An advanced mathematical modeling technique for ultrasonic wave propagation in viscoelastic media with granularity has been developed and demonstrated. Mathematical modeling and algorithm development for the extraction of micro-viscoelastic and scattering properties of compressed oral solid dosage materials in a non-destructive manner</p> <p>+ Based on our experience in the project, we have completed a commercialization plan development effort based on a customer discovery study under SBIR Bootcamp Winter 2022 and the Dawnbreaker program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our project's ultimate societal impact objective is to increase the quality of drug products via real-time testing and lower the cost of their production/manufacturing by incorporating high-technology monitoring techniques and equipment.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Cetin&nbsp;Cetinkaya</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The quality of pharmaceutical products is the foundation that allows patients and consumers to have confidence in the safety and effectiveness of their medications. Nearly 70% of US patients and consumers are on at least one prescription drug, and more than half take two. Vulnerabilities in the supply of drugs, including generics, have been linked to drug quality and safety concerns, and notably geography-based concerns, including weather-related events impacting domestic production and controversies involving international trade provisions among foreign manufacturers. High costs and price volatilities have also been noted among specific generic prescription drugs in the USA, often related to supply or quality concerns. The recent coronavirus (Covid-19) pandemic has heightened concerns regarding USA's reliance on foreign drugs.     As of 2020, 74% of all active pharmaceutical ingredients (APIs) and 54% of all finished dosage form human drug products were manufactured at production facilities outside the US. About 78% of API manufacturers are located outside of the USA. In addition, most pharmaceutical manufacturing equipment makers are headquartered outside the USA. Among the top five equipment makers, there is no U.S.-based company.     The compressed drug tablet is the most popular oral solid dosage (OSD) form in use worldwide. However, compared to many other industries, the unit operation-based Batch Manufacturing (BM) approach currently employed in the pharmaceutical manufacturing industry is often outdated. In the past decade, a handful of large companies have adopted a new paradigm to replace the current BM with Continuous Manufacturing (CM). However, the transformation process has been sluggish, as smaller and generic manufacturers have been slow to adopt for various reasons, such as high cost, lack of expertise, and lack of regulations and standards. One cost-saving component in the process is the Real-Time Release (RTR) of OSD forms, which will eliminate or minimize costly, time-consuming manual release processes. In this STTR Phase I project, we developed a set of mathematical analysis methods and experimental techniques to be used in the ultrasonic viscoelastic and microstructure characterization of OSD forms in the RTR of OSD forms in CM. Our findings target to support two distinct product groups: (i) RTR and a real-time quality monitoring unit for CM production lines and (ii) a stand-alone laboratory device for characterizing tablet physical properties to be used in drug design and development laboratories.     Our most significant result is that we have demonstrated that we can accurately sense and characterize the defect state, shape, viscoelastic, granular scattering, and anisotropic properties of tablets using our ultrasonic proof-of-concept platform. Specifically, our accomplishments and project outcomes are as follows:  + A proof-of-concept platform with automation has been built and utilized to acquire data published or submitted for publication in the form of peer-reviewed journal articles in leading journals. Its robotic tablet handling system for consistent and repeatable tablet testing and characterization has been demonstrated.  + A characterization technique for micro-viscoelastic materials with a machine learning approach has been developed, and a proof-of-concept study has been conducted.  + For the first time, we have demonstrated that the characterization of viscoelastic media and granularity simultaneously can be extracted.   + An advanced mathematical modeling technique for ultrasonic wave propagation in viscoelastic media with granularity has been developed and demonstrated. Mathematical modeling and algorithm development for the extraction of micro-viscoelastic and scattering properties of compressed oral solid dosage materials in a non-destructive manner  + Based on our experience in the project, we have completed a commercialization plan development effort based on a customer discovery study under SBIR Bootcamp Winter 2022 and the Dawnbreaker program.     Our project's ultimate societal impact objective is to increase the quality of drug products via real-time testing and lower the cost of their production/manufacturing by incorporating high-technology monitoring techniques and equipment.       Last Modified: 12/21/2022       Submitted by: Cetin Cetinkaya]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
