<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Requisite lifetimes for coherent transition pathways in electron transfer flavoprotein: a quantum biology approach]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Engin Serpersu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eserpers@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927124</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[One of the great challenges of modern science is to bridge the gap between atomic and cellular level phenomena that affect outcomes in living systems. A potentially transformational facet of this challenge is Quantum Biology: understanding how quantum properties play governing roles in biological functions. The overarching goal of this project seeks to apply theory-driven predictions of Quantum Biology for multi-scale integration of cellular function. The inter-disciplinary team proposes to use front-edge computational and modelling techniques in synergy with advanced magnetic resonance techniques to probe quantum coherent pathways in the biochemical activity of electron transfer flavoprotein (ETF) that controls the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS). ROS is a highly reactive species and its buildup in cell causes damages and eventual cell death. The project aims to use computational and experimental approaches to provide ground-breaking insights into the requisite lifetimes for quantum coherence in ETF and its role in ROS production. Connecting persistent quantum effects to cellular behaviors bridge the atomic and cellular levels. The project pursues research that challenges fundamental assumptions about educational and research approaches and aims to achieve a paradigm shift beyond multidisciplinary approaches in the way the next generation of students are educated and introduced to quantum research. Researchers and students will develop necessary skills to accelerate and integrate new knowledge to converge research at the emerging frontier of Quantum Biology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to connect broad spatio-temporal scales, from rapid dynamics at the molecular level to gradual ROS production at the macromolecular level. The project also focuses on a novel Quantum Biology area in cell redox biology: the activation of molecular oxygen by reduced flavoenzymes, where the production of reactive oxygen species can be described by manifestly quantum phenomena. Also included in this research is the development of the mathematical foundation of quantum optimal control with the ultimate goal of proving optimality condition in the form of Pontryagin’s maximum principle. This project is supported by the Molecular Biophysics cluster of the Molecular and Cellular Biosciences Division in the Directorate for Biological Sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051510</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Martino</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlos F Martino</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Carlos.Martino@jhuapl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000671093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University APL]]></Name>
<CityName>Laurel</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207236099</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11100 Johns Hopkins Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1" style="text-align: justify;"><span style="font-size: 12.0pt;">We studied<span style="background: white;"> quantum effects on biochemical processes and biological function via theoretical, computational, and experimental analysis. We applied mathematical theory of optimal control to understand fundamental mechanisms connecting atomic and sub-cellular levels in quantum biological systems. New optimality condition was proved and an effective computational algorithm for the identification of optimal values of external electromagnetic field and internal hyperfine parameter was developed.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>The method is based on Pontryagin optimization, sensitivity analysis and Tikhonov regularization in the quantum-mechanical context. </span>Numerical results demonstrated that the quantum yield of the radical pair system can be significantly reduced if optimization is pursued simultaneously for external magnetic field and internal hyperfine parameters. The results reveal direct connection between quantum optimization and quantum coherence for the simplified radical-pair system. </span></p> <p class="p1" style="text-align: justify;"><span style="font-size: 12.0pt;">The major outcome of the modeling work is a better understanding of interactions between oxygen and human electron transfer flavoprotein (ETF), which has impacts ranging across signaling and oxidative stress phenomena. We have built on prior literature work and used molecular dynamics simulations to identify new locations in ETF most likely to bind oxygen species. These results also suggest potential mechanisms for radical pair formation that may underlie quantum biological phenomena in related flavin-containing proteins.</span><span style="font-size: 12.0pt;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1" style="text-align: justify;"><span style="font-size: 12.0pt;">The major finding of our biochemical characterization work is the demonstration that reactive oxygen species levels vary slightly when the ETF reaction is exposed to different strength magnetic fields. In these experiments, ETF is reacted in the presence of oxygen, medium chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase (MCAD), and MCAD substrate to generate an <em>in vitro </em>electron transfer chain terminating in the reduction of oxygen. Our results show that peroxide levels increase slightly when exposed to magnetic fields significantly above terrestrial magnetic field levels.</span><span style="font-size: 12.0pt;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Carlos&nbsp;F&nbsp;Martino</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  We studied quantum effects on biochemical processes and biological function via theoretical, computational, and experimental analysis. We applied mathematical theory of optimal control to understand fundamental mechanisms connecting atomic and sub-cellular levels in quantum biological systems. New optimality condition was proved and an effective computational algorithm for the identification of optimal values of external electromagnetic field and internal hyperfine parameter was developed.  The method is based on Pontryagin optimization, sensitivity analysis and Tikhonov regularization in the quantum-mechanical context. Numerical results demonstrated that the quantum yield of the radical pair system can be significantly reduced if optimization is pursued simultaneously for external magnetic field and internal hyperfine parameters. The results reveal direct connection between quantum optimization and quantum coherence for the simplified radical-pair system.  The major outcome of the modeling work is a better understanding of interactions between oxygen and human electron transfer flavoprotein (ETF), which has impacts ranging across signaling and oxidative stress phenomena. We have built on prior literature work and used molecular dynamics simulations to identify new locations in ETF most likely to bind oxygen species. These results also suggest potential mechanisms for radical pair formation that may underlie quantum biological phenomena in related flavin-containing proteins.  The major finding of our biochemical characterization work is the demonstration that reactive oxygen species levels vary slightly when the ETF reaction is exposed to different strength magnetic fields. In these experiments, ETF is reacted in the presence of oxygen, medium chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase (MCAD), and MCAD substrate to generate an in vitro electron transfer chain terminating in the reduction of oxygen. Our results show that peroxide levels increase slightly when exposed to magnetic fields significantly above terrestrial magnetic field levels.           Last Modified: 02/22/2022       Submitted by: Carlos F Martino]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
