<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Controlled Application of Shock Waves to Extinguish Wildfires]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this SBIR Phase I project is the potential to apply novel shock wave technology to wildfires in a way that can directly save lives, protect property and infrastructure, significantly reduce fine particulate air pollution, and prevent the permanent devastation of fragile ecosystems that can no longer fully recover from the large and intense wildfires that are increasingly commonplace in the American West. Current technologies for responding to large wildfires do not typically achieve direct extinguishment and are rather aimed at the gradual guidance and containment of fires - in the era of regular megafires (greater than 100,000 acres), methods such as aerial drops are rarely effective despite their enormous expense. As populations have further expanded into the urban-wildland interface, environmental change has produced extended droughts and weakened forests, and fuel loads have accumulated for far longer than would be natural, fire seasons now approach perennial levels. As a result, Federal annual spending on emergency suppression now regularly reaches $2B to $3B, up from an average of less than $1B at the end of the 20th century, and the holistic economic impact of a bad fire season may cost the broader economy an order of magnitude more in lost Gross Domestic Product.  The proposed project implements a cost-effective, rapid-response shock wave technology to extinguish large fire fronts. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project involves technical innovation in the novel application of controlled, directed shock waves to uncontrolled wildfire-scale flames fueled by organic material, with the goal of achieving rapid extinguishment. Characterization of turbulent flame and debris field response to a multitude of variables which are important for field deployment will result from testing with a physical prototype device – this device features novel mechanisms for the safe, repeated delivery of tunable shock waves. The unique data generated will in turn enable the optimization and refinement of a portable product that can eventually proceed to industrial application with firefighting agencies. The project work comprises detailed design, fabrication, and experimental testing of the shock-generating device at appropriate scale using high speed videography with density-based visualization. This will be combined with high-frequency pressure and temperature sensing, to demonstrate the effectiveness of the technique and further improve understanding of the underlying fluid and fire dynamics as the shock wave interactions occur.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051780</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Sutton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William R Sutton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[will@rebelresearch.xyz]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/15/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Graham</FirstName>
<LastName>Doig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Graham C Doig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[graham@seaflight.tech]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828854</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/15/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rebel Research LLC</Name>
<CityName>RANCHO PALOS VERDES</CityName>
<ZipCode>902751722</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8055393355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>26326 BIRCHFIELD AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CRANHWLM8LA7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REBEL RESEARCH LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rebel Research]]></Name>
<CityName>RCH PALOS VRD</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>902751722</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[26326 BIRCHFIELD AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>SBIR Phase I: Controlled Application of Shock Waves to Extinguish Wildfires</p> <p>Project Outcomes Report</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Wildfires are becoming more costly, more deadly, and more destructive, yet there is currently no technique available to firefighters to suppress a large uncontrolled wildfire by directly extinguishing flames.&nbsp;NSF SBIR Phase I grant funding supported Rebel Research's goal of developing and starting to commercialize a novel shockwave-based approach to large-scale wildfire fighting that has transformative potential to address uncontrolled blazes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project team set out to answer the questions: what is a realistic "fire volume" or ground area that can be treated with shockwaves and associated flow features? What are the most effective combinations of test variables - and in what scenarios might this not work at all?&nbsp;How expensive would this technique be in actual practice, and therefore how does this compare to costs and rates that firefighting agencies currently experience? And, what is required for acceptance by firefighters that would lead to initial field trials of the technology?&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Following customer discovery with firefighters across agencies and in different parts of the world, the shockwave approach was applied to real trees at a scale representative of a typical wildfire flank where firefighters may work in active proximity to the fire (flame heights from 5 to 25ft). The scientific R&amp;D in this phase built on prior academic work on extinguishing flames with shockwaves conducted by the original project PI, Dr. Graham Doig. Two related test campaigns were conducted featuring dozens of different setups with regards to tree type, tree size, tree condition, proximity of the test apparatus to trees or ground fuel, and then a variety of parameters relating to the strength and character of the shockwaves produced. The testing was conducted in New Mexico in realistic wind conditions. A combination of high-speed video and a variety of other property measurements were used to establish the interplay between the variables and determine under what circumstances the flames were likely to be extinguished permanently, and in which cases there would likely be partial extinguishment or re-ignition. The result was a large and unique dataset that elucidates when and how the technique can be effective.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="paragraph">The key high-level conclusions that can be drawn from the research conducted in Phase 1 of this grant were: 1) Controlled application of fluid dynamic features caused by controlled blasts directed at trees on fire can, in the right circumstances, be an effective extinguishing mechanism, removing flames in the treatment zone inside a fraction of a second.&nbsp;2) The efficacy of the technique is significantly affected by local conditions, fuel conditions, as well as the properties and behavior of the flow features being generated - dynamic optimization for different scenarios is necessary. 3) Challenges relating to safety and portability remain in being able to deploy this in the field. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p class="paragraph">&nbsp;</p> <p class="paragraph">The accelerated growth of US Federal wildfire suppression direct costs -exceeding $3bn for the first time in 2018 - now routinely consumes at least half the US Forest Service's total budget, reducing its ability to undertake prescribed burning/fuel reduction, introduce other new technology or conduct mitigation research. The economic costs of so-called megafires now extend an order or two of magnitude higher; for instance, the holistic impact of the 2018 California fire season was estimated to top $148bn, or 0.7% us US GDP. In Australia's catastrophic 2019-2020 season, over 0.7 metric gigatons of C02 were released -more than emissions from all other sectors combined. Taken to formal commercialization following this initial de-risking phase, Rebel Research's shockwave technology could enable meaningful progress in being able to bring the most destructive fires under formal control, providing a waterless, cost-effective method which can free up personnel to defend life and property elsewhere.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/25/2022<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;R&nbsp;Sutton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SBIR Phase I: Controlled Application of Shock Waves to Extinguish Wildfires  Project Outcomes Report     Wildfires are becoming more costly, more deadly, and more destructive, yet there is currently no technique available to firefighters to suppress a large uncontrolled wildfire by directly extinguishing flames. NSF SBIR Phase I grant funding supported Rebel Research's goal of developing and starting to commercialize a novel shockwave-based approach to large-scale wildfire fighting that has transformative potential to address uncontrolled blazes.      The project team set out to answer the questions: what is a realistic "fire volume" or ground area that can be treated with shockwaves and associated flow features? What are the most effective combinations of test variables - and in what scenarios might this not work at all? How expensive would this technique be in actual practice, and therefore how does this compare to costs and rates that firefighting agencies currently experience? And, what is required for acceptance by firefighters that would lead to initial field trials of the technology?      Following customer discovery with firefighters across agencies and in different parts of the world, the shockwave approach was applied to real trees at a scale representative of a typical wildfire flank where firefighters may work in active proximity to the fire (flame heights from 5 to 25ft). The scientific R&amp;D in this phase built on prior academic work on extinguishing flames with shockwaves conducted by the original project PI, Dr. Graham Doig. Two related test campaigns were conducted featuring dozens of different setups with regards to tree type, tree size, tree condition, proximity of the test apparatus to trees or ground fuel, and then a variety of parameters relating to the strength and character of the shockwaves produced. The testing was conducted in New Mexico in realistic wind conditions. A combination of high-speed video and a variety of other property measurements were used to establish the interplay between the variables and determine under what circumstances the flames were likely to be extinguished permanently, and in which cases there would likely be partial extinguishment or re-ignition. The result was a large and unique dataset that elucidates when and how the technique can be effective.     The key high-level conclusions that can be drawn from the research conducted in Phase 1 of this grant were: 1) Controlled application of fluid dynamic features caused by controlled blasts directed at trees on fire can, in the right circumstances, be an effective extinguishing mechanism, removing flames in the treatment zone inside a fraction of a second. 2) The efficacy of the technique is significantly affected by local conditions, fuel conditions, as well as the properties and behavior of the flow features being generated - dynamic optimization for different scenarios is necessary. 3) Challenges relating to safety and portability remain in being able to deploy this in the field.      The accelerated growth of US Federal wildfire suppression direct costs -exceeding $3bn for the first time in 2018 - now routinely consumes at least half the US Forest Service's total budget, reducing its ability to undertake prescribed burning/fuel reduction, introduce other new technology or conduct mitigation research. The economic costs of so-called megafires now extend an order or two of magnitude higher; for instance, the holistic impact of the 2018 California fire season was estimated to top $148bn, or 0.7% us US GDP. In Australia's catastrophic 2019-2020 season, over 0.7 metric gigatons of C02 were released -more than emissions from all other sectors combined. Taken to formal commercialization following this initial de-risking phase, Rebel Research's shockwave technology could enable meaningful progress in being able to bring the most destructive fires under formal control, providing a waterless, cost-effective method which can free up personnel to defend life and property elsewhere.          Last Modified: 10/25/2022       Submitted by: William R Sutton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
