<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Soil-derived mycobacteria for the treatment of posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and other anxiety disorders]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of novel therapeutics for the treatment of mental health disorders, specifically, posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD). While PTSD is most commonly associated with military personnel, it is estimated that roughly 7-8% of Americans will suffer from PTSD at some point in their lives resulting from everyday trauma, such as car accidents and sexual trauma. Further, it is anticipated there will be dramatic increases in the incidence of PTSD as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic. The proposed therapeutics would be most effective as part of an integrative approach to treating PTSD. The proposed innovation is also a fit for the burgeoning complementary and alternative medicine industry. This industry supplements the health needs of roughly 36% of Americans and is estimated to reach $296 billion in global revenues by 2027.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development and testing of novel strains of mycobacteria that may be incorporated into nutraceuticals for public consumption. Mycobacteria have been shown to reduce inflammation and modify the immune system of the brain. These characteristics of mycobacteria have important implications for mental health. Specifically, it has been shown that administration of heat-killed mycobacteria prior to stress enhances stress resilience and prevents stress-induced exaggeration of inflammation, spontaneous colitis, and anxiety in animal models. These effects specifically address two of the main symptoms of PTSD: avoidance and alterations in excitation or reactivity. These symptoms are associated with well-known behaviors in individuals with PTSD, such as irritability, sleep problems, difficulty concentrating, and avoiding experiences associated with trauma.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051920</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Lowry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher A Lowry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[christopher.lowry@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000502608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 MARINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine St Rm 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our project grew out of foundational research on the effects of beneficial soil-derived bacteria on stress and stress resilience. Through the life of this project, we focused on identification of target markets and value propositions, in addition to prototype development, of our lead strain of mycobacteria. To accomplish this goal, we conducted over 130 customer interviews during our NSF I-Corps cohort and subsequent conference attendance. Through these activities, we identified our target customer as multi-national probiotics developers, manufacturers, and distributors. We learned about the overall ecosystem of the probiotics industry, and how these developers supply the raw materials to formulators that market and sell the probiotics many of us are familiar with. The big players in this space are companies like Chr Hansen, International Flavors and Fragrances, DSM, Kaneka, and Novozymes, and it is a multi-billion dollar industry. Through our discussions with decision makers at these companies, we identified the need for new and novel strains that can address a growing demand for products in the mental wellness, cognitive health, and stress resilience space. Furthermore, we learned of the competitive advantage that science-backed, proprietary ingredients have over the more commoditized generic strains. Discerning consumers and formulators value rigorously validated products and favor them even at higher price points. In addition to these discussions, we were successful in developing a lead strain that we are currently finalizing a provision patent filing on. We have learned of next steps required for commercialization and are actively pursuing funding for future clinical testing of this strain. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>However, in addition to the strong business case, we spoke with many end users of probiotics and practitioners that prescribe them to better understand why they take them. Many of these people suffered from chronic issues that did not fully resolve with the use of traditional medicine. They sought alternative therapies that could assist in addressing the underlying causes of the dysfunction that they were experiencing. Our entire company was founded on the premise that losing touch with beneficial bacteria in an increasingly industrialized and urbanized world is a contributing factor to a variety of health issues and that Western medicine is not able to completely address them. It is our hope that through our work, we will be able to bring to market a product that can be used in as a complementary therapy to improve overall mental health and well-being. This is the mission of our company and the most significant broader impact we can have.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2023<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;A&nbsp;Lowry</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our project grew out of foundational research on the effects of beneficial soil-derived bacteria on stress and stress resilience. Through the life of this project, we focused on identification of target markets and value propositions, in addition to prototype development, of our lead strain of mycobacteria. To accomplish this goal, we conducted over 130 customer interviews during our NSF I-Corps cohort and subsequent conference attendance. Through these activities, we identified our target customer as multi-national probiotics developers, manufacturers, and distributors. We learned about the overall ecosystem of the probiotics industry, and how these developers supply the raw materials to formulators that market and sell the probiotics many of us are familiar with. The big players in this space are companies like Chr Hansen, International Flavors and Fragrances, DSM, Kaneka, and Novozymes, and it is a multi-billion dollar industry. Through our discussions with decision makers at these companies, we identified the need for new and novel strains that can address a growing demand for products in the mental wellness, cognitive health, and stress resilience space. Furthermore, we learned of the competitive advantage that science-backed, proprietary ingredients have over the more commoditized generic strains. Discerning consumers and formulators value rigorously validated products and favor them even at higher price points. In addition to these discussions, we were successful in developing a lead strain that we are currently finalizing a provision patent filing on. We have learned of next steps required for commercialization and are actively pursuing funding for future clinical testing of this strain.        However, in addition to the strong business case, we spoke with many end users of probiotics and practitioners that prescribe them to better understand why they take them. Many of these people suffered from chronic issues that did not fully resolve with the use of traditional medicine. They sought alternative therapies that could assist in addressing the underlying causes of the dysfunction that they were experiencing. Our entire company was founded on the premise that losing touch with beneficial bacteria in an increasingly industrialized and urbanized world is a contributing factor to a variety of health issues and that Western medicine is not able to completely address them. It is our hope that through our work, we will be able to bring to market a product that can be used in as a complementary therapy to improve overall mental health and well-being. This is the mission of our company and the most significant broader impact we can have.       Last Modified: 08/08/2023       Submitted by: Christopher A Lowry]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
