<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Phage-amplified Identification and Antimicrobial Susceptibility Test]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be the development of new diagnostic tools that allow rapid, direct-from-specimen bloodstream infection testing in clinical settings. The new technological innovations proposed here will more quickly identify bacteria responsible for the vast majority of blood infections while providing vital phenotypic data on antibiotics and dosages effective for treating these infections. This will improve patient outcomes through faster diagnosis and more precise antibiotic selection while also helping to combat the growing incidence of multidrug-resistant infections by reducing broad prescription of these drugs, which is critical to efforts to preserve the usefulness of existing antibiotics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop a new tests for direct-from-specimen identification (ID), antimicrobial susceptibility testing (AST) and minimum inhibitory drug concentration (MIC) determination against Escherichia coli in blood. A significant limitation with existing standards-of-care is time required for actionable results; current approaches require 18-72 hrs. Due to the time required, physicians must make empiric antimicrobial therapy decisions that often lead to negative patient outcomes. Genotypic approaches are limited because of the varied mechanisms utilized by bacteria to evolve resistance, which can lead to false-negative results. Mass spectrometry requires colony isolation and provides ID only. Other time-consuming tests are then required for AST and MIC. Rapid phenotypic approaches are needed. To solve these problems, bacteriophage mixtures will be used that are highly specific and have demonstrated overlapping host ranges from component phages, produce a measurable signal quickly, and are well-suited to a simple automatable 96-well plate immunoassay.  Project objectives of are to: 1) develop a rapid ID and AST/MIC immunoassay using phage-specific antibodies, and 2) prove feasibility of direct-from-specimen testing in blood samples. Side-by-side comparison to the current standard-of-care diagnostic strategies will also be performed. Anticipated results include ID, AST, and quantitative MIC in less than 5 hours directly in blood.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Cox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Cox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[crcoxcc@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803858</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>COBIO DIAGNOSTICS INC.</Name>
<CityName>AURORA</CityName>
<ZipCode>800457335</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3038860206</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>12635 E MONTVIEW BLVD RM 219</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DNNKH7TPCUG3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COBIO DIAGNOSTICS INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[COBIO DIAGNOSTICS INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Aurora</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>800457335</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12635 E Montview Blvd Suite 325]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes to date.</strong></p> <p>There is a significant demand in U.S. as well as international clinical laboratories for phenotypic, direct-from-specimen bacterial diagnostic assays capable of same-day testing for identifying the causative agent of infection and determining antimicrobial susceptibility (AST) and minimum inhibitory therapeutic concentrations (MIC). Most diagnostic technologies currently employed in hospitals and other clinical testing labs require 18-72 hours for ID and rely on secondary techniques to determine AST and MIC, often extending testing times even further.&nbsp;</p> <p>During its NSF Phase I research, Cobio Diagnostics, Inc has proven the feasibility of PhAAST-MIC (Phage-Amplified ID, AST and MIC) <em>ag</em>ainst <em>E. coli</em> bloodstream infections. PhAAST-MIC consists of 1) a mixture of species-specific <em>E. coli</em> phages with broad lytic capacity against isolates associated with human bloodstream infection, 2) a collection of highly specific anti-phage capture and reporter antibodies against these phages, and 3) a pair of 96-well plates for phage amplification and ELISA analysis. The first plate is a direct-from-specimen phage-amplification plate which is used to apply the phage cocktail directly in patient blood specimens in a nutrient bacterial growth medium. It includes a series of wells with and without the inclusion of antimicrobials approved for the treatment of Gram-negative septicemia. Each drug is serially diluted to determine AST and MIC at the same time in accordance with CLSI performance standards. The second plate is used for an ELISA assay on aliquots of the reactions obtained with the first plate. As designed, this pairing of exponential phage amplification with novel anti-phage capture and secondary reporter antibodies allows a combination of precision and speed to simultaneously ID <em>E. coli</em> directly in clinical blood specimens while determining antimicrobial susceptibility profile and MIC of antimicrobials in one test.</p> <p>Cobio successfully met all our stated objectives with prototypes that allowed ID, AST and MIC. Feasibility was demonstrated through detection of <em>E. coli</em> directly in blood specimens and in mock blood infections prepared with known clinical isolates including multidrug resistant septicemia-associated strains spiked in sterile donor blood at concentrations emulating human bloodstream bacterial loads typically experienced during human infection.&nbsp; Results were achieved in as little as 5 hr total testing time with eight carbapenem and &beta;-lactam antimicrobials commonly utilized to treat <em>E. coli</em> septicemia and for which high-level resistance is well-documented.</p> <p><strong>Conclusions of Phase I findings</strong></p> <p>This Phase I feasibility project met all intended milestones and exceeded the stated host range coverage of clinical MDR <em>E. coli</em>.&nbsp; The project also exceeded target assay sensitivity and testing time.&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>We sought at least 95% accuracy and achieved 96% against a diverse range of multidrug resistant extraintestinal <em>E. coli</em>.&nbsp;</li> <li>We sought an assay sensitivity of at least 1x10<sup>5</sup> bacteria/mL in 5 hrs or less and achieved 1x10<sup>2</sup> bacteria/mL in that timeframe.&nbsp;</li> <li>Further, the platform, when allowed to enrich bacteria in patient blood 1-2 hrs prior to phage amplification, was shown to be capable of detection of 10 organisms or less in 6-7 hrs.&nbsp; This even lower limit of detection, while requiring slightly longer, was still capable of delivering actionable diagnostic results to the clinician within the same day.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>The knowledge gained in this Phase I project strongly suggests that this same approach for assay design, prototyping/validation and antibody production can now be effectively applied to expand the assay to other multidrug resistant bacterial pathogens associated with human infections.</p> <p>This new approach has the potential to provide physicians and testing labs with a user-friendly multiplexed ELISA that uses common reagents and a common absorbance plate reader that clinical laboratory personnel are familiar with and that can be easily implemented in current diagnostic workflows.&nbsp; These new capabilities, when commercialized, will improve patient outcomes, contribute to better antimicrobial stewardship and ultimately save lives in the face of increasingly common multidrug resistant bacterial infections.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Cox</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes to date.  There is a significant demand in U.S. as well as international clinical laboratories for phenotypic, direct-from-specimen bacterial diagnostic assays capable of same-day testing for identifying the causative agent of infection and determining antimicrobial susceptibility (AST) and minimum inhibitory therapeutic concentrations (MIC). Most diagnostic technologies currently employed in hospitals and other clinical testing labs require 18-72 hours for ID and rely on secondary techniques to determine AST and MIC, often extending testing times even further.   During its NSF Phase I research, Cobio Diagnostics, Inc has proven the feasibility of PhAAST-MIC (Phage-Amplified ID, AST and MIC) against E. coli bloodstream infections. PhAAST-MIC consists of 1) a mixture of species-specific E. coli phages with broad lytic capacity against isolates associated with human bloodstream infection, 2) a collection of highly specific anti-phage capture and reporter antibodies against these phages, and 3) a pair of 96-well plates for phage amplification and ELISA analysis. The first plate is a direct-from-specimen phage-amplification plate which is used to apply the phage cocktail directly in patient blood specimens in a nutrient bacterial growth medium. It includes a series of wells with and without the inclusion of antimicrobials approved for the treatment of Gram-negative septicemia. Each drug is serially diluted to determine AST and MIC at the same time in accordance with CLSI performance standards. The second plate is used for an ELISA assay on aliquots of the reactions obtained with the first plate. As designed, this pairing of exponential phage amplification with novel anti-phage capture and secondary reporter antibodies allows a combination of precision and speed to simultaneously ID E. coli directly in clinical blood specimens while determining antimicrobial susceptibility profile and MIC of antimicrobials in one test.  Cobio successfully met all our stated objectives with prototypes that allowed ID, AST and MIC. Feasibility was demonstrated through detection of E. coli directly in blood specimens and in mock blood infections prepared with known clinical isolates including multidrug resistant septicemia-associated strains spiked in sterile donor blood at concentrations emulating human bloodstream bacterial loads typically experienced during human infection.  Results were achieved in as little as 5 hr total testing time with eight carbapenem and &beta;-lactam antimicrobials commonly utilized to treat E. coli septicemia and for which high-level resistance is well-documented.  Conclusions of Phase I findings  This Phase I feasibility project met all intended milestones and exceeded the stated host range coverage of clinical MDR E. coli.  The project also exceeded target assay sensitivity and testing time.   We sought at least 95% accuracy and achieved 96% against a diverse range of multidrug resistant extraintestinal E. coli.  We sought an assay sensitivity of at least 1x105 bacteria/mL in 5 hrs or less and achieved 1x102 bacteria/mL in that timeframe.  Further, the platform, when allowed to enrich bacteria in patient blood 1-2 hrs prior to phage amplification, was shown to be capable of detection of 10 organisms or less in 6-7 hrs.  This even lower limit of detection, while requiring slightly longer, was still capable of delivering actionable diagnostic results to the clinician within the same day.    The knowledge gained in this Phase I project strongly suggests that this same approach for assay design, prototyping/validation and antibody production can now be effectively applied to expand the assay to other multidrug resistant bacterial pathogens associated with human infections.  This new approach has the potential to provide physicians and testing labs with a user-friendly multiplexed ELISA that uses common reagents and a common absorbance plate reader that clinical laboratory personnel are familiar with and that can be easily implemented in current diagnostic workflows.  These new capabilities, when commercialized, will improve patient outcomes, contribute to better antimicrobial stewardship and ultimately save lives in the face of increasingly common multidrug resistant bacterial infections.          Last Modified: 07/14/2023       Submitted by: Christopher Cox]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
