<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Rapid and Sensitive Quantification of Phenylalanine within Test Strip]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project addresses an urgent need for a rapid and convenient method to monitor blood phenylalanine levels for patients with phenylketonuria, or PKU for short. Patients with PKU are unable to catabolize phenylalanine and therefore have elevated, toxic levels. These patients are treated with a severely protein-restricted diet and other potential medications. Since excess phenylalanine results in neurologic injury, and inadequate phenylalanine results in protein malnutrition, the diet of patients must be carefully balanced. This balance can only be accomplished by tracking blood phenylalanine levels, which fluctuate throughout the day. Currently the turnaround time of laboratory tests is 5 to 7 days, and sometimes longer, during which patients may experience prolonged episodes of behavioral and neurocognitive morbidities. PKU is a lifelong genetic disorder and requires constant tuning of diet therapy. The annual societal cost for taking care of patients with PKU can range from $15,000 to $200,000; this disease causes irreversible damage and high costs of care when improperly managed. The proposed project will develop a new monitor for these patients to prevent long-term effects. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop a new rapid, phenylalanine monitor for patients with phenylketonuria. Rapid quantification of blood phenylalanine levels to improve patient outcomes.  The device will also be a cost effective alternative to the standard of care as it is today. This device consists of a test strip and a test device. The test strip accepts a blood drop from a finger prick. The test strip contains various chemistries that condition the blood sample prior to optically analysis by the test device. The test device implements spectroscopy to interrogate the test strip as it determines phenylalanine quantity. The focus of this project is to optimize the product design and system algorithm. The proposed work enables cost-effective manufacturing and deployment of the device to the end user; the end goal of this project is to develop a simple prototype.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051803</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louay</FirstName>
<LastName>Fakhro</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louay K Fakhro</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[louayfakhro@omaroon.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000787136</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FAKHRO, LOUAY K</Name>
<CityName>MISSION VIEJO</CityName>
<ZipCode>926916111</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9495342684</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>27061 MALLORCA LN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>40</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA40</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VYR3MARJVCS8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FAKHRO LOUAY K</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FAKHRO, LOUAY K]]></Name>
<CityName>Mission Viejo</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926916111</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[27061 Mallorca]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>40</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA40</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of this phase I SBIR grant from NSF successfully enabled Omaroons first step to convert their benchtop test setup into a commercially viable form factor in their work towards creating a rapid blood phenylalanine level monitor for patients with rare disease Phenylketonuria (PKU). PKU is a lifelong condition, which if left untreated, causes serious health problems such as irreversible brain damage leading to intellectual and learning disabilities, behavioral problems, and seizures. Complications related to PKU can be avoided with strict diet control and frequent blood level monitoring.</p> <p>Our first commercial grade proof-of-concept test strip design will be put to the test to assess and rapidly quantify blood Phenylalanine levels in clinical samples of spiked and un-spiked blood samples during our clinical evaluation of the device. Our innovative monitoring technology will improve the quality of life for patients with rare disease Phenylketonuria (PKU) by allowing them same day access to their blood phenylaniline levels as opposed to waiting, at times, over two weeks when visiting blood draw clinics or submitting mail-in blotted blood sample filter paper before they can assess and calibrate their diet therapy regimen. The time delay is detrimental to their gold standard of care: diet therapy, and has been shown to negatively affect neurocognitive outcomes when monitoring becomes less frequent.</p> <p>This Phase I SBIR grant from NSF successfully supported advancing the PQS 1.0 by converting benchtop chemistry into a handheld commercially viable form factor. The latest PQS 1.0 units achieved an accuracy of 92%. The PQS 1.0 is well positioned and prepared for the commencement of clinical trials. The processes developed with this Phase 1 award, will be used to calibrate and ensure highest levels of quality in building additional test strips and the streamlined production level calibration of units. This Phase 1 award is instrumental to providing a new technology that has yet to be released to the market, thereby improving the quality of life for the people with life-long rare disease PKU.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/16/2023<br>      Modified by: Louay&nbsp;K&nbsp;Fakhro</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of this phase I SBIR grant from NSF successfully enabled Omaroons first step to convert their benchtop test setup into a commercially viable form factor in their work towards creating a rapid blood phenylalanine level monitor for patients with rare disease Phenylketonuria (PKU). PKU is a lifelong condition, which if left untreated, causes serious health problems such as irreversible brain damage leading to intellectual and learning disabilities, behavioral problems, and seizures. Complications related to PKU can be avoided with strict diet control and frequent blood level monitoring.  Our first commercial grade proof-of-concept test strip design will be put to the test to assess and rapidly quantify blood Phenylalanine levels in clinical samples of spiked and un-spiked blood samples during our clinical evaluation of the device. Our innovative monitoring technology will improve the quality of life for patients with rare disease Phenylketonuria (PKU) by allowing them same day access to their blood phenylaniline levels as opposed to waiting, at times, over two weeks when visiting blood draw clinics or submitting mail-in blotted blood sample filter paper before they can assess and calibrate their diet therapy regimen. The time delay is detrimental to their gold standard of care: diet therapy, and has been shown to negatively affect neurocognitive outcomes when monitoring becomes less frequent.  This Phase I SBIR grant from NSF successfully supported advancing the PQS 1.0 by converting benchtop chemistry into a handheld commercially viable form factor. The latest PQS 1.0 units achieved an accuracy of 92%. The PQS 1.0 is well positioned and prepared for the commencement of clinical trials. The processes developed with this Phase 1 award, will be used to calibrate and ensure highest levels of quality in building additional test strips and the streamlined production level calibration of units. This Phase 1 award is instrumental to providing a new technology that has yet to be released to the market, thereby improving the quality of life for the people with life-long rare disease PKU.          Last Modified: 01/16/2023       Submitted by: Louay K Fakhro]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
