<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  CANCER DIAGNOSTIC TOOL USING CANCER GENOMIC SIGNATURES TO DETERMINE CANCER TYPE]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255987.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275987</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a data analytic tool to predict and identify the organ of origin from early cancer screening blood tests. This will allow noninvasive detection of cancer at early stages, when it can be treated with potentially improved outcomes and in a less costly manner.  Second, a complementary application of the proposed  technology is to address an unmet need in identifying cancer organ of origin in metastatic cancers of unknown primary, where not knowing the organ of origin hampers designing an effective treatment plan in 30,000+ cases/yr in the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will accomplish internal development, and external validation of the proposed data analytic technology so it is ready to be validated on circulating tumor DNA data from blood, and can be used for metastatic tumors of unknown primary origin.  The proposed technology addresses the problem of the unknown primary by analyzing whole genome or large subsets using predictive tools. Different cancer (sub)types have different patterns or signatures of somatic single nucleotide variations in the cancer genome. A library of these signatures is built using a large number of whole genome data samples with a broad cross-section of known cancer (sub)types. The unknown cancer organ of origin of a new data sample is identified by comparing its somatic mutational patterns to the signatures in the library. A key research objective is to identify the minimum subset of whole genome required to determine the cancer organ of origin to facilitate its application in blood tests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2051900</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zurab</FirstName>
<LastName>Kakushadze</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zurab Kakushadze</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zura@quantigic.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000835142</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>VYNANCE TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</Name>
<CityName>SHERIDAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>828016317</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129641530</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>30 N GOULD ST, STE 26957</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LZ2AX8KARXD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VYNANCE TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[VYNANCE TECHNOLOGIES, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112293933</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2060 E 19TH ST Unit 3K]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~275987</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project comprises two parts. First, early cancer screening blood tests will allow noninvasive detection of cancer at early stages, when cancer can be treated with much better outcomes and more cost-efficiently. A viable blood test must diagnose that there is cancer, and also identify the cancer organ of origin. The proposed patented technology addresses this latter critical component of early cancer screening blood tests. Such blood tests aim to be administered at annual physical exams (~50M tests/yr in the U.S.) potentially saving millions of lives. Estimated cost-savings from early (stages I/II) vs. late (stages III/IV) cancer diagnosis are $26B/yr in the U.S., which is the market size for early cancer screening blood tests. An estimated cost-neutral price of such a test is $600. The expected per-test percentage attributable to the proposed patented technology is at least 3%, resulting in $900M/yr in revenues. Second, a complementary and immediate impact/application of the proposed patented technology is to address an unmet need in identifying the cancer organ of origin in metastatic cancers of unknown primary (CUPs), where not knowing the organ of origin hampers designing an effective treatment plan, which affects 100,000+ cases/yr in the U.S. when accounting for cases reported as CUPs, cases that should be reported as CUPs (but are not due to reporting idiosyncrasies), and cases with differential organ of origin diagnoses. A precedent-based price of such a test is around $4,000 or higher, resulting in $40M/yr in revenues at 10% market penetration. &nbsp;</p> <p>Several companies are developing early cancer screening blood tests, where the cancer organ of origin a priori is unknown. Knowing there is cancer without the organ of origin is insufficient and counterproductive. The proposed patented technology solves this problem by analyzing whole genome or its large subsets (as opposed to its small subsets such as gene panels or exome) using predictive proprietary tools adapted from quantitative trading. Thus, different cancer (sub)types have different patterns, or signatures, of somatic single nucleotide variations in the cancer genome. A library of these signatures is built using a large number of whole genome data samples with a broad cross-section of known cancer (sub)types. The unknown cancer organ of origin of a new data sample is identified by comparing its somatic mutational patterns to the signatures in the library. This methodology can be used to identify the cancer organ of origin in early cancer screening blood tests and CUPs.</p> <p>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project has successfully completed all its R&amp;D objectives, to wit: i) internal cross-validation of the proposed patented technology using ICGC (International Cancer Genome Consortium) and TCGA (The Cancer Genome Atlas) WGS (whole genome sequencing) data and ensuring the absence of batch effects in said cross-validation; ii) independent external validation of the internal validation results, by validating the software tools used for both downloading and processing ICGC and TCGA data as well as identifying the cancer organ of origin; iii) determining the (proprietary) smallest subset of whole genome for which cancer organ of origin can be identified with acceptable sensitivity; iv) receiving substantive feedback from FDA regarding a potential application of the proposed patented technology to CUPs. The internal and external validation results have demonstrated the viability of the proposed patented technology. Furthermore, extensive customer discovery in the NSF SBIR Beat-the-Odds Bootcamp and i-Corps programs, which included 160+ interviews with oncologists and other potential stakeholders such as insurance companies, sequencing companies, NCCN (National Comprehensive Cancer Network) and various others, has enabled to hone the (proprietary) product packaging and structure, value proposition, product-market fit, channels, etc., and position the proposed patented technology with respect to potential (strategic) partners and other potentially interested parties and stakeholders.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Zurab&nbsp;Kakushadze</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project comprises two parts. First, early cancer screening blood tests will allow noninvasive detection of cancer at early stages, when cancer can be treated with much better outcomes and more cost-efficiently. A viable blood test must diagnose that there is cancer, and also identify the cancer organ of origin. The proposed patented technology addresses this latter critical component of early cancer screening blood tests. Such blood tests aim to be administered at annual physical exams (~50M tests/yr in the U.S.) potentially saving millions of lives. Estimated cost-savings from early (stages I/II) vs. late (stages III/IV) cancer diagnosis are $26B/yr in the U.S., which is the market size for early cancer screening blood tests. An estimated cost-neutral price of such a test is $600. The expected per-test percentage attributable to the proposed patented technology is at least 3%, resulting in $900M/yr in revenues. Second, a complementary and immediate impact/application of the proposed patented technology is to address an unmet need in identifying the cancer organ of origin in metastatic cancers of unknown primary (CUPs), where not knowing the organ of origin hampers designing an effective treatment plan, which affects 100,000+ cases/yr in the U.S. when accounting for cases reported as CUPs, cases that should be reported as CUPs (but are not due to reporting idiosyncrasies), and cases with differential organ of origin diagnoses. A precedent-based price of such a test is around $4,000 or higher, resulting in $40M/yr in revenues at 10% market penetration.    Several companies are developing early cancer screening blood tests, where the cancer organ of origin a priori is unknown. Knowing there is cancer without the organ of origin is insufficient and counterproductive. The proposed patented technology solves this problem by analyzing whole genome or its large subsets (as opposed to its small subsets such as gene panels or exome) using predictive proprietary tools adapted from quantitative trading. Thus, different cancer (sub)types have different patterns, or signatures, of somatic single nucleotide variations in the cancer genome. A library of these signatures is built using a large number of whole genome data samples with a broad cross-section of known cancer (sub)types. The unknown cancer organ of origin of a new data sample is identified by comparing its somatic mutational patterns to the signatures in the library. This methodology can be used to identify the cancer organ of origin in early cancer screening blood tests and CUPs.  This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project has successfully completed all its R&amp;D objectives, to wit: i) internal cross-validation of the proposed patented technology using ICGC (International Cancer Genome Consortium) and TCGA (The Cancer Genome Atlas) WGS (whole genome sequencing) data and ensuring the absence of batch effects in said cross-validation; ii) independent external validation of the internal validation results, by validating the software tools used for both downloading and processing ICGC and TCGA data as well as identifying the cancer organ of origin; iii) determining the (proprietary) smallest subset of whole genome for which cancer organ of origin can be identified with acceptable sensitivity; iv) receiving substantive feedback from FDA regarding a potential application of the proposed patented technology to CUPs. The internal and external validation results have demonstrated the viability of the proposed patented technology. Furthermore, extensive customer discovery in the NSF SBIR Beat-the-Odds Bootcamp and i-Corps programs, which included 160+ interviews with oncologists and other potential stakeholders such as insurance companies, sequencing companies, NCCN (National Comprehensive Cancer Network) and various others, has enabled to hone the (proprietary) product packaging and structure, value proposition, product-market fit, channels, etc., and position the proposed patented technology with respect to potential (strategic) partners and other potentially interested parties and stakeholders.          Last Modified: 05/01/2022       Submitted by: Zurab Kakushadze]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
