<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[AGS-PRF: Resolving High-Resolution Paleoclimate Variability in Subarctic Canada across the Mid Pleistocene Transition and Interglacial Periods of the Last 1.5 Ma]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>190000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>190000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020108</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Verardo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dverardo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924695</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Speleothem-based paleoclimate reconstructions provide some of the highest-resolution terrestrial climate records. This proposal aims to characterize past interglacial Pleistocene climate variability in mid-continental, subarctic Canada using a rare collection of slow-growing subarctic speleothems. The researcher will combine a set of analytical tools to these speleothems including, novel geochronological techniques (U-Pb), micro-analytical technique (secondary ion mass spectrometry, SIMS), and imaging (confocal fluorescent laser microscopy, CFLM) to reconstruct high-latitude North American paleoclimate. These new records will investigate whether high-latitude climates were more or less variable during past interglacial periods that were even warmer than today, such as the warmest interglacial period of the last 800 ka.  The potential results of this project will include resolving broad records of temperature changes across different interglacial stages of the last 1.5 Million years, as well as providing snapshots of high-frequency (sub-annual to sub-decadal) hydroclimate variability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The potential Broader Impacts are twofold: (1) professional development of the postdoctoral fellow, and (2) community engagement. The postdoctoral researcher will gain first-hand experience in novel geochronology methods to date speleothems records in one of the only labs in the United States that is set up for U-Pb dating of speleothems. Additionally, the postdoctoral fellow will gain mentoring experience through direct work and interaction with undergraduate and graduate students. The research finding of this project will be shared with local communities in Northwest Territories (Canada) by setting up a two-way collaborative network that will, 1) Expose and engage students and staff at Aurora College (the only post-secondary institution within the Northwest Territories) about active climate research projects at Northwest Territory caves, and 2) Teach the postdoctoral fellow and project colleagues about the impact Arctic warming has on local indigenous communities. As part of these outreach efforts, educational and interactive display materials will be distributed to local municipalities, specifically Aurora College. One of the goals of this outreach plan will be to share what is learned from the people living in the communities of the Northwest Territories to climate scientists at Geoscience meetings (e.g. AGU) to better science communication initiatives and relay the broader societal impact of climate science research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2022</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052633</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cameron</FirstName>
<LastName>Batchelor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cameron J Batchelor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000836208</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Batchelor, Cameron J</Name>
<CityName>MIDDLETON</CityName>
<ZipCode>535624726</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Batchelor, Cameron J]]></Name>
<CityName>Middleton</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>535622756</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>Postdoctoral Fellowships</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1530</Code>
<Text>PALEOCLIMATE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~190000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
