<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A novel class of molecular vehicles for the targeted and precise integration of specified genetic information into the genomes of host cells and organisms]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to advance artificial integration of genetic information (genetic payloads) into the genomes of animal cells, microorganisms, and plants. A novel class of molecular vehicles (DNA donors) allows an unprecedented efficiency in delivering genetic payloads when combined with the established CRISPR (clustered short interspaced palindromic repeats) system for gene editing and genome engineering. The new payload delivery technology is expected to enable many emergent and innovative applications. This technology provides a safer alternative to the state-of-the-art method at lower cost. Non-therapeutic applications will enable the efficient generation of cell lines and transgenic animals. In plant biotechnology, the new DNA donors will allow complex genetic engineering with only one round of genome modification, improving crop yields and agricultural production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project provides a key innovation to the DNA donors that are used for transferring genetic payloads for targeted integration via CRISPR. Whereas CRISPR-mediated gene disruption (knock-out) is very efficient, integration of transfected DNA donors for targeted integration (knock-in) is generally limited. Existing commercial solutions are focused on small gene-sized payloads, but an innovative solution that enables the integration of larger payloads carrying several genes or entire genetic circuits is critically needed. The work in this proposal will demonstrate the broad applicability of the gene transfer and editing technology in a subset of therapeutically relevant cell types, such as stem cells and primary immune cells. The performance of the novel donor vehicles will be assessed by comparing their integration efficiency and precision of integration and cell toxicity to conventional DNA donor molecules and virus-based delivery systems. In addition, the project will demonstrate the ability to produce large quantities of the new DNA donors, thus greatly facilitating their application in cell therapies and dramatically reducing their overall cost.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052290</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bernhard</FirstName>
<LastName>Suter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bernhard Suter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bernhard.suter@stellatedna.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000603567</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>STELLATE DNA LLC</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021384555</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6163043788</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>625 MOUNT AUBURN ST STE 211</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VJFTN82ZM173</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>STELLATE DNA LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[STELLATE DNA LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Farmington</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>060321913</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Farmington Ave Ste 1702]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Stellate DNA's Phase I work established the technical and commercial feasibility of the <em>Stellate Gatalyst<sup>TM</sup></em> product, a proprietary form of circular single-stranded DNA that can be used as a DNA donor with CRISPR to <strong>(1)</strong> precisely repair DNA and <strong>(2)</strong> simultaneously minimize many of the known issues with DNA repair. These issues include cell toxicity (the act of repairing DNA can kill or damage the cell) and off-target effects (what happens when the DNA that will make the repair is not delivered to the correct location in the genome). Because of the therapeutic importance of developing methods to repair DNA --- in humans, other animals, and plants --- the field of genome integration technologies is very competitive.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The Phase I version of production is reproducible and scalable, which meant that we could do evaluation projects and start early sales. We found that the <em>Stellate Gatalyst<em><sup>TM</sup></em></em>&nbsp;cssDNA worked better than other current DNA donors under different types of conditions in multiple different cell lines, especially those that are important for commercial applications. Importantly, the <em>Stellate Gatalyst<sup>TM</sup></em>&nbsp;cssDNA works well with large payloads (long sequences of DNA) and does not use a viral vector for delivery. Those two features alone reduce the cost of DNA repair and can accelerate how quickly a particular repair can be designed and delivered. The broader impacts for this work are in healthcare applications and in agriculture. The <em>Stellate Gatalyst<sup>TM</sup></em>&nbsp;cssDNA technology can be used to treat human genetic diseases, and to provide farmers with more and better crop options at a time when rapid climate change threatens the US (and global) agricultural market.</p> <div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The achievements made in the Phase I project poise Stellate DNA for its follow-on Phase II application and for commercial success.</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Bernhard&nbsp;Suter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Stellate DNA's Phase I work established the technical and commercial feasibility of the Stellate GatalystTM product, a proprietary form of circular single-stranded DNA that can be used as a DNA donor with CRISPR to (1) precisely repair DNA and (2) simultaneously minimize many of the known issues with DNA repair. These issues include cell toxicity (the act of repairing DNA can kill or damage the cell) and off-target effects (what happens when the DNA that will make the repair is not delivered to the correct location in the genome). Because of the therapeutic importance of developing methods to repair DNA --- in humans, other animals, and plants --- the field of genome integration technologies is very competitive.    The Phase I version of production is reproducible and scalable, which meant that we could do evaluation projects and start early sales. We found that the Stellate GatalystTM cssDNA worked better than other current DNA donors under different types of conditions in multiple different cell lines, especially those that are important for commercial applications. Importantly, the Stellate GatalystTM cssDNA works well with large payloads (long sequences of DNA) and does not use a viral vector for delivery. Those two features alone reduce the cost of DNA repair and can accelerate how quickly a particular repair can be designed and delivered. The broader impacts for this work are in healthcare applications and in agriculture. The Stellate GatalystTM cssDNA technology can be used to treat human genetic diseases, and to provide farmers with more and better crop options at a time when rapid climate change threatens the US (and global) agricultural market.      The achievements made in the Phase I project poise Stellate DNA for its follow-on Phase II application and for commercial success.           Last Modified: 12/02/2022       Submitted by: Bernhard Suter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
