<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: In-situ forest ecosystem response to wildfire]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>56544.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>56544</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kendra McLauchlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmclauch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922217</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Wildfire is increasing in frequency and duration in Western US forests because of longer fire seasons, greater fuel load, prolonged drought, and intense heat waves. In 2020, wildfires burned  existing research forests in Oregon, USA, creating the opportunity to study how and why fire kills some trees but not others. This research will investigate and track the fate of forest trees that suffered varying degrees of burn severity, determine reasons for tree death and survival, and use the knowledge to determine the impact of wildfire on forest recovery in similar systems across the western US. Knowing how trees survive fire and drought is important for land owners and policy makers in developing management plans for alleviating forest stress and for reducing the risk and impact of wildfire. This project will provide training for  a postdoctoral researcher, and contribute to a broader understanding of how fire and forest structure affect carbon and water cycling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will provide critical knowledge about sensitivity of trees to varying fire severity, how traits of trees interacts with burn severity to impact survival, and how variability in tree mortality at the individual scale affects larger ecosystem processes, primarily net carbon balance.  This research will  quantify ecosystem response and recovery across a gradient of fire severity to answer this important research question: What are the immediate (weeks) and short-term (&lt;1 year) impacts of wildfire on forest ecosystem carbon stocks and fluxes, resilience, and mortality at tree, stand, and ecosystem levels? Post-fire data will be compared with the existing 20 years of continuous pre-fire data from the site, including eddy covariance, meteorology, subcanopy fluxes, automated soil respiration and sap flow on mature trees. Being able to characterize mechanisms for tree death and ecosystem recovery following fire is important for making predictions with process-based models of the impacts of fire at larger scales now and in the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052587</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beverly</FirstName>
<LastName>Law</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beverly E Law</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bev.law@oregonstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000263581</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>CORVALLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318655</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 SW JEFFERSON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MZ4DYXE1SL98</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7381</Code>
<Text>Ecosystem Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~56544</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Forests remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and store it in plant tissue and soils. This process of carbon uptake helps reduce greenhouse gases and climate warming. Forest carbon uptake and storage is affected by wildfire because trees can die or be injured. Wildfire is increasing in frequency and duration in the Western US forests because of longer growing seasons, fuels, drought, and heat waves caused by anthropogenic climate change. In 2020, wildfires burned through existing research forests in Oregon, USA creating the opportunity to study how and why fire kills some trees, how and why some trees survive, and how long it takes for the forest to recover. This research investigated and tracked the recovery of forest trees, determine reasons for tree death and survival, and used the knowledge to determine the impact of wildfire on forest recovery and resilience in similar systems across the Western US. Knowing how trees survive fire and drought is important for landowners and policy makers in developing management plans for alleviating forest stress and for reducing the risk and impact of wildfire and drought.</p> <p>Key outcomes of this work include significant advancement of knowledge about how conifers respond physiologically to fire. More than 90% of the trees within the burn perimeter were still alive a year after the fire, including individuals that were severely damaged by the fire (i.e., nearly all the tree needles were scorched or consumed). Most of our study trees exhibited considerable degrees of physiological activity and had visible evidence of new growth. Nearly all trees exhibited budburst by June 2021. Remarkably, we found that needle photosynthetic capacity (measured as the maximum velocity of carboxylation) increased with the severity of tree fire damage (R2 = 0.71, p = 0.02). Increasing photosynthetic capacity with tree damage suggests live needles on more severely burnt trees have an increased ability to fix carbon. This could be because of increased nitrogen uptake or nitrogen reallocation to surviving photosynthetic tissues, an area of future study. We also found that burned trees maintained higher leaf water potentials suggesting less water stress as the summer drought progressed.&nbsp;</p> <p>Another outcome was contribution of information to our modeling of future vulnerability to drought and fire in the western US (Law et al. 2021, Nature Comm. Earth &amp; Environ., https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-021-00326-0). The data backed up earlier findings on a fire in ponderosa pine, but the forest wasn?t logged post-fire (Irvine et al. 2007 Glob. Change Biol.). In that study, larger trees (&gt;20 cm) suffered only 34% mortality under moderate severity fire, and contributed 91% of post-fire NPP of the forest.</p> <p>Our most important broader impact was the production of a <em>documentary film called Elemental</em>, which was on wildfire and the science of biological recovery and management effects. The film was made at our AmeriFlux 90-year old ponderosa pine site that had been running for 20 years. The documentary began 5 years before the fire, and followed it through post-fire conditions and then a standard post-fire management action that scraped the soil surface and removed all trees, such that no N-fixing shrubs could resprout for wildlife, and no seed-fall could provide diversity of natural regeneration. This forest included remnant incense cedar and was an old forest with abundant wildlife. A majority of the trees survived the fire and did well post-fire, so they killed the survivors. The film was shown to policy-makers, and the sadness of how the land was abused changed the minds of policy-makers from supporting one-size-fits-all management to understanding how forests that experience mixed-severity fire, especially ponderosa pine forests, are best left to naturally regeneration and support wildlife through the recovery process by allowing the N-fixing shrubs to resprout and buffer high temperatures for seedling growth. The film is showing nation-wide and has won many film festival awards. It will be streaming in summer of 2023.</p> <p>Results from this work have been presented at several scientific conferences and to the general public at local chapter meetings of the Idaho Native Plant Society and California Rotary clubs, and to the <em>US House in Dr. Law?s invited testimony on wildfires</em><em>&nbsp;(available from the US House Subcommittee on National Parks, Forests &amp; Public Lands , Apr, 2021)</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/16/2023<br>      Modified by: Beverly&nbsp;E&nbsp;Law</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Forests remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and store it in plant tissue and soils. This process of carbon uptake helps reduce greenhouse gases and climate warming. Forest carbon uptake and storage is affected by wildfire because trees can die or be injured. Wildfire is increasing in frequency and duration in the Western US forests because of longer growing seasons, fuels, drought, and heat waves caused by anthropogenic climate change. In 2020, wildfires burned through existing research forests in Oregon, USA creating the opportunity to study how and why fire kills some trees, how and why some trees survive, and how long it takes for the forest to recover. This research investigated and tracked the recovery of forest trees, determine reasons for tree death and survival, and used the knowledge to determine the impact of wildfire on forest recovery and resilience in similar systems across the Western US. Knowing how trees survive fire and drought is important for landowners and policy makers in developing management plans for alleviating forest stress and for reducing the risk and impact of wildfire and drought.  Key outcomes of this work include significant advancement of knowledge about how conifers respond physiologically to fire. More than 90% of the trees within the burn perimeter were still alive a year after the fire, including individuals that were severely damaged by the fire (i.e., nearly all the tree needles were scorched or consumed). Most of our study trees exhibited considerable degrees of physiological activity and had visible evidence of new growth. Nearly all trees exhibited budburst by June 2021. Remarkably, we found that needle photosynthetic capacity (measured as the maximum velocity of carboxylation) increased with the severity of tree fire damage (R2 = 0.71, p = 0.02). Increasing photosynthetic capacity with tree damage suggests live needles on more severely burnt trees have an increased ability to fix carbon. This could be because of increased nitrogen uptake or nitrogen reallocation to surviving photosynthetic tissues, an area of future study. We also found that burned trees maintained higher leaf water potentials suggesting less water stress as the summer drought progressed.   Another outcome was contribution of information to our modeling of future vulnerability to drought and fire in the western US (Law et al. 2021, Nature Comm. Earth &amp; Environ., https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-021-00326-0). The data backed up earlier findings on a fire in ponderosa pine, but the forest wasn?t logged post-fire (Irvine et al. 2007 Glob. Change Biol.). In that study, larger trees (&gt;20 cm) suffered only 34% mortality under moderate severity fire, and contributed 91% of post-fire NPP of the forest.  Our most important broader impact was the production of a documentary film called Elemental, which was on wildfire and the science of biological recovery and management effects. The film was made at our AmeriFlux 90-year old ponderosa pine site that had been running for 20 years. The documentary began 5 years before the fire, and followed it through post-fire conditions and then a standard post-fire management action that scraped the soil surface and removed all trees, such that no N-fixing shrubs could resprout for wildlife, and no seed-fall could provide diversity of natural regeneration. This forest included remnant incense cedar and was an old forest with abundant wildlife. A majority of the trees survived the fire and did well post-fire, so they killed the survivors. The film was shown to policy-makers, and the sadness of how the land was abused changed the minds of policy-makers from supporting one-size-fits-all management to understanding how forests that experience mixed-severity fire, especially ponderosa pine forests, are best left to naturally regeneration and support wildlife through the recovery process by allowing the N-fixing shrubs to resprout and buffer high temperatures for seedling growth. The film is showing nation-wide and has won many film festival awards. It will be streaming in summer of 2023.  Results from this work have been presented at several scientific conferences and to the general public at local chapter meetings of the Idaho Native Plant Society and California Rotary clubs, and to the US House in Dr. Law?s invited testimony on wildfires (available from the US House Subcommittee on National Parks, Forests &amp; Public Lands , Apr, 2021).          Last Modified: 03/16/2023       Submitted by: Beverly E Law]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
