<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Physics (PHY) Rateless Codec Technology for Proximity Space Links]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project stems from developing a wireless communications technology based on physical (PHY) layer rateless codes.  If successfully demonstrated, these codes could provide high data rates with low computational costs, minimum latency, and enhanced energy efficiency, i.e., long battery life. The initial target of the technological innovation is the space communications market - both commercial and government space programs. Space communication systems are a critical and integral part of every space mission. This Phase I project focuses on an enabling technology addressing capability gaps that could provide cheaper and faster solutions for the data communication systems. Commercialization of the proposed technology is beneficial to the US economy and government since the development of innovative technologies for the space sector contributes to economic growth in the emerging space economy. The proposed next-generation wireless communications technology may also support a wide variety of applications and use cases in the terrestrial wireless market. These application areas include 5G Ultra Reliable Low Latency Communications (URLLC), Industrial Internet of Things (IoT) use cases, and unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) communications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is focused on developing a PHY rateless codes-based novel adaptive transmission technology for the reliable transmission of information bits between a wireless transmitter and receiver. PHY rateless codes have the innate ability to adapt both the code construction and the number of code bits for an as-needed transmission of code bits. The adaptive transmission technology in the PHY layer interacts with the automatic repeat request (ARQ) protocols in the data link layer (DLL) affecting its sequence of operations. The DLL designed for the traditional fixed-rate coding is a poor match for the PHY rateless system. A key goal of the proposed Phase I project is to design a simple and yet effective DLL for a proximity space link using PHY rateless codes which optimizes the throughput, establishing the technical feasibility. The Phase I project aims to add new design features to the PHY rateless encoder and decoder based on deep learning/auto encoder enhancements, structured permutations, and efficient algorithms/techniques for solving sparse linear systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/28/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/03/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052395</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amogh</FirstName>
<LastName>Rajanna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amogh Rajanna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Amogh.Rajanna@ieee.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836457</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TFWIRELESS INC.</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554101414</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6129994959</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3210 W 45TH STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U2E9BZ5W11N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TFWIRELESS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TFWIRELESS INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Burbank</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>915044015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1220 N 5 St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Technical Outcomes</span>:</p> <p>A key goal of the Phase I project is to demonstrate the technical feasibility of the&nbsp;Physical Layer (PHY) Rateless Codec Technology for Proximity Space Links. In the layered protocol stack of the satellite communication (SATCOM) standards, the PHY Layer Rateless Codec technology is positioned in the PHY layer. The technical study aimed at establishing the feasibility of supporting the novel PHY layer rateless codec technology within the layered protocol stack without major changes to the layers above the PHY layer. The technical risks of the novel SATCOM technology have been addressed.</p> <p>In the Phase I project, we compare the performance&nbsp;of the PHY Layer Rateless Codec technology with the most widely accepted and adopted SATCOM standard, i.e., the ETSI DVB-S2X from both throughput/spectral efficiency and&nbsp;costs perspective.&nbsp;The PHY&nbsp;Layer Rateless Codec communication system has similar throughput/ spectral efficiency performance and a lower energy/power consumption, i.e., SWaP-C relative to the DVB-S2X communication system due to lower computational costs, lower memory costs, lower feedback costs/resources associated with the baseband operations such as encoder, decoder, modulator, and demodulator.&nbsp;</p> <p>The novel PHY layer rateless codec technology was also compared to the Adaptive Data Rate (ADR) option of the CCSDS Proximity-1 standard to address the NASA market risks and shown to provide higher throughput/ spectral efficiency performance with lower SWaP-C.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Commercialization Outcomes</span>:</p> <p>The NSF Phase I award provided valuable technology entrepreneurship and leadership development opportunities for the PI. Participation in the NSF Beat-the-Odds boot camp and the NSF All SBIR National I-Corps program and the related customer discovery process played a big part in understanding the Satellite Communications (SATCOM) industry ecosystem and value chain differentiation.</p> <p>Based on the&nbsp;customer discovery process, new technology and business opportunities were identified such as the DIFI-compliant digital IF modem solutions market for the digital IF transformation of the SATCOM ground segment. The first testing ground for the novel PHY layer rateless codec technology can be the space communications system (satellite) and ground communications systems (gateways/terminals) of the PWSA - Proliferated Warfighter Space Architecture. PWSA is being developed by SDA along with Space Systems Command (SSC) within the US Space Force.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Amogh&nbsp;Rajanna</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539197302_Tech_Visual_GS--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539197302_Tech_Visual_GS--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ground Segment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539197302_Tech_Visual_GS--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ground Segment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ground Segment Infrastructure of SATCOM.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Amogh Rajanna</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Amogh&nbsp;Rajanna</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ground Segment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539088030_TwitterHeaderPhoto--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539088030_TwitterHeaderPhoto--rgov-800width.jpg" title="TFWireless Inc"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539088030_TwitterHeaderPhoto--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="TFWireless Inc"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Logo of the tech startup.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Amogh Rajanna</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Amogh&nbsp;Rajanna</div> <div class="imageTitle">TFWireless Inc</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539261222_TMS_Fig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539261222_TMS_Fig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="TMS"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052395/2052395_10773583_1677539261222_TMS_Fig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="TMS"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Technical Merit Summary</div> <div class="imageCredit">Amogh Rajanna</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Amogh&nbsp;Rajanna</div> <div class="imageTitle">TMS</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Technical Outcomes:  A key goal of the Phase I project is to demonstrate the technical feasibility of the Physical Layer (PHY) Rateless Codec Technology for Proximity Space Links. In the layered protocol stack of the satellite communication (SATCOM) standards, the PHY Layer Rateless Codec technology is positioned in the PHY layer. The technical study aimed at establishing the feasibility of supporting the novel PHY layer rateless codec technology within the layered protocol stack without major changes to the layers above the PHY layer. The technical risks of the novel SATCOM technology have been addressed.  In the Phase I project, we compare the performance of the PHY Layer Rateless Codec technology with the most widely accepted and adopted SATCOM standard, i.e., the ETSI DVB-S2X from both throughput/spectral efficiency and costs perspective. The PHY Layer Rateless Codec communication system has similar throughput/ spectral efficiency performance and a lower energy/power consumption, i.e., SWaP-C relative to the DVB-S2X communication system due to lower computational costs, lower memory costs, lower feedback costs/resources associated with the baseband operations such as encoder, decoder, modulator, and demodulator.   The novel PHY layer rateless codec technology was also compared to the Adaptive Data Rate (ADR) option of the CCSDS Proximity-1 standard to address the NASA market risks and shown to provide higher throughput/ spectral efficiency performance with lower SWaP-C.  Commercialization Outcomes:  The NSF Phase I award provided valuable technology entrepreneurship and leadership development opportunities for the PI. Participation in the NSF Beat-the-Odds boot camp and the NSF All SBIR National I-Corps program and the related customer discovery process played a big part in understanding the Satellite Communications (SATCOM) industry ecosystem and value chain differentiation.  Based on the customer discovery process, new technology and business opportunities were identified such as the DIFI-compliant digital IF modem solutions market for the digital IF transformation of the SATCOM ground segment. The first testing ground for the novel PHY layer rateless codec technology can be the space communications system (satellite) and ground communications systems (gateways/terminals) of the PWSA - Proliferated Warfighter Space Architecture. PWSA is being developed by SDA along with Space Systems Command (SSC) within the US Space Force.          Last Modified: 02/27/2023       Submitted by: Amogh Rajanna]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
