<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Ultra-Fast COVID-19 Sensor]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project include the deployment of a diagnostic sensor at the COVID-19 pandemic frontlines such as hospitals, clinical laboratories, authorized drive-in labs, airports, and public spaces like supermarkets, schools, and universities, work spaces.  The sensor will be used for ultra-fast (less than 1 minute) non-invasive screening of samples to ensure safety. The ultimate goal is a home-based test that minimizes the exposure and transmission of virus to clinical technicians and others at testing locations. This testing ability will identify and isolate carriers of the virus and thereby control the spread of virus. This technology is timely to counter COVID-19; However, it can be extended towards detecting other bacteria and viruses and has shown promise for detecting HIV as well. The versatility of the sensor will be investigated. In general, the innovation may lead to ensuring the healthcare of the population by monitoring the condition of individuals rapidly without causing discomfort. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project focuses on a new technology for COVID-19 diagnosis. The ultra-fast COVID-19 (UFC-19) detection sensor is a fast, portable, small size instrument that operates directly with saliva (it does not require special swabs or collection devices) for COVID-19 diagnosis with the ability to sense the presence/absence of the virus SARS-CoV-2 in a sample in less than 1 second.  The portability and the speed of results makes this sensor a potentially important diagnostic tool for fast initial screening of samples and continuous monitoring of an individual. The UFC-19 technology is based on the electron transfer reaction between the proteins present in the SARS-CoV-2 virus at the electrode/electrolyte interface. This innovation advances the current understanding of electrochemical sensors for point-of-care applications by utilizing multidisciplinary contributions from electrochemical engineering, virology, and physiology, among others. Through this I-Corps program, the team intends to learn about the proposed market to pave the path for commercializing the sensor.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052574</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerardine</FirstName>
<LastName>Botte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gerardine G Botte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gerri.botte@ttu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000256907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>LUBBOCK</CityName>
<ZipCode>79409</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2500 BROADWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EGLKRQ5JBCZ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>With the advent of Covid-19 pandemic, the necessity for rapid tests to swiftly screen and identify infected individuals became high. The high turnaround time for PCR based tests called for alternate tests that could return results almost instantly. To fulfil these requirements, Team EviroTECH participated in the NSF I-Corps program in January 2021. The goal of the team was to identify their market, customer segment and formulate a business plan to be a successful start up which sold devices for rapid Covid-19 diagnosis. Based on the foundation obtained from the I-Corps program, Team EviroTECH has accomplished the following outcomes in the past 2 years:</p> <ul> <li>Successfully conducted 102 interviews within 7 weeks to understand the market, customer segment, and develop a business plan.</li> <li>Understood what customers will be willing to pay for the product and what profit margin could be obtained for the company to be successful.</li> <li>Raised angel funds to expand the team and spin-off a company, EviroTECH LLC</li> <li>Hired a chief operating officer, a research and development engineer, and 2 interns.</li> <li>Partnered with a contract medical device manufacturer who was one of the groups the team interviewed during the I-Corps</li> <li>Obtained grant from DARPA ($500,000) to expand technology platform for air detection</li> <li>Submitted pre-application for FDA EUA</li> <li>US patent was granted. After a year, filed a follow up patent for air virus detection</li> <li>Invited to give presentation at Gordon Research Conference in June of 2023 (2023 Nonproliferation, Counterproliferation and Disarmament Science)</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Gerardine&nbsp;G&nbsp;Botte</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052574/2052574_10717884_1685655545365_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052574/2052574_10717884_1685655545365_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="EviroTech Covid-19 Testing Device"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052574/2052574_10717884_1685655545365_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="EviroTech Covid-19 Testing Device"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Covid-19 testing device with test kits, sample collection and test card</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gerri Botte</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gerardine&nbsp;G&nbsp;Botte</div> <div class="imageTitle">EviroTech Covid-19 Testing Device</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ With the advent of Covid-19 pandemic, the necessity for rapid tests to swiftly screen and identify infected individuals became high. The high turnaround time for PCR based tests called for alternate tests that could return results almost instantly. To fulfil these requirements, Team EviroTECH participated in the NSF I-Corps program in January 2021. The goal of the team was to identify their market, customer segment and formulate a business plan to be a successful start up which sold devices for rapid Covid-19 diagnosis. Based on the foundation obtained from the I-Corps program, Team EviroTECH has accomplished the following outcomes in the past 2 years:  Successfully conducted 102 interviews within 7 weeks to understand the market, customer segment, and develop a business plan. Understood what customers will be willing to pay for the product and what profit margin could be obtained for the company to be successful. Raised angel funds to expand the team and spin-off a company, EviroTECH LLC Hired a chief operating officer, a research and development engineer, and 2 interns. Partnered with a contract medical device manufacturer who was one of the groups the team interviewed during the I-Corps Obtained grant from DARPA ($500,000) to expand technology platform for air detection Submitted pre-application for FDA EUA US patent was granted. After a year, filed a follow up patent for air virus detection Invited to give presentation at Gordon Research Conference in June of 2023 (2023 Nonproliferation, Counterproliferation and Disarmament Science)        Last Modified: 06/01/2023       Submitted by: Gerardine G Botte]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
