<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Feasibility of Dynamic Configurable Liquid Molding]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/ commercial potential of this SBIR Phase I project is the creation of a new set of tools for bioscience applications. The innovation has shown promise in benchtop tests to fill a capability gap in manufacturing, and the project will build upon this promise to create 3-dimensional nanoscale fluid pathways. The first target application is to enable widespread use of nanometer-sized particles (30-150 nm) to carry cell signaling information throughout the body. Particles designed to signal a particular cellular response are a major component of drug therapeutics as their size allows them to access parts of the body otherwise impossible to reach, such as the blood-brain barrier in the event of a stroke and tumor penetration for cancer patients. Problematic for these research endeavors is the differentiating these particles from others due to similarity in size (100-300 nm). The innovation could enable these nanoscale entities to traverse nanoscale pathways, resulting in size and physics-based exclusion from other particles. Success in this project aids in promoting the advancement of detection and treatment for global health issues, adding to the general welfare of society, as well as creating a new sector in U.S. bioeconomy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Phase I assesses the feasibility of a potentially disruptive new manufacturing process to create a solid form structure with 3-dimensional pathways, such as helices and sine waves, of circular cross section interior channels for use in micro/nano-fluidics products. The innovation uses the physics of fluid flow to dynamically mold a fluid against a smart fluid, during which process the diameter of the channel being formed can be changed by adjusting the process variables in real-time. The work progresses the knowledge associated with advancing manufacturing capabilities and enables a wide variety of fields based on the products made using the method. For the former, the technology provides a new way to rapidly create fluidic pathways for nano to micro structures, enhancing the understanding of fluidic behaviors, polymerization, smart fluid applications, and creates a new field of study for the dynamic behavior of fluid/fluid molding. The technical goals of the Phase I work use a combination of fluidic modeling and the set-up and execution of a series of experimental tests to demonstrate active control of the channel diameter for 50-500 nm, 3-dimensional structures with controlled diameter channels, and merging and diverging channels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052113</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eleanor</FirstName>
<LastName>Derbyshire</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eleanor Derbyshire</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hawes@hummingbirdnano.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000635354</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hummingbird Nano, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>NICHOLASVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>403562162</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8595598735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JOHN C WATTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H569M257CNK7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HUMMINGBIRD NANO INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GLMCGTCJJ7H4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hummingbird Nano, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Nicholasville</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>403562162</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 John C, Watts Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>SBIR Phase I: Feasibility of Dynamic Liquid Configurable Molding sought to demonstrate the feasibility of a novel manufacturing method for the creation of three-dimensional micro- and nanofluidic pathways. The manufacturing method proved highly feasible and versatile. The pathways created during Phase I have circular cross-sections, can intersect and diverge, and can be configured in true three-dimensions. This manufacturing technique opens the door for the use of gravitational, lateral, and inertial forces acting upon flow at very small size scales. The results showed that the manufacturing process occurs at speeds comparable to injection molding, although the post-processing steps, including the addition of connectors, are not yet optimized&nbsp;and take longer. The process showed channel cross-sections as small as 200 nm, which was the limit of the<strong>&nbsp;</strong>optical detection capabilities at Hummingbird Nano, Inc. (HBN), and as large&nbsp;as 3 millimeters. The length of the channels is not limited for diameters of 3 microns and above, creating very high aspect ratios. The new manufacturing method has the potential to impact a wide variety of fields, including, but not limited to, significant advances in precision fluid dispensing, vascular models, precision detection, isolation of nanosized particles etc. Hummingbird Nano, Inc., is initially focused on supplying new laboratory tooling for advancing the life sciences. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Eleanor&nbsp;Derbyshire</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SBIR Phase I: Feasibility of Dynamic Liquid Configurable Molding sought to demonstrate the feasibility of a novel manufacturing method for the creation of three-dimensional micro- and nanofluidic pathways. The manufacturing method proved highly feasible and versatile. The pathways created during Phase I have circular cross-sections, can intersect and diverge, and can be configured in true three-dimensions. This manufacturing technique opens the door for the use of gravitational, lateral, and inertial forces acting upon flow at very small size scales. The results showed that the manufacturing process occurs at speeds comparable to injection molding, although the post-processing steps, including the addition of connectors, are not yet optimized and take longer. The process showed channel cross-sections as small as 200 nm, which was the limit of the optical detection capabilities at Hummingbird Nano, Inc. (HBN), and as large as 3 millimeters. The length of the channels is not limited for diameters of 3 microns and above, creating very high aspect ratios. The new manufacturing method has the potential to impact a wide variety of fields, including, but not limited to, significant advances in precision fluid dispensing, vascular models, precision detection, isolation of nanosized particles etc. Hummingbird Nano, Inc., is initially focused on supplying new laboratory tooling for advancing the life sciences.            Last Modified: 12/30/2021       Submitted by: Eleanor Derbyshire]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
