<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Transparent inorganic photoresists for high index photonics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will enable next-generation engineered optics employed in augmented and virtual reality (AVR) devices. Engineered optics manufacturers currently deposit polymeric thin films and imprint and cure them with transparent molds and UV light. Such polymeric films often have high costs and sub-optimal optical performance. Novel high-index materials are required for device miniaturization and increased field of view.  This project will provide AVR manufacturers with cost effective methods to fabricate high refractive index transparent photonic devices that would otherwise be impossible or cost prohibitive to manufacture by methods currently available.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will expand the knowledge base of high-index, UV-curable precursors that can be used for engineered optics.  UV-curable polymeric-nanoparticle composite materials represent the current state-of-the-art to produce optical waveguide components for augmented and virtual reality (AVR) applications. These coatings often suffer from low-optical transmission, increased haze values, high coefficients of thermal expansion, and low-indices of refraction. This project develops UV-curable, inorganic films that exceeds the standards of currently used materials. This research project will focus on elucidating correlations between precursor formulation and film processing to control film thickness, refractive index, and optical transmission.  The proposed research objectives will reproducibly demonstrate materials with controlled optical performance that that meets or exceeds the current state-of-the-art and establish a pathway for manufacturers to achieve device miniaturization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/10/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052401</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Omid</FirstName>
<LastName>Sadeghihosseinabadi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Omid Sadeghihosseinabadi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Omid.sadeghi.h@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818032</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PHOSIO CORPORATION</Name>
<CityName>CORVALLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>973304254</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5415130157</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1110 NE CIRCLE BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZNKXRL1PJS55</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PHOSIO CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZNKXRL1PJS55</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[PHOSIO CORPORATION]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973304254</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1110 NE Circle Blvd., ATAMI/Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-325df4fe-7fff-0d9b-6893-054921b6041e"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Besides many advantages that Augmented Reality (AR) devices offer, the users have a strong need for more efficacious and wearable AR headsets. Current headsets do not satisfy end-user expectations, as they are bulky and present a small field of view (FOV), low image quality, and short battery life.To improve the user&rsquo;s immersive experience and efficiency of the devices, AR manufacturers are seeking components fabricated with transparent, high refractive-index materials which is made of a glass substrate and high refractive index coating. Glass manufacturers have recently announced the availability of new, high-index glass substrates (n ~ 2.1) to meet the technical needs for next-generation devices but high-index, imprintable materials to match the index of the new glass substrates are currently unavailable in the market.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Phosio is developing UV-curable inorganic inks for imprinting and manufacturing high refractive-index coatings. The materials and fabrication methods are crucial for realizing the next generation of wearable devices in the AR market. During Phase I, we demonstrated the feasibility of new materials and methods to nano-pattern transparent, high refractive-index films via solution deposition by UV and low-temperature annealing that meet the needs of the AR market. Our inks comprise a platform technology, providing opportunities to build on success in the AR market through additional company growth in solid state lighting (LED and OLED), optical sensor, optical adhesive, anti-reflective coating, and display markets.</span></p> <br /></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/24/2022<br>      Modified by: Omid&nbsp;Sadeghihosseinabadi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Besides many advantages that Augmented Reality (AR) devices offer, the users have a strong need for more efficacious and wearable AR headsets. Current headsets do not satisfy end-user expectations, as they are bulky and present a small field of view (FOV), low image quality, and short battery life.To improve the user’s immersive experience and efficiency of the devices, AR manufacturers are seeking components fabricated with transparent, high refractive-index materials which is made of a glass substrate and high refractive index coating. Glass manufacturers have recently announced the availability of new, high-index glass substrates (n ~ 2.1) to meet the technical needs for next-generation devices but high-index, imprintable materials to match the index of the new glass substrates are currently unavailable in the market. Phosio is developing UV-curable inorganic inks for imprinting and manufacturing high refractive-index coatings. The materials and fabrication methods are crucial for realizing the next generation of wearable devices in the AR market. During Phase I, we demonstrated the feasibility of new materials and methods to nano-pattern transparent, high refractive-index films via solution deposition by UV and low-temperature annealing that meet the needs of the AR market. Our inks comprise a platform technology, providing opportunities to build on success in the AR market through additional company growth in solid state lighting (LED and OLED), optical sensor, optical adhesive, anti-reflective coating, and display markets.            Last Modified: 05/24/2022       Submitted by: Omid Sadeghihosseinabadi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
