<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Infrared light-emitting nanoparticles for biological imaging]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a cancer surveillance technology with a broad range of applications from improved surgery guidance in patients to pre-clinical cancer therapy prognostics.  The proposed technology utilizes probes that may be targeted to the cancers and illuminated using short-wave infrared (SWIR) light emitted upon excitation, which allows researchers to see cancer lesions deeper in tissue and with better resolution. This technology will address a major unmet need in personalized medicine, where patients with difficult to treat cancers have limited time to pursue the best treatment regimen.  The solution relies on harvesting, grafting and screening patient cancers using animal models to rapidly identify the most effective, patient-specific treatment.  The global small animal imaging market is expected to grow by 6-8% to $3.6 billion by 2024 (“Preclinical Imaging Market Analysis” Grandview Research; 2016), while optical imaging represents ~20% of the market.  The proposed technology has the potential to expand and disrupt some of the current optical imaging technologies within this market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a cancer surveillance technology, a bundled disease and drug screening platform of infrared light-emitting, cancer-targeted nanoprobes paired with an imaging system for scanning live animals. The nanoprobes have a rare earth nanoparticle core (Er3+, Ho3+, Tm3+) and are rendered biocompatible through encapsulation in an albumin shell. When excited with near-infrared (NIR) light, they emit short-wave infrared (SWIR) light that travels further through blood and tissue than does light from other optical imaging modalities, thus allowing imaging of tumors and other tissues deeper in the animal. The rare earth-based nanoprobes have been shown to detect smaller deep-seated diseased lesions in the animal and have been used to monitor multi-organ metastases longitudinally. The proposed nanoprobes are engineered to emit at multiple differentiated narrow bandwidth SWIR wavelengths, resulting in the unique ability to multiplex for detection of multiple diagnostic markers.  The proposed technology has been shown to have significantly greater sensitivity for early detection of cancers than the current standard for preclinical imaging (bioluminescence (BLI) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)). In addition, the technology has been used to track the response of different tumor subsets to drugs, positioning it as one of the first methods for precise detection of therapy response.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052770</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vidya</FirstName>
<LastName>Ganapathy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vidya Ganapathy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vg180@soe.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000837411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 RUTGERS PLZ</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088548058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Public Health Relevance:</strong></p> <p>Current imaging approaches for sub-tissue microlesions are severely limited as current in vivo optical imaging technologies are not able to detect subsurface microlesions, causing delays in drug testing until the tumors grow to detectable sizes, while also losing clinical relevance by the time tumors are detected. NanoInk Imaging has developed an optical imaging technology leveraging functionalized nanoprobes that emit short-wave infrared (SWIR) light to enable small sub-tissue microlesion detection in small animal disease models. NanoInk?s nanoprobe imaging platform will allow tumor growth and regression to be quantitatively monitored over time, before and after introduction of potential therapeutic agents, enabling advancements in preclinical research and personalized medicine.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Hypothesis:</strong></p> <p>In vivo whole-body imaging of mice is a key component of preclinical drug screening and therapy validation. Our hypothesis was that <strong>current</strong> in vivo optical imaging technologies <strong>are not able to detect subsurface microlesions,</strong> causing delays in drug testing until the tumors grow to detectable sizes. Such a delay could result in tumors that are less clinically relevant, potentially leading to incorrect outcomes of preclinical studies; by the time these tumors grow large enough in animal models to be detected by standard imaging technologies, researchers have missed the critical window of development during which the tumors can be closely compared to human models, and the disease is effectively at a different stage of progression than what is being targeted for investigation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p> <p>We conducted over 101 interviews with potential customers, suppliers, and strategic partners during the program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Through customer discovery interviews, we validated our hypothesis that preclinical researchers are limited in their ability to do high-throughput monitoring of tumor growth and response to drugs <em>in vivo</em>, using current imaging modalities.&nbsp; <strong>Current whole-body optical imaging technologies</strong> still have limitations including:</p> <ul> <li><strong>The need to genetically modify cells</strong></li> <li><strong>High tissue autofluorescence (impacting signal/background ratio) and</strong></li> <li><strong>Poor penetration of bioluminescent emissions in tissue, limiting imaging depth and resolution</strong></li> </ul> <p>Through these interviews, we also gained new insights into the imaging of <strong>liquid tumors</strong> such as leukemias and lymphomas. There remains a significant unmet need for researchers in these indications, as there is no methodology to currently image or monitor sub-tissue liquid tumors in mouse models other than by animal sacrifice at a timepoint when these tumors have grown to the point where they are no longer clinically relevant.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Customers:</strong></p> <p>We confirmed our target customer group to be 1. Researchers at academic institutions, 2. contract research organizations, and 2. core imaging centers that frequently use bioluminescence imaging (BLI) to assess tumor growth and treatment efficacy in murine models.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Product-market fit:</strong></p> <p>Through the I-Corps process we confirmed a <strong>strong product-market fit</strong> for NanoInk Imaging Sytem (NIS).</p> <ul> <li>NIS addresses a clear unmet need in preclinical drug discovery</li> <li>Pricing of both nanoprobes and hardware is both profitable for us and acceptable for the customer</li> <li>Identified partners for probe and hardware manufacturing</li> <li>Identified potential customers who are interested in beta-testing our technology</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Current Efforts:</strong></p> <p>We identified some minimal activities that NanoInk needs to conduct in order to enter the market and start generating revenue. These include:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; scale the production of nanoparticle manufacturing 2) manufacture a minimal viable hardware and software product for our NIS</p> <p>We subsequently secured an NIH grant and friends and family funds to pursue these efforts. We are also pursuing other non-dilutive and dilutive funding to get us to commercial readiness</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Innovation:</strong></p> <p>At the core of NanoInk?s patented luminescent contrast agents are nanoparticles doped with rare-earth elements that emit short-wave infrared (SWIR) light. SWIR light travels through blood and tissue with less scattering than the visible and near infrared light used by BLI, resulting in higher resolution imaging. Background light due to tissue autofluorescence is negligible at SWIR wavelengths, resulting in higher contrast imaging. These nanoparticles are encapsulated in a biocompatible protein or polymer shell that can be conjugated with targeting ligands. By pairing different color nanoparticles with different targeting ligands, we can perform multiplexed imaging of distinct disease biomarkers in individual animals. Together, these advantages enable molecular-specific imaging of small lesions located deep within live animals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Vidya&nbsp;Ganapathy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Public Health Relevance:  Current imaging approaches for sub-tissue microlesions are severely limited as current in vivo optical imaging technologies are not able to detect subsurface microlesions, causing delays in drug testing until the tumors grow to detectable sizes, while also losing clinical relevance by the time tumors are detected. NanoInk Imaging has developed an optical imaging technology leveraging functionalized nanoprobes that emit short-wave infrared (SWIR) light to enable small sub-tissue microlesion detection in small animal disease models. NanoInk?s nanoprobe imaging platform will allow tumor growth and regression to be quantitatively monitored over time, before and after introduction of potential therapeutic agents, enabling advancements in preclinical research and personalized medicine.     Hypothesis:  In vivo whole-body imaging of mice is a key component of preclinical drug screening and therapy validation. Our hypothesis was that current in vivo optical imaging technologies are not able to detect subsurface microlesions, causing delays in drug testing until the tumors grow to detectable sizes. Such a delay could result in tumors that are less clinically relevant, potentially leading to incorrect outcomes of preclinical studies; by the time these tumors grow large enough in animal models to be detected by standard imaging technologies, researchers have missed the critical window of development during which the tumors can be closely compared to human models, and the disease is effectively at a different stage of progression than what is being targeted for investigation.     Key Learnings:  We conducted over 101 interviews with potential customers, suppliers, and strategic partners during the program.     Through customer discovery interviews, we validated our hypothesis that preclinical researchers are limited in their ability to do high-throughput monitoring of tumor growth and response to drugs in vivo, using current imaging modalities.  Current whole-body optical imaging technologies still have limitations including:  The need to genetically modify cells High tissue autofluorescence (impacting signal/background ratio) and Poor penetration of bioluminescent emissions in tissue, limiting imaging depth and resolution   Through these interviews, we also gained new insights into the imaging of liquid tumors such as leukemias and lymphomas. There remains a significant unmet need for researchers in these indications, as there is no methodology to currently image or monitor sub-tissue liquid tumors in mouse models other than by animal sacrifice at a timepoint when these tumors have grown to the point where they are no longer clinically relevant.     Customers:  We confirmed our target customer group to be 1. Researchers at academic institutions, 2. contract research organizations, and 2. core imaging centers that frequently use bioluminescence imaging (BLI) to assess tumor growth and treatment efficacy in murine models.     Product-market fit:  Through the I-Corps process we confirmed a strong product-market fit for NanoInk Imaging Sytem (NIS).  NIS addresses a clear unmet need in preclinical drug discovery Pricing of both nanoprobes and hardware is both profitable for us and acceptable for the customer Identified partners for probe and hardware manufacturing Identified potential customers who are interested in beta-testing our technology    Current Efforts:  We identified some minimal activities that NanoInk needs to conduct in order to enter the market and start generating revenue. These include:  1)     scale the production of nanoparticle manufacturing 2) manufacture a minimal viable hardware and software product for our NIS  We subsequently secured an NIH grant and friends and family funds to pursue these efforts. We are also pursuing other non-dilutive and dilutive funding to get us to commercial readiness     Innovation:  At the core of NanoInk?s patented luminescent contrast agents are nanoparticles doped with rare-earth elements that emit short-wave infrared (SWIR) light. SWIR light travels through blood and tissue with less scattering than the visible and near infrared light used by BLI, resulting in higher resolution imaging. Background light due to tissue autofluorescence is negligible at SWIR wavelengths, resulting in higher contrast imaging. These nanoparticles are encapsulated in a biocompatible protein or polymer shell that can be conjugated with targeting ligands. By pairing different color nanoparticles with different targeting ligands, we can perform multiplexed imaging of distinct disease biomarkers in individual animals. Together, these advantages enable molecular-specific imaging of small lesions located deep within live animals.                      Last Modified: 06/01/2022       Submitted by: Vidya Ganapathy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
