<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Low-cost clean one-step production of solar silicon from natural quartzite]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255730.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>271730</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be the reduction of silicon in PV modules from 4¢/W to 0.8-1¢/W. Besides considerable silicon price reduction, this novel technology removes currently presented safety and environmental concerns of silicon production. Decreasing the total PV module cost will improve access to solar cells, through which the overall consumption of fossil fuels could be reduced. Moreover, since this novel technology is zero direct GHG emission, replacing the current manufacturing processes with our new technology can positively affect the environment directly and immediately. This project will also advance the state-of-the-art in silicon manufacturing and provide a domestic source of PV quality silicon.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to develop a new molten salt electrolysis process which can produce solar silicon from natural 99.7-99.9% pure quartzite (SiO₂) in just two steps, replacing a complex energy-intensive five-step process today.  This process utilizes a state-of-the-art molten salt composition with a new mechanism for suppressing dendrite formation and salt trapping. This process can potentially produce silicon with 4-5N purity at $1.70/kg using &lt;30 kWh/kg, with pure oxygen by-product and zero direct Greenhouse Gas (GHG) emissions. The 4-5N product purity would be sufficient for directional solidification or direct boule/wafer production, resulting in $2.20-2.70/kg solar-grade silicon cost, i.e., 75-80% lower than today. This purity through the novel process is achievable via electrochemical selection, an inert anode to avoid carbon anode contamination, and low impurity solubility in the solid silicon product. The technical issues/risks to be addressed in this proposal are salt trapping to practically produce dense and pure product, removing more electronegative impurities (P, Fe) that cause problems with carrier lifetimes, and utilizing magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) stirring to overcome stagnant electrolyte bath.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052310</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>MOHAMMAD</FirstName>
<LastName>ASADIKIYA</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>MOHAMMAD ASADIKIYA</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[masadi@silartek.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000837444</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SILARTEK LLC</Name>
<CityName>LEOMINSTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>014533304</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7864491164</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>272 NASHUA ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CAQCVNEN5NQ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SILARTEK LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SILARTEK LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Worcester</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016054336</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 PLANTATION ST., APT. 415]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~271730</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Project Outcomes Report</span></strong></p> <p>Silicon is the dominant Photovoltaic (PV) material due to its abundance, low cost, and good PV efficiency. Polysilicon production for photovoltaics via the Siemens process today consists of carbothermic reduction, synthesis, purification, and chemical vapor deposition of toxic explosive chlorosilanes. This process is inherently complex, energy-intensive (300 kWh/kg), and unsafe.</p> <p>Our goal is to produce high-purity silicon from natural 99.7-99.9% pure quartzite (SiO&#8322;) in only one-step, utilizing molten salt electrolysis with a state-of-the-art molten salt composition. This process can potentially produce silicon with 4-5N purity at $1.70/kg using &lt;30 kWh/kg, with pure oxygen by-product and zero direct Greenhouse Gas (GHG) emissions. The 4-5N product purity would be sufficient for directional solidification or direct boule/wafer production, resulting in $2.20-2.70/kg solar-grade silicon cost, i.e., up to 90% lower than today. This purity through the novel process is achievable via electrochemical selection, an inert anode to avoid carbon anode contamination, and low impurity solubility in the solid silicon product. Besides considerable silicon price reduction, our novel technology removes currently presented safety and environmental concerns of silicon production.&nbsp;</p> <p>Thank to the NSF SBIR Phase I funding, lots of experiments and studies executed to address technical challenges and evaluate the market. During Phase I project, SilarTek LLC conducted a wide range of studies regarding different aspects that might affect the solar silicon production applying high-temperature molten salt electrolysis process. More specifically, the effects of electrolysis temperature, heating rate, holding times, applied voltage, oxygen partial pressure, bath composition, substrate material to deposit silicon on, mixing the bath during electrolysis, electrical isolation of the cell, the diffusion behavior of species in the flux, the proper frequency and duty cycle for the current switch, and the amount of silicon dioxide added to the melt were carefully studied. The outcome of each experiment moved the technology one or more steps forward towards the final solar silicon product.</p> <p>Currently, all the abovementioned parameters have been optimized and the practical window of each parameter has been determined. It was demonstrated that the determined windows can result in solar silicon deposition, thus, the process is ready for the next step, which is continuous production.</p> <p>Moreover, it was revealed during market evaluation activities in the Beat the Odds boot camp and the NSF I-Corps site program at Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI) that the solar silicon price fluctuation is the main pain point acknowledged by prospective customers. In long term, SilarTek novel technology can control solar silicon price fluctuations due to its capability to adapt the production with the market demand. Therefore, it is expected the traditional production methods are replaced with the SilarTek novel technology in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Mohammad&nbsp;Asadikiya</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052310/2052310_10728840_1688056886779_Picture--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052310/2052310_10728840_1688056886779_Picture--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SilarTek Novel Technology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052310/2052310_10728840_1688056886779_Picture--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SilarTek Novel Technology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of the silicon-PV supply chain and SilarTek novel solar silicon production technology</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mohammad Asadikiya</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mohammad&nbsp;Asadikiya</div> <div class="imageTitle">SilarTek Novel Technology</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052310/2052310_10728840_1688057165018_ValuePropositions--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052310/2052310_10728840_1688057165018_ValuePropositions--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SilarTek Novel Technology Value Proposition"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2052310/2052310_10728840_1688057165018_ValuePropositions--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SilarTek Novel Technology Value Proposition"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SilarTek novel technology value proposition and solar silicon market value</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mohammad Asadikiya</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mohammad&nbsp;Asadikiya</div> <div class="imageTitle">SilarTek Novel Technology Value Proposition</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Project Outcomes Report  Silicon is the dominant Photovoltaic (PV) material due to its abundance, low cost, and good PV efficiency. Polysilicon production for photovoltaics via the Siemens process today consists of carbothermic reduction, synthesis, purification, and chemical vapor deposition of toxic explosive chlorosilanes. This process is inherently complex, energy-intensive (300 kWh/kg), and unsafe.  Our goal is to produce high-purity silicon from natural 99.7-99.9% pure quartzite (SiO&#8322;) in only one-step, utilizing molten salt electrolysis with a state-of-the-art molten salt composition. This process can potentially produce silicon with 4-5N purity at $1.70/kg using &lt;30 kWh/kg, with pure oxygen by-product and zero direct Greenhouse Gas (GHG) emissions. The 4-5N product purity would be sufficient for directional solidification or direct boule/wafer production, resulting in $2.20-2.70/kg solar-grade silicon cost, i.e., up to 90% lower than today. This purity through the novel process is achievable via electrochemical selection, an inert anode to avoid carbon anode contamination, and low impurity solubility in the solid silicon product. Besides considerable silicon price reduction, our novel technology removes currently presented safety and environmental concerns of silicon production.   Thank to the NSF SBIR Phase I funding, lots of experiments and studies executed to address technical challenges and evaluate the market. During Phase I project, SilarTek LLC conducted a wide range of studies regarding different aspects that might affect the solar silicon production applying high-temperature molten salt electrolysis process. More specifically, the effects of electrolysis temperature, heating rate, holding times, applied voltage, oxygen partial pressure, bath composition, substrate material to deposit silicon on, mixing the bath during electrolysis, electrical isolation of the cell, the diffusion behavior of species in the flux, the proper frequency and duty cycle for the current switch, and the amount of silicon dioxide added to the melt were carefully studied. The outcome of each experiment moved the technology one or more steps forward towards the final solar silicon product.  Currently, all the abovementioned parameters have been optimized and the practical window of each parameter has been determined. It was demonstrated that the determined windows can result in solar silicon deposition, thus, the process is ready for the next step, which is continuous production.  Moreover, it was revealed during market evaluation activities in the Beat the Odds boot camp and the NSF I-Corps site program at Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI) that the solar silicon price fluctuation is the main pain point acknowledged by prospective customers. In long term, SilarTek novel technology can control solar silicon price fluctuations due to its capability to adapt the production with the market demand. Therefore, it is expected the traditional production methods are replaced with the SilarTek novel technology in the future.             Last Modified: 06/29/2023       Submitted by: Mohammad Asadikiya]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
