<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Novel size-changing, gadolinium-free contrast agent for magnetic resonance angiography]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is improved diagnosis of cardiovascular disease, the top cause of death globally, taking about 18 million lives each year. The proposed work will develop a contrast agent that improves the diagnostic value of magnetic resonance angiograms (MRA), by enhancing images of the vascular system, and which also shows an improved safety profile compared to currently utilized contrast agents. It thus has the potential to vastly improve the detection of abnormalities (e.g. aneurysms) in the aorta, peripheral, renal, and carotid arteries, among others. This product will bring significant value to radiologists and medical institutions that perform MRAs for diagnosis of deep venous thrombosis, vascular malformations, peripheral arterial disease, and in pediatric imaging. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I will develop a novel iron-based, blood-pool contrast agent (BPCA) for use in magnetic resonance angiograms (MRA) with enhanced imaging capabilities and reduced risk of long-term side effects. Contrast-enhanced MRA is a staple diagnostic procedure for imaging blood vessels, and the market is currently dominated by gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs) due to their excellent longitudinal (T1)-shortening effects. However, GBCAs are associated with numerous side effects and long-term gadolinium deposition in the brain. Due to their potential toxicity, GBCAs are designed to be rapidly cleared through kidney filtration – leaving only a short window for MRA image acquisition and resulting in poor image quality. To address the need for a safer contrast agent that provides enhanced vascular imaging, this project will develop an iron-based BPCA (i.e. one that remains in blood vessels), enabling an extended imaging window for improved vascular imaging in MRA, but which is then cleared by kidney filtration (minimizing tissue accumulation). Successful accomplishment of Phase I goals will demonstrate that the proposed agent achieves the desired BPCA that is cleared through kidney filtration, control pharmacokinetics and biodistribution, and demonstrates enhanced MRA performance versus GBCAs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052242</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tareq</FirstName>
<LastName>Anani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tareq Anani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tareqbanani@nanoxort.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/29/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abhinav</FirstName>
<LastName>Sannidhi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abhinav Sannidhi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[abhinavsannidhi@nanoxort.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000853596</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
<LastName>David</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allan E David</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aedavid@auburn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000642176</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NANOXORT LLC</Name>
<CityName>AUBURN</CityName>
<ZipCode>368325888</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3305244503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>540 DEVALL DR STE 101-1A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XEFGPVQ94B79</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NANOXORT LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NANOXORT LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>AUBURN</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>368324361</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2175 PUMPHREY AVE SPC 6]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3649958f-7fff-799e-318d-37dc7c81ac93"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance angiography (CE-MRA) is a staple diagnostic procedure for imaging blood vessels, and the market is currently dominated by gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs) due to their excellent longitudinal (T1)-shortening effects. However, GBCAs are associated with several side effects and long-term gadolinium deposition in the brain. Due to their potential toxicity, GBCAs are designed to be rapidly cleared through kidney filtration - leaving only a short imaging window for CE-MRA image acquisition and resulting in poor image quality at steady-state.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is improved diagnosis of cardiovascular disease, the top cause of death globally, taking about 18 million lives each year. To address this, Nanoxort developed an iron-based blood-pool contrast agent (i.e. one that remains in blood vessels), for use in CE-MRA for detection of vascular diseases. Our size-changing nano-particles result in better image quality through enhanced signal-to-noise and contrast-to-noise ratios compared to GBCAs, and longer vascular retention enabling longer imaging window, while reducing toxicity that results from traditional GBCAs. The NSF Phase I STTR feasibility study yielded a minimum viable product with excellent imaging characteristics enabling an extended imaging window for improved vascular imaging in MRA, but which is then cleared by kidney filtration reducing the risk of long-term side effects. Additionally, the product showed no signs of toxicity. This product will bring significant value to radiologists and medical institutions that perform MRAs for diagnosis of deep venous thrombosis, vascular malformations, peripheral arterial disease, renal stenosis, and in pediatric imaging. Nanoxort's blood-pool contrast agent creates a win-win-win scenario for everyone involved; for patients with vascular disease, not only does iron provide a safer alternative than gadolinium, but also a more accurate and quick diagnosis (rather than having to be exposed to multiple inferior diagnostic tools that could take weeks to schedule, etc., and could receive resistance from insurance companies) that will allow doctors to prescribe safer, more effective treatments. For the patient's family, it's less financial and stress burden. For radiologists, it's clearer images, hence more accurate diagnoses (simplifies the workflow). For physicians, a more accurate diagnosis creates more confidence in assigning treatment and mitigates the potential for malpractice suits.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Abhinav&nbsp;Sannidhi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance angiography (CE-MRA) is a staple diagnostic procedure for imaging blood vessels, and the market is currently dominated by gadolinium-based contrast agents (GBCAs) due to their excellent longitudinal (T1)-shortening effects. However, GBCAs are associated with several side effects and long-term gadolinium deposition in the brain. Due to their potential toxicity, GBCAs are designed to be rapidly cleared through kidney filtration - leaving only a short imaging window for CE-MRA image acquisition and resulting in poor image quality at steady-state.  The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is improved diagnosis of cardiovascular disease, the top cause of death globally, taking about 18 million lives each year. To address this, Nanoxort developed an iron-based blood-pool contrast agent (i.e. one that remains in blood vessels), for use in CE-MRA for detection of vascular diseases. Our size-changing nano-particles result in better image quality through enhanced signal-to-noise and contrast-to-noise ratios compared to GBCAs, and longer vascular retention enabling longer imaging window, while reducing toxicity that results from traditional GBCAs. The NSF Phase I STTR feasibility study yielded a minimum viable product with excellent imaging characteristics enabling an extended imaging window for improved vascular imaging in MRA, but which is then cleared by kidney filtration reducing the risk of long-term side effects. Additionally, the product showed no signs of toxicity. This product will bring significant value to radiologists and medical institutions that perform MRAs for diagnosis of deep venous thrombosis, vascular malformations, peripheral arterial disease, renal stenosis, and in pediatric imaging. Nanoxort's blood-pool contrast agent creates a win-win-win scenario for everyone involved; for patients with vascular disease, not only does iron provide a safer alternative than gadolinium, but also a more accurate and quick diagnosis (rather than having to be exposed to multiple inferior diagnostic tools that could take weeks to schedule, etc., and could receive resistance from insurance companies) that will allow doctors to prescribe safer, more effective treatments. For the patient's family, it's less financial and stress burden. For radiologists, it's clearer images, hence more accurate diagnoses (simplifies the workflow). For physicians, a more accurate diagnosis creates more confidence in assigning treatment and mitigates the potential for malpractice suits.          Last Modified: 03/14/2023       Submitted by: Abhinav Sannidhi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
