<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Low-cost photothermal nanosensors for quantitative biomarker detection using a thermometer]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of new, low-cost, portable biomarker detection methods in response to the growing market of biomolecular detectors for various applications such as disease diagnosis and cancer biomarker detection at the point of care. For example, prostate cancer is the second leading cause of cancer death in men in the United States. It is estimated that 191,930 new cases and 33,330 deaths from this disease will occur this year. However, the current technologies for prostate cancer diagnosis are invasive, and require expensive instrumentation, which significantly impairs their capacity for point-of-care (POC) detection in low-resource settings such as physician’s offices or at a patient’s bedside. The proposed photothermal nanobiosensor uses a thermometer for quantitative biosensing.  The nanobiosensor is rapid, low-cost, minimally invasive, and does not require expensive equipment and trained personnel for data recording and processing; This may enable prostate-specific antigen (PSA, a prostate cancer biomarker) testing in small physician’s offices.  The thermometer-based nanobiosensor also may be used to detect a variety of other disease biomarkers and biochemicals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of the thermometer-based nanosensor for point-of-care (POC) detection of biomarkers such as the prostate-specific antigen (PSA). The innovation is based on a biosensing method using a thermometer as the signal reader. The thermometer-based nanobiosensor is not only rapid, low-cost, and portable, but also minimizes instrumentation requirements. In addition, the nanobiosensor offers comparable detection sensitivity to conventional immunoassay methods. The proposed photothermal immunosensor may open up new opportunities for affordable detection of disease biomarkers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052347</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>XiuJun</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>XiuJun Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xli4@utep.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000599427</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at El Paso</Name>
<CityName>EL PASO</CityName>
<ZipCode>799680001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9157475680</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 W UNIVERSITY AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C1DEGMMKC7W7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT EL PASO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at El Paso]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>799680001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cancer biomarker detection plays a vital role in cancer early diagnosis and timely treatment. However, current methods cannot meet the increasing needs for simple low-cost methods for timely cancer biomarker detection at the point of care. For instance, prostate cancer is the second leading cause of cancer death in men in the United States. It is estimated that 191,930 new cases and 33,330 deaths from this disease occur in 2022.&nbsp;However, the current major technologies for prostate cancer diagnosis are invasive, and require expensive instrumentation, which significantly impairs their capacity for point-of-care (POC) detection in low-resource settings such as physician&rsquo;s offices or a patient&rsquo;s bedside. Our new photothermal nanobiosensor using a thermometer for quantitative biosensing is rapid, low-cost, minimally invasive, and does not require expensive equipment and trained personnel for data recording and processing, enabling prostate-specific antigen (PSA, a prostate cancer biomarker) testing available in small physician&rsquo;s office that is currently incapable. &nbsp;Our thermometer-based nanobiosensor can also be used to detect a variety of other disease biomarkers. The impact of this research is broad.</p> <p><em>Through more than 1</em><em>00</em><em> customer interviews, we have concluded there is a product-market fit. A start-up company microBioChip Diagnostics LLC has been founded to further implement this effort of the commercialization.</em><em> An NSF PFI proposal is under preparation for further implementation of this effort. </em><em>With the support this grant, we have published 1</em><em>2</em><em> papers. This project also give</em><em>s</em><em> two Ph.D. students and two minority undergraduate students to receive not only biotechnology development training but also entrepreneurship training.</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Xiujun&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cancer biomarker detection plays a vital role in cancer early diagnosis and timely treatment. However, current methods cannot meet the increasing needs for simple low-cost methods for timely cancer biomarker detection at the point of care. For instance, prostate cancer is the second leading cause of cancer death in men in the United States. It is estimated that 191,930 new cases and 33,330 deaths from this disease occur in 2022. However, the current major technologies for prostate cancer diagnosis are invasive, and require expensive instrumentation, which significantly impairs their capacity for point-of-care (POC) detection in low-resource settings such as physician’s offices or a patient’s bedside. Our new photothermal nanobiosensor using a thermometer for quantitative biosensing is rapid, low-cost, minimally invasive, and does not require expensive equipment and trained personnel for data recording and processing, enabling prostate-specific antigen (PSA, a prostate cancer biomarker) testing available in small physician’s office that is currently incapable.  Our thermometer-based nanobiosensor can also be used to detect a variety of other disease biomarkers. The impact of this research is broad.  Through more than 100 customer interviews, we have concluded there is a product-market fit. A start-up company microBioChip Diagnostics LLC has been founded to further implement this effort of the commercialization. An NSF PFI proposal is under preparation for further implementation of this effort. With the support this grant, we have published 12 papers. This project also gives two Ph.D. students and two minority undergraduate students to receive not only biotechnology development training but also entrepreneurship training.             Last Modified: 05/29/2023       Submitted by: Xiujun Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
