<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Development of a smart container for mobile blood banking system used in cold blood storage and transport in extreme environments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to increase the availability of cold stored medical therapies for point of injury care in a prehospital setting, as well as to increase cold chain payload transparency with real time data tracking for a wide variety of biological materials.  Increased cold chain transparency via internet of things (IoT) connected devices will allow clinicians and inventory managers to confidently push therapies outside of a hospital with full confidence in their efficacy upon administration to severely wounded patients where care is needed prior to or during transport to a medical facility. Real time data on payload conditions may enable clinicians know exactly what the payload temperatures are without having to manually open a container, exposing payloads to heat, dust, sun and other undesirable conditions to determine the status of their cold-stored biomaterials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project specifically targets the high mortality rates associated with trauma wounds in the field or at the accident site. By providing a modular cooling, storage, and transportation system, the use of preferred whole blood and blood component therapies will be more readily available for life saving interventions. The goal of this project is to identify lightweight, mobile, and modular cooler and storage devices to validate small unit, interchangeable blood banking solutions to support clinicians in a prehospital setting. Additional research goals focus on sensor integration both inside and outside of device to use data driven learning and in a future state artificial intelligence to maximize use of temperature sensitive therapies from an inventory management perspective.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052341</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffry</FirstName>
<LastName>Skiba</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffry Skiba</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeff.skiba@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000870093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/17/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Travis</FirstName>
<LastName>Witzke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Travis Witzke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[travis@desertvalleytech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000837214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/17/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>DESERT VALLEY TECH INC.</Name>
<CityName>SCOTTSDALE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852581132</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6023846520</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7721 E NORTH LANE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N5BQPJNTAE21</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DESERT VALLEY TECH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[DESERT VALLEY TECH INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Mesa</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852016690</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[123 N Centennial Way, #205]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4097</Code>
<Text>NETWORKING RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Outcomes for Contemporary Solution for Cold Chain Transportation of Biologics/Blood</em></p> <p>Linda Vu M.D., Burt Skiba J.D, MBA, BSME, Jeffry Skiba PI, BSME, BSBA,</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Transportation of biologics which include but are not limited to blood, organs, tissue, and vaccines, must follow a strict, regulated chain of custody to preserve their viability and function upon arrival at their destination. Shipping controls in the future will include active monitoring, damage and tamper evidence and effective chain of custody to ensure the products arrive at their destination whole, intact and unaffected by the rigors of transport. Breakdown within the U.S. supply chain are becoming routinely experienced.&nbsp; Experiencing supply chain failures with life-saving blood at a critical point of need can result in unnecessary injury and casualties.</p> <p>During production and storage, conditions can be controlled and monitored. However, once in shipment, conditions must be equally maintained inside the shipping container, because shipping environmental temperatures can range from below freezing to extremely hot. In a desert environment, temperatures inside of a delivery vehicle can reach up to 150 degrees Fahrenheit.&nbsp; During production or blood donation process handling is controlled. However, when shipping the package will go through varying conditions and package validation studies require aggressive physical tests to demonstrate the package can protect its contents. Current validation standards of shipments require vertical drops, horizontal slides, diagonal slides, and vibration to ensure the package integrity survives the transportation.&nbsp; In the case of temperature extremes with sensitive products, addition of coolants and insulation is required to maintain proper storage conditions without the potential for contamination of the contents. Maintenance of thermal conditions during shipment is currently limited to under three days in hot conditions. The proposed modification to the physical transportation and storage will significantly improve supply chains for the most critical contents that require a high level of protection and monitoring.</p> <p>Moving vaccines has recently challenged the supply chain by sheer number and that it requires very low temperatures to preserve the vaccine in extreme environmental conditions. Currently, the FDA and American Red Cross is pushing for, and requiring, in critical circumstances, more reliable shipping methods that include validated cold chain custody, package integrity, and tamper evidence.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Once a biologic leaves the manufacturers&rsquo; control into shipping the cold chain custody challenge begins. Currently, an accepted method of shipping utilizes a cardboard box lined with Styrofoam then packed with ice. Limitations of this package include limited impact protection, limited security, potential for freezing, short storage times, and no onboard sensors. These types of containers require being in close proximity to a controlled temperature refrigerator to shorten the time to move precooled biologic into the shipping container reducing the potential for warming.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant evaluated the feasibility of a Mobile Biologic Cooling System (&ldquo;MOBIS&rdquo;), powered and designed to actively cool multiple containers when docked within the MOBIS, providing a high level of controlled cooling and package integrity addressing each of the critical design elements. The solution modularizes two units of blood by using the existing blood storage bag and inserting it into an active/passively cooled transport container. Active cooling when docked and passive when separated extends the effective storage time and range at the contents required storage temperature.</p> <p>Onboard sensors and relay systems are intended to actively send real-time location data, the content's thermal exposure conditions, and tamper evidence to the user. This system provides maximum verification that the Biologics are delivered to the end user in the best possible condition and actively reports if the contents have become unusable due to thermal exposure or tampering. Active tracking will enable the centralized system to report what product is available and where it is located, how much of the supply is close to expiration, and delivery times within the supply chain. When needed, each individual container can be separated from the MOBIS and continue to maintain internal temperature through highly insulative container. This design maintains below the maximum allowable temp for up to five days. The container can also be re-inserted into the MOBIS and cooled back down to reuse it or cool the contents that may not have been used back to set point temperatures.&nbsp; Once the MOBIS cools the individual containers, the containers can be disconnected from MOBIS and be airlifted to any location that is within a five-day window (extending current times by three days). This approach will place a strategic, critical supply of blood closer to where it is needed, when it is needed and place active cooling at the place where it is needed.</p> <p>In this study, the feasibility of designing an improved biologics transport system was reduced to three initial aims.&nbsp; Each aim was divided into subtasks and are included in the Aims Reports attached the grant final report. &nbsp;Feasibility through procedure review, user specification and design inputs, and simulation approach for testing design.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeffry&nbsp;Skiba</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes for Contemporary Solution for Cold Chain Transportation of Biologics/Blood  Linda Vu M.D., Burt Skiba J.D, MBA, BSME, Jeffry Skiba PI, BSME, BSBA,     Transportation of biologics which include but are not limited to blood, organs, tissue, and vaccines, must follow a strict, regulated chain of custody to preserve their viability and function upon arrival at their destination. Shipping controls in the future will include active monitoring, damage and tamper evidence and effective chain of custody to ensure the products arrive at their destination whole, intact and unaffected by the rigors of transport. Breakdown within the U.S. supply chain are becoming routinely experienced.  Experiencing supply chain failures with life-saving blood at a critical point of need can result in unnecessary injury and casualties.  During production and storage, conditions can be controlled and monitored. However, once in shipment, conditions must be equally maintained inside the shipping container, because shipping environmental temperatures can range from below freezing to extremely hot. In a desert environment, temperatures inside of a delivery vehicle can reach up to 150 degrees Fahrenheit.  During production or blood donation process handling is controlled. However, when shipping the package will go through varying conditions and package validation studies require aggressive physical tests to demonstrate the package can protect its contents. Current validation standards of shipments require vertical drops, horizontal slides, diagonal slides, and vibration to ensure the package integrity survives the transportation.  In the case of temperature extremes with sensitive products, addition of coolants and insulation is required to maintain proper storage conditions without the potential for contamination of the contents. Maintenance of thermal conditions during shipment is currently limited to under three days in hot conditions. The proposed modification to the physical transportation and storage will significantly improve supply chains for the most critical contents that require a high level of protection and monitoring.  Moving vaccines has recently challenged the supply chain by sheer number and that it requires very low temperatures to preserve the vaccine in extreme environmental conditions. Currently, the FDA and American Red Cross is pushing for, and requiring, in critical circumstances, more reliable shipping methods that include validated cold chain custody, package integrity, and tamper evidence.     Once a biologic leaves the manufacturers’ control into shipping the cold chain custody challenge begins. Currently, an accepted method of shipping utilizes a cardboard box lined with Styrofoam then packed with ice. Limitations of this package include limited impact protection, limited security, potential for freezing, short storage times, and no onboard sensors. These types of containers require being in close proximity to a controlled temperature refrigerator to shorten the time to move precooled biologic into the shipping container reducing the potential for warming.     This grant evaluated the feasibility of a Mobile Biologic Cooling System ("MOBIS"), powered and designed to actively cool multiple containers when docked within the MOBIS, providing a high level of controlled cooling and package integrity addressing each of the critical design elements. The solution modularizes two units of blood by using the existing blood storage bag and inserting it into an active/passively cooled transport container. Active cooling when docked and passive when separated extends the effective storage time and range at the contents required storage temperature.  Onboard sensors and relay systems are intended to actively send real-time location data, the content's thermal exposure conditions, and tamper evidence to the user. This system provides maximum verification that the Biologics are delivered to the end user in the best possible condition and actively reports if the contents have become unusable due to thermal exposure or tampering. Active tracking will enable the centralized system to report what product is available and where it is located, how much of the supply is close to expiration, and delivery times within the supply chain. When needed, each individual container can be separated from the MOBIS and continue to maintain internal temperature through highly insulative container. This design maintains below the maximum allowable temp for up to five days. The container can also be re-inserted into the MOBIS and cooled back down to reuse it or cool the contents that may not have been used back to set point temperatures.  Once the MOBIS cools the individual containers, the containers can be disconnected from MOBIS and be airlifted to any location that is within a five-day window (extending current times by three days). This approach will place a strategic, critical supply of blood closer to where it is needed, when it is needed and place active cooling at the place where it is needed.  In this study, the feasibility of designing an improved biologics transport system was reduced to three initial aims.  Each aim was divided into subtasks and are included in the Aims Reports attached the grant final report.  Feasibility through procedure review, user specification and design inputs, and simulation approach for testing design.           Last Modified: 04/01/2022       Submitted by: Jeffry Skiba]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
