<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Nursing Workforce Optimization Algorithm and Software]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact /commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project improves nursing operations in hospitals for better patient outcomes. This will be achieved through the analysis of a health system’s data regarding nurse staffing, scheduling, and nurse-patient matching. This research will analyze data on nurses, patients, and inpatient clinical environments and their relationship to outcomes to develop unique algorithms, software, and datasets in care facilities.  This is significant because the approach to nursing workforce management decisions influences care outcomes and the cost of delivery of quality care. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project involves advanced research techniques that aim to optimize nurse staffing, scheduling, and nurse-patient matching. Relationships will be examined between 1. independent variables associated with nursing operations and 2. dependent variables that include patient safety indicator variables developed by the Agency for Healthcare Quality and Research. The exploration of these relationships will help answer questions including 1) how many nurses to employ and deploy day-to-day (i.e. staffing), 2) how many and in what complement to deploy nurses on shifts (i.e. scheduling), and 3) how to match nurses to patients on each unit each shift (i.e. nurse-patient assignments) to optimize outcomes. The proposed optimization process enables a data- driven approach to address staffing, scheduling, and nurse-patient matching challenges. The methods involve multivariate regression analyses and machine learning techniques including autoregressive integrated moving average (ARIMA). The goals of this research involve the development of algorithms and software that empower hospital administrators with the insight and technology to improve nursing care and patient outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052208</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
<LastName>Plover</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colin Plover</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[colinplover@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000780943</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>1442 S. FALLON STREET, LLC</Name>
<CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>191433806</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8452422861</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1230 S 47TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FXRMGKG32HA4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>1442 S FALLON STREET LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[1442 S. FALLON STREET, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191430031</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~275997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This work resulted in the development of an innovative technology that helps nurses in hospitals align their nursing workforce with patients more efficiently and in ways that have potential to achieve better outcomes. Customer discovery and market research have not revealed that nurses have software with visualization, automation, customization, and machine learning geared towards improving outcomes and efficiency of core nursing operations.</p> <p>This technology addresses the critical need for nurses to have research driven, evidence-based nursing operations interventions geared towards improving the efficiency of care delivery, patient outcomes, costs of care, and revenue. The software offers <strong>visualization</strong> of nursing workforce dynamics that better inform nurse staffing, scheduling, and nurse-patient matching. The software also provides <strong>automation</strong>, allowing for the collection of data via integration with inpatient technologies. The software allows nurses to create customized interfaces and algorithms to systematically deploy their strategies to their nursing operations work. The software includes <strong>predictive analytics </strong>with integrated machine learning algorithms designed to improve outcomes associated with nursing workforce deployments. The algorithms apply insights from research exploring relationships between nursing workforce characteristics and outcomes to achieve better outcomes. The software can also serve to facilitate research as it is a resource for large amounts of unique data.</p> <p>The Phase I project involved the collection and synthesis of nurse perspectives across the country. In response to this customer discovery, several adjustments were made to the design of the software. Additional features were added to support nurses from the bedside to administrators in their decision-making regrading staffing, scheduling, and nurse-patient matching. This work also involved collaborating with multiple healthcare systems to access large amounts of nurse and patient data to examine relationships between nursing workforce characteristics and outcomes and to develop machine learning algorithms. This progress has advanced the technology towards full integrating into nursing care delivery by providing data that will identify what constitutes optimal nursing workforce utilizations. This technology has the potential to improve nurse and patient outcomes, costs of care, and care delivery efficiency. This could translate to lower morbidity and mortality for millions of hospitalized patients each year.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Colin&nbsp;Plover</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This work resulted in the development of an innovative technology that helps nurses in hospitals align their nursing workforce with patients more efficiently and in ways that have potential to achieve better outcomes. Customer discovery and market research have not revealed that nurses have software with visualization, automation, customization, and machine learning geared towards improving outcomes and efficiency of core nursing operations.  This technology addresses the critical need for nurses to have research driven, evidence-based nursing operations interventions geared towards improving the efficiency of care delivery, patient outcomes, costs of care, and revenue. The software offers visualization of nursing workforce dynamics that better inform nurse staffing, scheduling, and nurse-patient matching. The software also provides automation, allowing for the collection of data via integration with inpatient technologies. The software allows nurses to create customized interfaces and algorithms to systematically deploy their strategies to their nursing operations work. The software includes predictive analytics with integrated machine learning algorithms designed to improve outcomes associated with nursing workforce deployments. The algorithms apply insights from research exploring relationships between nursing workforce characteristics and outcomes to achieve better outcomes. The software can also serve to facilitate research as it is a resource for large amounts of unique data.  The Phase I project involved the collection and synthesis of nurse perspectives across the country. In response to this customer discovery, several adjustments were made to the design of the software. Additional features were added to support nurses from the bedside to administrators in their decision-making regrading staffing, scheduling, and nurse-patient matching. This work also involved collaborating with multiple healthcare systems to access large amounts of nurse and patient data to examine relationships between nursing workforce characteristics and outcomes and to develop machine learning algorithms. This progress has advanced the technology towards full integrating into nursing care delivery by providing data that will identify what constitutes optimal nursing workforce utilizations. This technology has the potential to improve nurse and patient outcomes, costs of care, and care delivery efficiency. This could translate to lower morbidity and mortality for millions of hospitalized patients each year.       Last Modified: 02/28/2023       Submitted by: Colin Plover]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
