<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Body fluid identification for forensic purposes using Raman spectroscopy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project proposes to develop the first universal method for non-destructive, confirmatory identification of all main bodily fluids in biological stains revealed at a crime, overcoming the limitations of standard biochemical tests when identifying biological stains. The proposed technology will allow for rapid, accurate and nondestructive identification of, and distinction between, biological stains that supports the possibility of linking DNA to a bodily fluid type, thus increasing the efficiency of crime labs and assisting law enforcement personnel in the identification of suspected criminals. Commercially, this technology will be of use to the 600+ Crime Investigation Labs and 19,000+ crime scene investigators within the U.S. Department of Justice. The new approach has the potential to reduce the backlog of unprocessed DNA samples in crime labs across the U.S., while providing data that can improve the efficiency of evidence analyses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This analysis platform has the potential to significantly advance the field of crime scene analysis by replacing single body fluid-specific chemical tests, that are inaccurate and destructive in nature, with software that offers the novel ability to positively identify all bodily fluids in order to generate real-time decisions regarding sample content and further analyses.  The project will establish proof-of-principle through the optimization of a Raman spectroscopy method for a desktop instrument while further developing software for realistic body fluid sampling. This will allow for the development of a working prototype for crime laboratory usage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052030</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexis</FirstName>
<LastName>Weber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexis R Weber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aweber@albany.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000858800</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Igor</FirstName>
<LastName>Lednev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Igor K Lednev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ilednev@albany.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000222541</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Hage</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hannah Hage</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hanhydehage@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834101</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/08/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUPREMETRIC LLC</Name>
<CityName>GLENMONT</CityName>
<ZipCode>120773318</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9043093477</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>66 JEFFERSON RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KX4JT8ZU8RG3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SUPREMETRIC LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUPREMETRIC LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>120773318</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8616</Code>
<Text>Instr Rsrch,Metro&amp;Std NanTech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The body fluid traces recovered at crime scenes are among the most important types of evidence to forensic investigators. Conventional methods of body fluid identification use labor-intensive, technologically diverse methods that are performed one after the other and are costly in both time and sample usage. The objectives of any crime scene investigation are to preserve physical evidence and collect only valuable evidence for the analytical examination. Therefore, the ability to characterize an unknown stain at the scene of the crime without destruction and having to wait for laboratory results is a very critical step in crime scene investigation.<strong> </strong>SupreMEtric has demonstrated that Raman spectroscopy, a nondestructive method for molecular structure analysis and identification based on inelastic laser-light scattering, can produce multidimensional spectroscopic signatures for complex multi-cell biological substances such as blood, semen, saliva, urine, vaginal fluid, and sweat. SupreMEtric is developing a unique, multi-use software platform and an advanced algorithm to identify multi-dimensional signatures of complex bio-substances to &lsquo;recognize&rsquo; bio trace signals on interfering substrates to confirm the presence of a body fluid type vs environmental interference (i.e., nail polish, juice, wine, etc.), and identify the type of fluid present.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In objective 1, we demonstrated and confirmed the earlier finding reported by our laboratory that Raman spectroscopy combined with machine learning is a viable method for confirmatory identification of body fluids for all body fluid types. More specifically, we demonstrated that the method is robust against environmental interferants (EIs), which we considered as potential false positives. Raman Spectra of common EI substances were compared to body fluids and analyzed using the SVMDA algorithm. All EI substances were classified correctly as NOT body fluids. Furthermore, SVMDA could distinguish between the two classes with 99% sensitivity and 90% specificity at the individual spectral level in internal cross-validation. The results were further verified using a strict threshold of 50%, thereby reaching 100% accuracy in classification at the sample level. Therefore, our preliminary conclusion is that Raman spectroscopy detects differences in body fluids&rsquo; biochemical composition and EI substances. Consequently, the proposed method, when fully developed, could be the first rapid tool to be used in a crime scene that would solve the problem of EI (i.e., potential false positive substances) found in crime scenes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>For objective 2, we investigated the application of Raman spectroscopy for the detection and identification of body fluid stains when it is complicated by substrate interference. It is not practical to have a spectral library of common substrates because of the wide variety and significant heterogeneity of substrates that can be found at a crime scene. We conducted a comparative analysis of two approaches for solving this problem:<em> a)</em> considering a substrate as an additional component in a combination &ldquo;sample &amp; substrate,&rdquo; or<em> b)</em> extracting Raman spectra of a target sample from this combination without defining substrate characteristics. The first approach tested was (a) the detection and identification of biological stains on strongly interfering substrates using Raman hyperspectroscopy combined with a newly developed program called multivariate curve resolution combined with the additions method (MCRAD) software. This method extracts the Raman spectroscopic signature of a body fluid trace without utilizing spectroscopic characteristics of the substrate with multivariant curve resolution. MCRAD effectively separates and quantifies the spectral components of known targets in complex overlapping spectra. However, it was our new approach based on reducing a spectrum complexity (RSC) (b) that was more advantageous because prior information about the substrate is not necessary. Overall, we were able to create a method that completely circumvents substrate interference and allows for the identification of biological stains despite complete matrices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In previous objectives, we demonstrated that environmental interferences could be accurately differentiated from all main body fluids using Raman spectroscopy. Along with the fact that the developed statistical approaches (MCRAD and RSC) do not require any knowledge about the substrates indicate that any substrate with an environmental contaminant(s) could be considered as a &ldquo;new substrate.&rdquo; As a result, for objective 3 it might NOT be needed to build a new machine-learning algorithm that considers interfering substrates and potential environmental interference since the developed MCRAD and RSC methods should work well for these &ldquo;new substrates.&rdquo;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, we use an optical objective and a confocal microscope to collect Raman scattered light, that means that we collect it from a micrometer-size spot corresponding to roughly a femtoliter volume containing a picogram of material. We have demonstrated that high-quality Raman spectra could be measured from a single red blood cell and result in a confident identification of blood. One can estimate that the amount of blood containing in average one red blood cell is thousands of times smaller than that needed for DNA profiling. The latter means that if there is enough blood for the DNA profiling then Raman spectroscopy can identify it easily.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Alexis&nbsp;R&nbsp;Weber</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The body fluid traces recovered at crime scenes are among the most important types of evidence to forensic investigators. Conventional methods of body fluid identification use labor-intensive, technologically diverse methods that are performed one after the other and are costly in both time and sample usage. The objectives of any crime scene investigation are to preserve physical evidence and collect only valuable evidence for the analytical examination. Therefore, the ability to characterize an unknown stain at the scene of the crime without destruction and having to wait for laboratory results is a very critical step in crime scene investigation. SupreMEtric has demonstrated that Raman spectroscopy, a nondestructive method for molecular structure analysis and identification based on inelastic laser-light scattering, can produce multidimensional spectroscopic signatures for complex multi-cell biological substances such as blood, semen, saliva, urine, vaginal fluid, and sweat. SupreMEtric is developing a unique, multi-use software platform and an advanced algorithm to identify multi-dimensional signatures of complex bio-substances to ‘recognize’ bio trace signals on interfering substrates to confirm the presence of a body fluid type vs environmental interference (i.e., nail polish, juice, wine, etc.), and identify the type of fluid present.     In objective 1, we demonstrated and confirmed the earlier finding reported by our laboratory that Raman spectroscopy combined with machine learning is a viable method for confirmatory identification of body fluids for all body fluid types. More specifically, we demonstrated that the method is robust against environmental interferants (EIs), which we considered as potential false positives. Raman Spectra of common EI substances were compared to body fluids and analyzed using the SVMDA algorithm. All EI substances were classified correctly as NOT body fluids. Furthermore, SVMDA could distinguish between the two classes with 99% sensitivity and 90% specificity at the individual spectral level in internal cross-validation. The results were further verified using a strict threshold of 50%, thereby reaching 100% accuracy in classification at the sample level. Therefore, our preliminary conclusion is that Raman spectroscopy detects differences in body fluids’ biochemical composition and EI substances. Consequently, the proposed method, when fully developed, could be the first rapid tool to be used in a crime scene that would solve the problem of EI (i.e., potential false positive substances) found in crime scenes.     For objective 2, we investigated the application of Raman spectroscopy for the detection and identification of body fluid stains when it is complicated by substrate interference. It is not practical to have a spectral library of common substrates because of the wide variety and significant heterogeneity of substrates that can be found at a crime scene. We conducted a comparative analysis of two approaches for solving this problem: a) considering a substrate as an additional component in a combination "sample &amp; substrate," or b) extracting Raman spectra of a target sample from this combination without defining substrate characteristics. The first approach tested was (a) the detection and identification of biological stains on strongly interfering substrates using Raman hyperspectroscopy combined with a newly developed program called multivariate curve resolution combined with the additions method (MCRAD) software. This method extracts the Raman spectroscopic signature of a body fluid trace without utilizing spectroscopic characteristics of the substrate with multivariant curve resolution. MCRAD effectively separates and quantifies the spectral components of known targets in complex overlapping spectra. However, it was our new approach based on reducing a spectrum complexity (RSC) (b) that was more advantageous because prior information about the substrate is not necessary. Overall, we were able to create a method that completely circumvents substrate interference and allows for the identification of biological stains despite complete matrices.     In previous objectives, we demonstrated that environmental interferences could be accurately differentiated from all main body fluids using Raman spectroscopy. Along with the fact that the developed statistical approaches (MCRAD and RSC) do not require any knowledge about the substrates indicate that any substrate with an environmental contaminant(s) could be considered as a "new substrate." As a result, for objective 3 it might NOT be needed to build a new machine-learning algorithm that considers interfering substrates and potential environmental interference since the developed MCRAD and RSC methods should work well for these "new substrates."     Finally, we use an optical objective and a confocal microscope to collect Raman scattered light, that means that we collect it from a micrometer-size spot corresponding to roughly a femtoliter volume containing a picogram of material. We have demonstrated that high-quality Raman spectra could be measured from a single red blood cell and result in a confident identification of blood. One can estimate that the amount of blood containing in average one red blood cell is thousands of times smaller than that needed for DNA profiling. The latter means that if there is enough blood for the DNA profiling then Raman spectroscopy can identify it easily.       Last Modified: 05/02/2023       Submitted by: Alexis R Weber]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
