<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Sensor-based bra to measure breast milk output and monitor changes in breast volume before and after breastfeeding or breast pumping]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be significant to breastfeeding mothers who experience difficulties producing milk or knowing the volume of milk expressed during each session. While the benefits of breastfeeding throughout the first year of a baby’s life are widely accepted in the medical community, 60% of mothers do not succeed in sustained breastfeeding. The success or failure of breastfeeding is dependent upon a baby getting enough milk, and currently there is no objective method of determining the amount of milk a baby is receiving and how much residual milk remains in the breasts. The proposed device will collect objective data that will help mothers overcome challenges in breastfeeding and avoid further complications like clogged ducts and/or mastitis. Specifically, the device will help mothers track their milk output accurately, therefore reaching lactation goals, and allow mothers to ensure that babies receive the required nutrition to thrive during the early stages of life. The depersonalized data collected from the bra will enable medical professionals and researchers to gain insights about human milk production volumes and factors influencing milk production and infant health, thereby expanding horizons for further research in this field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will create a proof-of-concept prototype bra that utilizes textile-based sensors to accurately measure the volume of milk expressed during a breastfeeding/breast pumping session. This project will lay important groundwork to create the first medical device using embedded fabric sensor technology to determine three data points: breast emptiness, milk volume output per session and changes in breast milk production over time. Research will focus on the design of the sensors and the form-factor of the bra that will facilitate capturing accurate data. There will be associated data capture and analysis demonstrating both measurable metric data trends to inform breastfeeding moms and aggregate cohort-level data trends for high level data analysis in an area with a paucity of actual data. When in use, the bra will be fitted to women while breastfeeding or pumping and be able to determine both the milk depletion and residual volume in the milk ducts and the volume of milk produced. After completing additional R&amp;D, the product will perform three different functions: 1) determine the degree of breast emptiness; 2) measure the volume of milk expressed per session; 3) detect early risk of clogged ducts to avoid mastitis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adriana</FirstName>
<LastName>Vazquez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adriana Vazquez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wearlilu@outlook.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836495</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>LILU, INC.</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100181510</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6468251423</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>240 W 40TH ST RM 312</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J78XLFFGAEN3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LILU INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LILU, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>New York City</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100113855</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[447 W 18th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~276000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c49775c7-7fff-6ceb-eedc-9a653ba64a5e"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The research goal for this SBIR Phase 1 project was to test proof-of-concept for the application of &lsquo;a fabric-based sensor integrated into a custom design bra&rsquo; in measuring changes in breast volume. The research carried out was to lay important groundwork to create The Lilu Insights Bra, the first product using fabric sensor technology to determine three data points: breast emptiness, milk volume output per session, and changes in milk volume produced in the breast over time, in order to: a) help breastfeeding mothers track their breast milk output, therefore reaching their lactation goals, and b) allow babies to receive the nourishment and nutrition that they need to thrive during the early stages of life.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The CDC, UNICEF, and the World Health Organization recommend that moms feed their babies breast milk exclusively for the first six months of life. Milk production in general is based upon demand, however, it is very difficult for most women to know when their breasts have fully emptied. This uncertainty frequently leads to stress and doubt that in turn creates even more problems producing milk causing a downward spiral that eventually results in mothers quitting breastfeeding altogether. There is currently no other way for a breastfeeding mom to accurately measure her milk production. The Lilu Insights Bra will give mothers the much needed data to know when their breast has all been emptied while breastfeeding.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In order to achieve our goal, we began by identifying the type of fabric-based sensors that would be suitable for our application. We sourced various fabric based sensor samples from a local sensor manufacturer and ran preliminary tests to see the characteristics of the sensors. We graded these samples on the following&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>(a) Type of construction,&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>(b) Material used in the sensor and&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>(c) Sensitivity and other characteristics of the sensor properties to an external force. We narrowed down the choices to 3 samples. In order to identify the optimum way to integrate the sensors into the bra, we developed test jigs using a phantom lactating breast model and tested the sensors using an &lsquo;off the bra&rsquo;. We &lsquo;inflated&rsquo; and &lsquo;deflated&rsquo; the breast model with liquid to simulate change in breast shape and volume and studied the response of the sensor data over various parts of the breast. This helped us narrow down the patterns of the fabric based sensors that would be integrated into a bra to maximize the efficacy of measuring changes in breast volume.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We then worked with a professional bra designer and specialized manufacturer to develop a custom designed bra to receive the fabric based sensors. We integrated the sensors determined in the preceding tests into the custom bra and ran experiments using the lactating model test jig. We &ldquo;inflated&rdquo; and &ldquo;deflated&rdquo; the breast model with known volume of a liquid in regular intervals and studied the response of the sensors. We repeated this several times to develop an equation between sensor data and amount of liquid displaced in and out of the breast model. </span><span><br /></span><span>Once we developed the equation, we repeated the experiment to test reproducibility and accuracy of the algorithm. Using the Lilu insights Bra prototype and the equation, we successfully detected volumetric changes of 15 ml of liquid in the breast.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Conclusion: We established proof of concept of using fabric-based sensors to measure changes in breast volume. We ran experiments with fabric-based sensors and determined the placement of sensors in the custom designed bra.&nbsp;</span>We determined the location of &lsquo;test points&rsquo; in the breast where the sensors would yield accurate, consistent readings with minimal noise.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Further, we have designed and developed a bra prototype that can be:</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Worn all day.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Converted easily into a nursing bra.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Used to support breast pumping with standard and portable breast pumps.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Tailored for the fabric-based sensors.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>From a technical perspective, we validated that the materials, construction and form factor seem fitting for the use case of breast milk production and output monitoring and successfully achieved our goal of engineering a Proof-of-Concept smart bra to track breast milk output.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition to the technical validation from the experiments, we also participated in the NSF Beat the Odds bootcamp and the supplementary SBIR ICorps program, where we validated &mdash; from over 130 interviews with customers, influencers, and other key stakeholders &mdash; that a device that could automatically track milk production over time and detect abnormalities in milk production that could result in complications, would not only be a key tool in the breastfeeding toolkit for mothers but also be very helpful for lactation experts and other healthcare providers who currently have no reliable means of getting accurate lactations related data from mothers.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In all, it was a resounding &ldquo;Go&rdquo; when time came to decide whether or not this would be a viable technology to develop into a product.&nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Adriana&nbsp;Vazquez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651527881883_testjig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651527881883_testjig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Test jig to simulate a lactating breast."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651527881883_testjig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Test jig to simulate a lactating breast."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A test jig built using a phantom lactating breast model over a mannequin was used to simulate milk production and milk expression in order to test the response of fabric based sensors and efficacy in accurately identifying the volume displaced.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lilu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Adriana&nbsp;Vazquez</div> <div class="imageTitle">Test jig to simulate a lactating breast.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651539041049_Graph--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651539041049_Graph--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Graph showing the predicted characteristics of the sensor vs the actual sensor readings"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651539041049_Graph--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Graph showing the predicted characteristics of the sensor vs the actual sensor readings"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This graph shows the predicted characteristics of the fabric based sensors based on the computer equation, for a given change in volume, vs the actual readings from the sensors. The results showed that the error between the read value and the estimated value was less than 5 percent.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lilu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Adriana&nbsp;Vazquez</div> <div class="imageTitle">Graph showing the predicted characteristics of the sensor vs the actual sensor readings</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651539202779_repeatable--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651539202779_repeatable--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Graph showing repeatability of sensor readings"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2052051/2052051_10729038_1651539202779_repeatable--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Graph showing repeatability of sensor readings"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This plot shows the sensor readings over 2 cycles of inflation and deflation of the breast model. The readings are repeatable and remain accurate over time after multiple cycles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lilu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Adriana&nbsp;Vazquez</div> <div class="imageTitle">Graph showing repeatability of sensor readings</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The research goal for this SBIR Phase 1 project was to test proof-of-concept for the application of ‘a fabric-based sensor integrated into a custom design bra’ in measuring changes in breast volume. The research carried out was to lay important groundwork to create The Lilu Insights Bra, the first product using fabric sensor technology to determine three data points: breast emptiness, milk volume output per session, and changes in milk volume produced in the breast over time, in order to: a) help breastfeeding mothers track their breast milk output, therefore reaching their lactation goals, and b) allow babies to receive the nourishment and nutrition that they need to thrive during the early stages of life. The CDC, UNICEF, and the World Health Organization recommend that moms feed their babies breast milk exclusively for the first six months of life. Milk production in general is based upon demand, however, it is very difficult for most women to know when their breasts have fully emptied. This uncertainty frequently leads to stress and doubt that in turn creates even more problems producing milk causing a downward spiral that eventually results in mothers quitting breastfeeding altogether. There is currently no other way for a breastfeeding mom to accurately measure her milk production. The Lilu Insights Bra will give mothers the much needed data to know when their breast has all been emptied while breastfeeding.   In order to achieve our goal, we began by identifying the type of fabric-based sensors that would be suitable for our application. We sourced various fabric based sensor samples from a local sensor manufacturer and ran preliminary tests to see the characteristics of the sensors. We graded these samples on the following  (a) Type of construction,  (b) Material used in the sensor and  (c) Sensitivity and other characteristics of the sensor properties to an external force. We narrowed down the choices to 3 samples. In order to identify the optimum way to integrate the sensors into the bra, we developed test jigs using a phantom lactating breast model and tested the sensors using an ‘off the bra’. We ‘inflated’ and ‘deflated’ the breast model with liquid to simulate change in breast shape and volume and studied the response of the sensor data over various parts of the breast. This helped us narrow down the patterns of the fabric based sensors that would be integrated into a bra to maximize the efficacy of measuring changes in breast volume.  We then worked with a professional bra designer and specialized manufacturer to develop a custom designed bra to receive the fabric based sensors. We integrated the sensors determined in the preceding tests into the custom bra and ran experiments using the lactating model test jig. We "inflated" and "deflated" the breast model with known volume of a liquid in regular intervals and studied the response of the sensors. We repeated this several times to develop an equation between sensor data and amount of liquid displaced in and out of the breast model.  Once we developed the equation, we repeated the experiment to test reproducibility and accuracy of the algorithm. Using the Lilu insights Bra prototype and the equation, we successfully detected volumetric changes of 15 ml of liquid in the breast.  Conclusion: We established proof of concept of using fabric-based sensors to measure changes in breast volume. We ran experiments with fabric-based sensors and determined the placement of sensors in the custom designed bra. We determined the location of ‘test points’ in the breast where the sensors would yield accurate, consistent readings with minimal noise. Further, we have designed and developed a bra prototype that can be:   Worn all day.   Converted easily into a nursing bra.   Used to support breast pumping with standard and portable breast pumps.    Tailored for the fabric-based sensors.   From a technical perspective, we validated that the materials, construction and form factor seem fitting for the use case of breast milk production and output monitoring and successfully achieved our goal of engineering a Proof-of-Concept smart bra to track breast milk output.    In addition to the technical validation from the experiments, we also participated in the NSF Beat the Odds bootcamp and the supplementary SBIR ICorps program, where we validated &mdash; from over 130 interviews with customers, influencers, and other key stakeholders &mdash; that a device that could automatically track milk production over time and detect abnormalities in milk production that could result in complications, would not only be a key tool in the breastfeeding toolkit for mothers but also be very helpful for lactation experts and other healthcare providers who currently have no reliable means of getting accurate lactations related data from mothers.  In all, it was a resounding "Go" when time came to decide whether or not this would be a viable technology to develop into a product.              Last Modified: 05/02/2022       Submitted by: Adriana Vazquez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
