<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Integrated Technologies for Addressing Environmental Challenges in the Energy Industries]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255597.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255597</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to capture carbon dioxide from the burning of fossil fuels and sequester it safely from the atmosphere. This project uniquely combines two new technologies to eliminate the carbon dioxide emissions resulting from flaring of huge volumes of natural gas in remote oil fields; the technologies burn it in a novel combustion system and uses the generated heat to treat the oil-field produced water. The cooled flue gases of combustion are then injected via a novel process into oilfields for enhancing oil recovery. This makes the entire process economically feasible and environmentally beneficial. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed combustion system involves a novel concept of “Fire-in-Water” to carry out combustion of a fuel directly within a flowing stream of water, thereby enhancing the heat transfer coefficients by several orders of magnitude compared to conventional indirect heat transfer systems involving metallic heat transfer surfaces (such as shell-and-tube heat exchangers) separating the heated and heating media. This project proposes this combustion system to burn natural gas currently wasted through flares in remote oil fields, resolving a major environmental problem facing the industry. The second innovation utilizes the heat generated by combustion of flare-gas in the novel burner to treat oil-field produced water, another long-standing environmental concern. The third innovation uses the flue gas generated by combustion (of flare-gas) for injection into oil fields to produce trapped oil. The project will demonstrate: (1) Successful adoption (through application of combustion, heat transfer and two-phase flow principles) of the combustor design from steam generator to flue gas generator; (2) The combustor’s ability to burn flare-gas of varying hydrocarbon contents and compositions; (3) The ability to treat oil-field produced water; (4) Field-scale viability; and (5) Mathematical models and computer simulations for implementation and process scale-up.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052367</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shyamsundar</FirstName>
<LastName>Chattanathan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shyamsundar Chattanathan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shyam.chattanathan@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000837569</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/13/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohammad</FirstName>
<LastName>Kazemi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohammad R Kazemi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[morkazemi@yahoo.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000855478</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/21/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Boyapati</FirstName>
<LastName>Sekar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Boyapati K Sekar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bksekar@directcombustiontech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000860499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>DIRECT COMBUSTION TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708205023</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2252410303</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6307 BELLE GROVE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RJE9G1WPGEN6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DIRECT COMBUSTION TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[DIRECT COMBUSTION TECHNOLOGIES, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708205023</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255597</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main objective of this SBIR Phase-1 R&amp;D project conducted by Direct Combustion Technologies, LLC (DCT) was to design novel processes, by uniquely combining the patented HydroFlame (HF) process and the patented Gas-Assisted Gravity Drainage (GAGD) process, to bring long-term environmental solutions to the Oil &amp; Gas industry by resolving long-existing problems of: (1) flaring of large quantities of natural gas in innumerable oil fields around the country and the world, (2) treating huge amounts of oil-field produced waters to enable their reuse, and (3) improving the low oil recoveries that the current enhanced oil recovery (EOR) processes are yielding - thereby providing a huge economic incentive to the energy industry to embrace these novel concepts and processes being proposed for further research and development in our Phase-2 proposal. With the Phase-I financial support from NSF SBIR program, DCT is a step closer to achieving this objective. This Phase-1 research study has successfully accomplished all the five objectives (and their corresponding tasks) listed in the original proposal by developing: (1) a chemical process model for using the HydroFlame's Fire-in-Water concept for treatment of oil-field produced waters and flue gas generation along with their detailed heat and material balances, (2) a Computational Fluid Dynamics and Combustion (CFDC) model for scaling up the HydroFlame process for flue gas generation at scale needed for oil-field implementation, and (3) a reservoir simulation case study of a selected reservoir in Louisiana that has successfully demonstrated the possibility of enhancing oil recovery by 3 to 4 folds compared to current industry practice.</p> <p>HydroFlame is a novel combustion process for burning natural gas directly in a flowing stream of water. Since the flame and water are in direct contact, heat transfer coefficients are increased by several orders of magnitude compared to conventional shell-and-tube heat exchangers, thereby not only eliminating the need for expensive metallic combustors but also enabling the design and development of a very compact and mobile (skid- or trailer-mounted) burner for flue gas generation for use in oil fields - which is one of the main objectives of DCT's Phase-II application.</p> <p>The GAGD process deviates from the current industry practice of horizontal displacement of gas-oil mixture in the reservoir to a vertical one. The current industry practice (WAG and CGI technologies) is an effort to fight with natural forces of gravity while GAGD takes advantage of natural gravity segregation of fluids. This ?working-with-nature? concept of GAGD process has enabled it to yield consistently high oil recoveries (65%-95%) in various pilot experiments compared to 5%-10% recoveries using conventional practice in 59 field projects. The flue gas produced by HF process is injected in the vertical wells which then accumulates at the top of the payzone due to gravity segregation displacing oil downwards and draining vertically to the horizontal producing well located at the bottom of the payzone. The gravity segregation also helps in eliminating gas breakthrough and preventing the gas phase from competing for flow with the oil resulting in higher oil production rates. Thus, this unique combination of HF and GAGD technologies, is expected to enable a long-awaited solution to (1) eliminating flares and CO2 emissions, (2) cost-effective produced water recycling, and (3) problem of low oil recoveries.</p> <p><span>This SBIR Phase-1 research study conducted by DCT has successfully demonstrated that it is feasible to successfully integrate the HydroFlame and Gas-Assisted Gravity Drainage processes to address the environmental challenges, namely of produced water handling, natural gas flaring and low recoveries, facing the energy industry. Additioanlly, by optimizing the field implementation parameters and strategies, the combination of these two technologies (HydroFlame and Gas-Assited Gravity Drainage) have been demonstrated by our Phase-I research to yield 3-4 folds higher recovery factors and economic enhancements than the current industry practice while simultaneously sequestering large quantities of CO2 in the reservoir.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>Significant opportunities to implement the Phase-I research findings in petroleum reservoirs located in Louisiana, Texas and Nevada have been identified, and discussions with the owners of these fields are underway for their participation in our planned Phase-2 study. Thus, the accomplished success of our Phase-I study has enabled DCT to make a strong and compelling SBIR Phase-II proposal in 2023.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Boyapati&nbsp;K&nbsp;Sekar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main objective of this SBIR Phase-1 R&amp;D project conducted by Direct Combustion Technologies, LLC (DCT) was to design novel processes, by uniquely combining the patented HydroFlame (HF) process and the patented Gas-Assisted Gravity Drainage (GAGD) process, to bring long-term environmental solutions to the Oil &amp; Gas industry by resolving long-existing problems of: (1) flaring of large quantities of natural gas in innumerable oil fields around the country and the world, (2) treating huge amounts of oil-field produced waters to enable their reuse, and (3) improving the low oil recoveries that the current enhanced oil recovery (EOR) processes are yielding - thereby providing a huge economic incentive to the energy industry to embrace these novel concepts and processes being proposed for further research and development in our Phase-2 proposal. With the Phase-I financial support from NSF SBIR program, DCT is a step closer to achieving this objective. This Phase-1 research study has successfully accomplished all the five objectives (and their corresponding tasks) listed in the original proposal by developing: (1) a chemical process model for using the HydroFlame's Fire-in-Water concept for treatment of oil-field produced waters and flue gas generation along with their detailed heat and material balances, (2) a Computational Fluid Dynamics and Combustion (CFDC) model for scaling up the HydroFlame process for flue gas generation at scale needed for oil-field implementation, and (3) a reservoir simulation case study of a selected reservoir in Louisiana that has successfully demonstrated the possibility of enhancing oil recovery by 3 to 4 folds compared to current industry practice.  HydroFlame is a novel combustion process for burning natural gas directly in a flowing stream of water. Since the flame and water are in direct contact, heat transfer coefficients are increased by several orders of magnitude compared to conventional shell-and-tube heat exchangers, thereby not only eliminating the need for expensive metallic combustors but also enabling the design and development of a very compact and mobile (skid- or trailer-mounted) burner for flue gas generation for use in oil fields - which is one of the main objectives of DCT's Phase-II application.  The GAGD process deviates from the current industry practice of horizontal displacement of gas-oil mixture in the reservoir to a vertical one. The current industry practice (WAG and CGI technologies) is an effort to fight with natural forces of gravity while GAGD takes advantage of natural gravity segregation of fluids. This ?working-with-nature? concept of GAGD process has enabled it to yield consistently high oil recoveries (65%-95%) in various pilot experiments compared to 5%-10% recoveries using conventional practice in 59 field projects. The flue gas produced by HF process is injected in the vertical wells which then accumulates at the top of the payzone due to gravity segregation displacing oil downwards and draining vertically to the horizontal producing well located at the bottom of the payzone. The gravity segregation also helps in eliminating gas breakthrough and preventing the gas phase from competing for flow with the oil resulting in higher oil production rates. Thus, this unique combination of HF and GAGD technologies, is expected to enable a long-awaited solution to (1) eliminating flares and CO2 emissions, (2) cost-effective produced water recycling, and (3) problem of low oil recoveries.  This SBIR Phase-1 research study conducted by DCT has successfully demonstrated that it is feasible to successfully integrate the HydroFlame and Gas-Assisted Gravity Drainage processes to address the environmental challenges, namely of produced water handling, natural gas flaring and low recoveries, facing the energy industry. Additioanlly, by optimizing the field implementation parameters and strategies, the combination of these two technologies (HydroFlame and Gas-Assited Gravity Drainage) have been demonstrated by our Phase-I research to yield 3-4 folds higher recovery factors and economic enhancements than the current industry practice while simultaneously sequestering large quantities of CO2 in the reservoir.   Significant opportunities to implement the Phase-I research findings in petroleum reservoirs located in Louisiana, Texas and Nevada have been identified, and discussions with the owners of these fields are underway for their participation in our planned Phase-2 study. Thus, the accomplished success of our Phase-I study has enabled DCT to make a strong and compelling SBIR Phase-II proposal in 2023.        Last Modified: 04/11/2023       Submitted by: Boyapati K Sekar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
