<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Mobile Produced Water Recycling for Reducing Costs in Natural Gas Production]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to realize significant cost savings for domestic natural gas producers, enabled by recycling wastewater that would otherwise be disposed of via expensive transportation and permanent injection into the ground. While the domestic production of natural gas is a central pillar in the transition to a cleaner energy economy, a detrimental by-product is contaminated wastewater, known as produced water, which comes to the surface in large volumes mixed with the gas. In regions such as the Marcellus Basin, the largest natural gas reserve in the United States, the only viable option is to truck this water long distances to disposal wells, where it is re-injected, for a cost that comprises large portions of the operational budget. By developing a new technology for the treatment and re-use of this water at the well-site, this project aims to provide a low-cost, environmentally sustainable solution. Doing so would reduce water management costs as much as 50%, lowering gas production costs, and conserving billions gallons of water through re-use that would otherwise be lost.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project aims to develop a new type of filtration membrane technology capable of removing critical contaminants from produced water, while providing the required durability, minimal footprint, mobility, and feasible cost to enable commercial water recycling for natural gas producers. Currently, no suitable technical solution exists for the economical recycling of produced water. This project focuses on a new type of ultra-durable silicon membrane that combines the filtration ability and low-cost of polymeric membranes with the resilience of ceramic. Through the strategic manipulation of the membrane fabrication approach, including catalyst deposition and chemical etching process parameters, efforts will focus on reducing pore size and increasing pore density in the membrane. The primary objective of the work is to enable the removal of critical contaminants from produced water, and to maximize filtration throughput in order to ensure a small footprint. Successful completion of the project will result in the advancement of the technology to the field-testing stage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052127</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brendan</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brendan D Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bsmith@sitration.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SITRATION, INC.</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>02139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8572347033</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>45 PROSPECT ST MA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XN36QDQRSAD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SITRATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sitration, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021392402</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[45 Prospect St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this NSF Phase I SBIR project, SiTration developed a technology to lower the cost for treating and recycling produced water in the oil and gas industry. The primary outcome of this work is the significant advancement of SiTration's silicon filtration membrane technology towards commercial viability. Key results include an increase in membrane thickness by an order of magnitude to enable mechanical stability in large membranes, a substantial improvement in membrane permeability to achieve industrially-viable throughput, and the demonstration of filtration rejection for a key contaminant present in produced water. These outcomes position SiTration well for further development, scale up, and commercialization of the silicon filtration membrane technology in the oil and gas industry and other impactful industrial applications.&nbsp;</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this project was the development of an extensive toolkit for controlling the structure and performance of SiTration's silicon membrane technology via a number of key fabrication parameters. Through the tuning and optimization of feedstock silicon type, fabrication catalyst type and morphology, and chemical etching etchant composition and concentration, critical improvements were made to membrane performance. These outcomes were amplified by the invention of a modified membrane architecture that circumvents fundamental tradeoffs between membrane thickness, permeability, and rejection to produce a membrane that combines performance and mechanical stability. The result of these advancements was a demonstration of partial rejection of magnesium sulfate, an important contaminant in produced water. In addition, both permeability and thickness of the silicon membrane were increased by roughly an order of magnitude from their baseline values, opening the door for future high-throughput, large-scale industrial implementation.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of this work center around the advancement of a robust, scalable, and mobile filtration technology capable of processing challenging industrial streams. In the oil and gas industry, the silicon membrane technology developed in this project stands to create positive impact through cost-effective and sustainable treatment and recycling of the large volumes of oil and gas wastewater produced both within the United States and elsewhere. Societal and environmental benefits include a reduction in the release of contaminated water near production sites, as well as the potential to re-use recycled water in oil and gas operations, thereby minimizing fresh water consumption. More broadly, the silicon filtration membrane technology is applicable to adjacent applications, including treatment of other difficult industrial waste streams and high-value separations such as the recovery of critical materials in lithium-ion battery recycling or mining. Finally, the technical development enabled by this project is catalyzing the expansion of a highly technical and domestic workforce, serving to strengthen the economy of the United States.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Brendan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this NSF Phase I SBIR project, SiTration developed a technology to lower the cost for treating and recycling produced water in the oil and gas industry. The primary outcome of this work is the significant advancement of SiTration's silicon filtration membrane technology towards commercial viability. Key results include an increase in membrane thickness by an order of magnitude to enable mechanical stability in large membranes, a substantial improvement in membrane permeability to achieve industrially-viable throughput, and the demonstration of filtration rejection for a key contaminant present in produced water. These outcomes position SiTration well for further development, scale up, and commercialization of the silicon filtration membrane technology in the oil and gas industry and other impactful industrial applications.   The intellectual merit of this project was the development of an extensive toolkit for controlling the structure and performance of SiTration's silicon membrane technology via a number of key fabrication parameters. Through the tuning and optimization of feedstock silicon type, fabrication catalyst type and morphology, and chemical etching etchant composition and concentration, critical improvements were made to membrane performance. These outcomes were amplified by the invention of a modified membrane architecture that circumvents fundamental tradeoffs between membrane thickness, permeability, and rejection to produce a membrane that combines performance and mechanical stability. The result of these advancements was a demonstration of partial rejection of magnesium sulfate, an important contaminant in produced water. In addition, both permeability and thickness of the silicon membrane were increased by roughly an order of magnitude from their baseline values, opening the door for future high-throughput, large-scale industrial implementation.   The broader impacts of this work center around the advancement of a robust, scalable, and mobile filtration technology capable of processing challenging industrial streams. In the oil and gas industry, the silicon membrane technology developed in this project stands to create positive impact through cost-effective and sustainable treatment and recycling of the large volumes of oil and gas wastewater produced both within the United States and elsewhere. Societal and environmental benefits include a reduction in the release of contaminated water near production sites, as well as the potential to re-use recycled water in oil and gas operations, thereby minimizing fresh water consumption. More broadly, the silicon filtration membrane technology is applicable to adjacent applications, including treatment of other difficult industrial waste streams and high-value separations such as the recovery of critical materials in lithium-ion battery recycling or mining. Finally, the technical development enabled by this project is catalyzing the expansion of a highly technical and domestic workforce, serving to strengthen the economy of the United States.           Last Modified: 05/31/2023       Submitted by: Brendan D Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
