<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Light-Driven Conversion of CO2 and Methane to Syngas and Methanol]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>961378.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>961378</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is that this technology represents a commercially feasible pathway to reduce and utilize greenhouse gas emissions (CO2 and methane) in the sector of chemicals manufacturing. This new chemical reactor technology will enable utilization of waste CO2 from industrial processes, renewable natural gas, and renewable electricity as feedstocks to produce a carbon-negative commodity chemical such as methanol. The proposed reactor runs on electricity, not fuel, creating novel business model opportunities. One example is building and selling small-scale, distributed methanol production plants that can utilize intermittent renewable electricity sources for their energy source. Large industrial plants, such as refineries, that have a source of waste CO2 can utilize the proposed technology to make and sell methanol. Moreover, this reactor uses methane, which is a plentiful domestic natural resource.  One pressing environmental problem that this technology could address is natural gas flaring in the oil and gas industry.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase II project proposes to demonstrate a scaled up photocatalytic dry methane-reforming (P-DMR) reactor system that consumes carbon dioxide and methane to produce green methanol. In the NSF Phase I project, a proof-of-concept bench-scale photo-chemical reactor was developed. This photo-chemical reactor uses electricity, not fuel, as energy input to operate. The P-DMR photocatalyst is energized with high-efficiency LEDs. The Phase II project will demonstrate a scaled-up photo-chemical reactor for P-DMR that consumes 17 kg/day of CO2 and 6 kg/day of CH4, integrate this photo-reactor to a water gas shift reactor and a methanol synthesis reactor to produce 5 kg/day of green methanol. A steady-state process model and a techno-economic model for a 1 barrel/day methanol production plant will be built as a demonstration prior to a commercialization plant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052133</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shreya</FirstName>
<LastName>Shah</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shreya Shah</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shreya@plasmonics.tech]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000783505</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syzygy Plasmonics Inc</Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>770542504</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8064705779</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9000 KIRBY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U9DMYKWDZAC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYZYGY PLASMONICS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syzygy Plasmonics Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770542504</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9000 Kirby Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9223</Code>
<Text>ENVIRON BENIGN CHEMICAL SYNTH &amp; PROCESS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~961378</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Title</strong>: Light-Driven Conversion of CO<sub>2</sub> and Methane to Syngas and Methanol</p> <p><strong>Project Duration</strong>: May 1, 2021 - May 31, 2023</p> <p><strong>Principal Investigator</strong>: Dr. Shreya Shah</p> <p><strong>Institution</strong>: Syzygy Plasmonics, INC</p> <p><strong>Award Number</strong>: 2052133</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong>:</p> <p>The main objective of this funded project was to explore an electrified light-driven process that converts two potent greenhouse gases (carbon dioxide and methane) into valuable chemicals (syngas and methanol) in a continuous integrated process. The process involves two major reaction steps; conversion of CO<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> into synthesis gas (CO and H<sub>2</sub>) by using Syzygy&rsquo;s novel photocatalyst and photoreactor, followed by a secondary reactor to convert synthesis gas directly into methanol. The project sought to address the urgent need for reducing greenhouse gas emissions and transitioning towards a carbon-neutral energy economy, and carbon-negative chemical production through the development of paradigm changing electrified chemical conversion technologies.</p> <p><strong>Project Objectives and Deliverables</strong>:</p> <ul> <li>Develop a novel photocatalyst for efficient conversion of CO<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> through photocatalytic dry methane reforming reaction pathway to produce syngas of desired grade (H<sub>2</sub> and CO).</li> <li>Scale up the production of the photocatalyst from the laboratory to the kilogram scale. Design and develop a safe and robust photocatalyst testing system to enable exploration and optimization of the catalyst and photocatalytic reactor.</li> <li>Design and develop an optimized integrated process that converts syngas produced into methanol.</li> <li>Study in detail the techno-economic implications of various pathways to methanol from CO<sub>2</sub> that utilize Syzygy&rsquo;s novel photocatalytic technologies. </li> <li>Provide opportunities to level up subject matter expertise and a platform to disseminate learnings to academia and industry to advance development of carbon-negative electrified chemical conversion technologies.</li> </ul> <p>The successful outcomes of this project have significant implications for sustainable energy and chemical production. The developed greenhouse-gases-to-methanol conversion technology offers the following potential benefits:</p> <ul> <li>Renewable Chemical Source: Methanol produced from CO<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> can serve as a clean and renewable chemical building block and reduce dependence on petroleum-derived feedstocks.</li> <li>Energy Storage and Distribution: Methanol can be used as a versatile energy storage medium and a transportation fuel, facilitating the integration of intermittent renewable energy sources into the grid and supporting the transition to a sustainable energy system.</li> <li>Economic Opportunities: The commercialization of greenhouse-gases-to-methanol conversion technology can create new job opportunities, stimulate innovation, and foster economic growth in the renewable chemicals manufacturing sector.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong>:</p> <p>The light-driven CO<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> conversion to Methanol project funded by the National Science Foundation has successfully achieved its objectives of developing for the first time an efficient, scalable, and economically viable light-driven methanol production process. Carrying out the tasks pertaining to the project has helped Syzygy level up its P-DMT technology exponentially, gaining invaluable insight into the operating capabilities of the catalyst in being able to efficiently convert potent greenhouse gases into useful chemicals, that can otherwise be used as feedstocks for other commodity chemicals &ndash; such as methanol. Additionally, this project also helped us to identify and understand the shortcomings of testing at the small-scale and giving us a path-forward when designing processes at the larger scale (process design, gas compressors, process optimization etc.).</p> <p>The project's outcomes have the potential to revolutionize the energy landscape by providing a sustainable solution for reducing carbon emissions. The dissemination of knowledge and engagement with stakeholders has allowed Syzygy to continue this research and execute external partnerships with major Fortune 500 sponsors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Shreya&nbsp;Shah</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Title: Light-Driven Conversion of CO2 and Methane to Syngas and Methanol  Project Duration: May 1, 2021 - May 31, 2023  Principal Investigator: Dr. Shreya Shah  Institution: Syzygy Plasmonics, INC  Award Number: 2052133  Summary:  The main objective of this funded project was to explore an electrified light-driven process that converts two potent greenhouse gases (carbon dioxide and methane) into valuable chemicals (syngas and methanol) in a continuous integrated process. The process involves two major reaction steps; conversion of CO2 and CH4 into synthesis gas (CO and H2) by using Syzygy’s novel photocatalyst and photoreactor, followed by a secondary reactor to convert synthesis gas directly into methanol. The project sought to address the urgent need for reducing greenhouse gas emissions and transitioning towards a carbon-neutral energy economy, and carbon-negative chemical production through the development of paradigm changing electrified chemical conversion technologies.  Project Objectives and Deliverables:  Develop a novel photocatalyst for efficient conversion of CO2 and CH4 through photocatalytic dry methane reforming reaction pathway to produce syngas of desired grade (H2 and CO). Scale up the production of the photocatalyst from the laboratory to the kilogram scale. Design and develop a safe and robust photocatalyst testing system to enable exploration and optimization of the catalyst and photocatalytic reactor. Design and develop an optimized integrated process that converts syngas produced into methanol. Study in detail the techno-economic implications of various pathways to methanol from CO2 that utilize Syzygy’s novel photocatalytic technologies.  Provide opportunities to level up subject matter expertise and a platform to disseminate learnings to academia and industry to advance development of carbon-negative electrified chemical conversion technologies.   The successful outcomes of this project have significant implications for sustainable energy and chemical production. The developed greenhouse-gases-to-methanol conversion technology offers the following potential benefits:  Renewable Chemical Source: Methanol produced from CO2 and CH4 can serve as a clean and renewable chemical building block and reduce dependence on petroleum-derived feedstocks. Energy Storage and Distribution: Methanol can be used as a versatile energy storage medium and a transportation fuel, facilitating the integration of intermittent renewable energy sources into the grid and supporting the transition to a sustainable energy system. Economic Opportunities: The commercialization of greenhouse-gases-to-methanol conversion technology can create new job opportunities, stimulate innovation, and foster economic growth in the renewable chemicals manufacturing sector.   Conclusion:  The light-driven CO2 and CH4 conversion to Methanol project funded by the National Science Foundation has successfully achieved its objectives of developing for the first time an efficient, scalable, and economically viable light-driven methanol production process. Carrying out the tasks pertaining to the project has helped Syzygy level up its P-DMT technology exponentially, gaining invaluable insight into the operating capabilities of the catalyst in being able to efficiently convert potent greenhouse gases into useful chemicals, that can otherwise be used as feedstocks for other commodity chemicals &ndash; such as methanol. Additionally, this project also helped us to identify and understand the shortcomings of testing at the small-scale and giving us a path-forward when designing processes at the larger scale (process design, gas compressors, process optimization etc.).  The project's outcomes have the potential to revolutionize the energy landscape by providing a sustainable solution for reducing carbon emissions. The dissemination of knowledge and engagement with stakeholders has allowed Syzygy to continue this research and execute external partnerships with major Fortune 500 sponsors.             Last Modified: 06/01/2023       Submitted by: Shreya Shah]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
