<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Pulsed Electric Field Mediated Intradermal Vaccine Delivery (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255930.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255930</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact / commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of more efficient delivery techniques for specific vaccines. The proposed technology increases the efficiency of DNA vaccine delivery while improving patient safety and reducing unwanted cell death. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will address the need for innovative technologies for administering DNA vaccines. Among the vaccines in development, DNA vaccines are particularly promising as they have the potential to induce positive humoral and cellular immune responses, avoid anti-vector immunity challenges, are easily scaled for production, and are stable at room temperature; However, these vaccines require an additional assist to transport the large DNA molecules into target cells. The proposed research will demonstrate the feasibility of a new approach to vaccine delivery which utilizes ultrashort electrical pulses to safely and effectively enhance DNA vaccine delivery in clinically relevant volumes of sub-dermal tissue. The scope of the proposed research includes designing a new pulse generation topology based around cutting edge transistors and evaluating previously unachievable waveforms in an in vitro skin model. Data from these experiments will then be used in computational multiphysics simulations to optimize the design of clinical applicators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052126</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Sano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Sano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbsano@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000647224</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/25/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>DeWitt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew R DeWitt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dewittm@gradient-medical.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000853591</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>GRADIENT MEDICAL, INC.</Name>
<CityName>CARY</CityName>
<ZipCode>275196913</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5188593798</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 SUGAR HILL PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HPZ7FS9MF8J1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GRADIENT MEDICAL INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[GRADIENT MEDICAL, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Cary</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275196913</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 SUGAR HILL PL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255930</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Gradient Medical is focused on the development of novel biomedical instrumentation utilizing pulsed electric fields to enable next generation therapeutics through optimized delivery and simplified clinical implementation of electroporation. Through our ACE technology, we will empower scientists, clinicians, and biotechnology developers to deliver safer, more predictable genetic engineering and novel therapies with algorithm-driven electroporation.&nbsp;</p> <p>DNA vaccines have the potential to expand the recent progress in the field of nucleic acid-based agents, which demonstrated promising rapid development and production capabilities to promptly respond to emerging diseases such as SARS-CoV-2. Like mRNA, DNA vaccines offer the same primary advantages of rapid development but offer superior thermostability for simplified worldwide distribution and do not require lipid nanoparticles for encapsulation. Despite advantages, DNA vaccine translation has been limited by poor cellular uptake <em>in vivo,</em> which requires the use of electroporation to transiently increase DNA transfection for antigen production.</p> <p>Algorithmically controlled electroporation (ACE) is a new technique for intradermal gene and vaccine delivery that is specifically designed to alleviate challenges associated with traditional DNA delivery technologies and enable next generation DNA prophylactics and therapeutics.&nbsp; The goal of this project was to demonstrate the feasibility of ACE for improving DNA vaccines and prepare for future clinical and commercial success of a medical device that delivers ACE for intradermal DNA transfection.</p> <p>Over the course of this Phase I project, the Gradient Medical team accomplished successful plasmid DNA transfection in multiple cell lines, demonstrating the feasibility of novel ACE waveforms to transiently increase cellular uptake of plasmid DNA. We completed the optimization of ACE waveforms through multiple <em>in vitro</em> and <em>in silico</em> models and discovered novel ACE waveforms that result in improved transfection. Specifically, we tested over 200 unique ACE waveform combinations in a high-throughput 3D <em>in vitro</em> tissue mimic to determine reversible and lethal electric field thresholds and down-selected waveforms that eventually produced over 500x DNA transfection compared to controls. Gradient Medical designed and prototyped high voltage pulse generators required for the microsecond pulsed electric fields and temperature control utilized during ACE. After demonstrating the ability to deliver high voltage pulses with our designed-for-manufacturing custom electronics developed in this Phase I, Gradient developed multiple applicators to deliver ACE pulses intradermally and utilized complex finite element computational modeling to predict treatment volumes and ensure safety <em>in vivo</em>. Gradient utilized rapid prototyping to develop applicators that will be utilized in Phase II <em>in vivo</em> validation studies. Moreover, through customer discovery efforts accomplished in the I-Corps process carried out during this Phase I, we identified strategic pre-clinical and clinical partners in the DNA vaccine market to collaborate and translate this technology through the Phase II and beyond.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Phase I research will have important broader impacts in the field of electroporation. ACE has the potential for gene delivery as demonstrated feasible in this project, but has additional significant promise as a non-thermal tissue ablation technology. Efforts to improve the clinical implementation of electroporation through optimizing ACE waveforms and devices will extend the technology to multiple potential therapeutic and prophylactic targets where the unique energy of ACE will enable ablative energy to be delivered. The advancement and eventual commercialization of ACE will allow options for numerous patients that are currently underserved.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/23/2023<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;R&nbsp;Dewitt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Gradient Medical is focused on the development of novel biomedical instrumentation utilizing pulsed electric fields to enable next generation therapeutics through optimized delivery and simplified clinical implementation of electroporation. Through our ACE technology, we will empower scientists, clinicians, and biotechnology developers to deliver safer, more predictable genetic engineering and novel therapies with algorithm-driven electroporation.   DNA vaccines have the potential to expand the recent progress in the field of nucleic acid-based agents, which demonstrated promising rapid development and production capabilities to promptly respond to emerging diseases such as SARS-CoV-2. Like mRNA, DNA vaccines offer the same primary advantages of rapid development but offer superior thermostability for simplified worldwide distribution and do not require lipid nanoparticles for encapsulation. Despite advantages, DNA vaccine translation has been limited by poor cellular uptake in vivo, which requires the use of electroporation to transiently increase DNA transfection for antigen production.  Algorithmically controlled electroporation (ACE) is a new technique for intradermal gene and vaccine delivery that is specifically designed to alleviate challenges associated with traditional DNA delivery technologies and enable next generation DNA prophylactics and therapeutics.  The goal of this project was to demonstrate the feasibility of ACE for improving DNA vaccines and prepare for future clinical and commercial success of a medical device that delivers ACE for intradermal DNA transfection.  Over the course of this Phase I project, the Gradient Medical team accomplished successful plasmid DNA transfection in multiple cell lines, demonstrating the feasibility of novel ACE waveforms to transiently increase cellular uptake of plasmid DNA. We completed the optimization of ACE waveforms through multiple in vitro and in silico models and discovered novel ACE waveforms that result in improved transfection. Specifically, we tested over 200 unique ACE waveform combinations in a high-throughput 3D in vitro tissue mimic to determine reversible and lethal electric field thresholds and down-selected waveforms that eventually produced over 500x DNA transfection compared to controls. Gradient Medical designed and prototyped high voltage pulse generators required for the microsecond pulsed electric fields and temperature control utilized during ACE. After demonstrating the ability to deliver high voltage pulses with our designed-for-manufacturing custom electronics developed in this Phase I, Gradient developed multiple applicators to deliver ACE pulses intradermally and utilized complex finite element computational modeling to predict treatment volumes and ensure safety in vivo. Gradient utilized rapid prototyping to develop applicators that will be utilized in Phase II in vivo validation studies. Moreover, through customer discovery efforts accomplished in the I-Corps process carried out during this Phase I, we identified strategic pre-clinical and clinical partners in the DNA vaccine market to collaborate and translate this technology through the Phase II and beyond.     The Phase I research will have important broader impacts in the field of electroporation. ACE has the potential for gene delivery as demonstrated feasible in this project, but has additional significant promise as a non-thermal tissue ablation technology. Efforts to improve the clinical implementation of electroporation through optimizing ACE waveforms and devices will extend the technology to multiple potential therapeutic and prophylactic targets where the unique energy of ACE will enable ablative energy to be delivered. The advancement and eventual commercialization of ACE will allow options for numerous patients that are currently underserved.       Last Modified: 01/23/2023       Submitted by: Matthew R Dewitt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
