<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Energy Harvesting Using Protein Nanostructures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255703.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255703</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to demonstrate proof-of-concept for a new clean energy technology that uses protein nanostructures to serve as a safe alternative, or supplement, to traditional batteries. The goal is to create power units that are 100% recyclable, preventing toxic electronic waste from accumulating in landfills, and that generate continuous power, reducing the direct and labor costs associated with replacing traditional batteries.  These costs are a significant hurdle that slows the widespread adoption and use of low-power, high-value electronics such as networks of industrial Internet of Things (IoT) sensors.  The project may also address applications, such a flammable gas sensors, where traditional batteries are not typically used to due to safety concerns.  This Phase 1 project is focused on the initial development of a safe and sustainable replacement for batteries using a technology that provides continuous renewable energy and is made with non-toxic recyclable materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merits of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project focuses on developing a prototype device that uses protein nanostructures to generate clean power by means of a new method of energy harvesting that leverages environmental humidity. The research objectives are to (i) fabricate standardized, reliable and reproducible testbed devices; (ii) demonstrate the feasibility of commercial-scale production of a range of protein nanostructures; and (iii) to evaluate these protein nanostructures using our testbed devices. The testbed prototype devices will be made using commercially scalable processes. Devices made using the protein nanostructures will be evaluated using electrochemical and electronic characterization techniques.  The goals of the project are to successfully fabricate thin-film power generation devices, prove commercial-scale production of protein nanostructures, evaluate the power output, and demonstrate a novel mechanism of action of power generation from the devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052263</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander F Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alex@powerforhumanity.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000852501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>POWER FOR HUMANITY, INC.</Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>010022240</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7813300064</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>272 AMITY ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RHNADLWLF655</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>POWER FOR HUMANITY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[POWER FOR HUMANITY, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Somerville</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021433260</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[444 Somerville Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>POWER, CONTROLS &amp; ADAPTIVE NET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255703</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Topic name</strong>: Energy Technology (EN). <strong>Sub-topic name</strong>: EN2. Energy Production and Power Generation</p> <p>This NSF SBIR Phase I project was focused on developing a bio-based ink used to fabricate a cathode coating to make metal-air batteries more energy-efficient and longer-lasting. This is accomplished by integrating the coating into existing battery systems to improve their key performance metrics, specifically current density, coulombic efficiency, discharge voltage, and discharge capacity. During Phase I, it was demonstrated that using a bio-based coating could improve the performance of metal-air battery prototypes made in our lab. This research enabled us to form partnerships with metal-air battery manufacturers that are potential customers for our ink. We are currently in the process of evaluating the viability of our technology once integrated into commercially relevant systems through our partnerships.</p> <p>Batteries are crucial for storing energy needed to power electronics and enabling the use of intermittent renewable energy sources. With the rising demand for electric vehicles, smart consumer and industrial electronics, and renewable energy sources like solar and wind, society needs better-performing batteries to meet consumer demand and to transition to a sustainable energy future. However, today?s batteries, predominantly lithium-ion, suffer from limitations. In addition to reaching their physical limit regarding energy density, they are flammable, toxic, and not easily recycled. Metal-air batteries, like zinc-air, are safer than lithium-ion batteries because they are non-flammable and made using non-toxic recyclable materials. Zinc-air batteries also have the potential for over 3 times higher energy density than lithium-ion batteries, with potential for nearly 10 times lower cost per unit energy stored. This is likely to impact electric vehicle market penetration and the decarbonization of transportation. This may also enable metal-air battery applications for long-duration grid storage to store energy from renewable sources. Such benefits will be important in order to transition society to a clean and sustainable energy future.</p> <p>This project has advanced multiple fields of research, including metal-air and other battery systems, as well as methods for the production and application of sustainable bio-based materials. The biomaterials that compose our bio-based ink are produced using novel synthetic biology techniques that utilize gene editing and state-of-the-art fermentation-style production, which are relevant tools used to manufacture chemicals, biologics, and biomaterials. &nbsp;While metal-air batteries possess massive potential to improve the cost and energy density relative to mature lithium-ion battery technologies, they suffer from performance-limiting issues with key metrics, including poor current density, coulombic efficiency, and usable capacity. In order to enable metal-air batteries to become commercially feasible, Power For Humanity is addressing these critical pain points through this project by developing a bio-based ink that is used to fabricate a cathode coating that improves these key battery performance metrics. This will position Power For Humanity to commercialize the technology through sales to metal-air battery manufacturers. With the improvement in performance, combined with the safe and recyclable nature of emerging battery technologies, Power For Humanity seeks to play an important role in the success of metal-air and related battery technologies.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;F&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Topic name: Energy Technology (EN). Sub-topic name: EN2. Energy Production and Power Generation  This NSF SBIR Phase I project was focused on developing a bio-based ink used to fabricate a cathode coating to make metal-air batteries more energy-efficient and longer-lasting. This is accomplished by integrating the coating into existing battery systems to improve their key performance metrics, specifically current density, coulombic efficiency, discharge voltage, and discharge capacity. During Phase I, it was demonstrated that using a bio-based coating could improve the performance of metal-air battery prototypes made in our lab. This research enabled us to form partnerships with metal-air battery manufacturers that are potential customers for our ink. We are currently in the process of evaluating the viability of our technology once integrated into commercially relevant systems through our partnerships.  Batteries are crucial for storing energy needed to power electronics and enabling the use of intermittent renewable energy sources. With the rising demand for electric vehicles, smart consumer and industrial electronics, and renewable energy sources like solar and wind, society needs better-performing batteries to meet consumer demand and to transition to a sustainable energy future. However, today?s batteries, predominantly lithium-ion, suffer from limitations. In addition to reaching their physical limit regarding energy density, they are flammable, toxic, and not easily recycled. Metal-air batteries, like zinc-air, are safer than lithium-ion batteries because they are non-flammable and made using non-toxic recyclable materials. Zinc-air batteries also have the potential for over 3 times higher energy density than lithium-ion batteries, with potential for nearly 10 times lower cost per unit energy stored. This is likely to impact electric vehicle market penetration and the decarbonization of transportation. This may also enable metal-air battery applications for long-duration grid storage to store energy from renewable sources. Such benefits will be important in order to transition society to a clean and sustainable energy future.  This project has advanced multiple fields of research, including metal-air and other battery systems, as well as methods for the production and application of sustainable bio-based materials. The biomaterials that compose our bio-based ink are produced using novel synthetic biology techniques that utilize gene editing and state-of-the-art fermentation-style production, which are relevant tools used to manufacture chemicals, biologics, and biomaterials.  While metal-air batteries possess massive potential to improve the cost and energy density relative to mature lithium-ion battery technologies, they suffer from performance-limiting issues with key metrics, including poor current density, coulombic efficiency, and usable capacity. In order to enable metal-air batteries to become commercially feasible, Power For Humanity is addressing these critical pain points through this project by developing a bio-based ink that is used to fabricate a cathode coating that improves these key battery performance metrics. This will position Power For Humanity to commercialize the technology through sales to metal-air battery manufacturers. With the improvement in performance, combined with the safe and recyclable nature of emerging battery technologies, Power For Humanity seeks to play an important role in the success of metal-air and related battery technologies.       Last Modified: 05/12/2022       Submitted by: Alexander F Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
