<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Enhancing MRI performance by using nonlinear metamaterials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255992.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255992</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to improve clinical magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). This project will enable improved image quality and/or shortened scan time, increasing the throughput, and decreasing the cost of this modern diagnostic tool. Potentially, this technology will improve patient access to MRI.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project advances magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) by constructing nonlinear metamaterial (NLMM)-enhanced surface coils to improve the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). The coupling between the NLMM and the surface coil will be investigated to optimize the SNR enhancement and avoid potential image artifacts through theoretical modeling and numerical simulation. The fabrication and implementation of the NLMM-integrated surface coil will be studied via the marriage of novel additive manufacturing and conventional screen-printing technology for mass production of such devices. The NLMM-enhanced surface coil performance will be optimized with the tandem development of image reconstruction algorithms to generate an improved MRI image acquisition by taking the field gradient induced by the NLMMs into account. The ultimate goal of this project is to provide highly integrated NLMM-enhanced surface coils to significantly improve SNR of MRI.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2052053</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>McNaughton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan McNaughton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[RMcNaughton@PriMetaz.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000881216</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoguang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoguang Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zhaoxg04@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000809057</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/21/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xin Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xinz@bu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000096200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PRIMETAZ, LLC</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022152421</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4432044304</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8 SAINT MARYS ST STE 610</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SNMHDNN1AXN8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRIMETAZ LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022152421</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8 Saint Mary's Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255992</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) system and accessory manufacturers have continually sought improved performance, driven by a desire for better diagnostic accuracy and imaging efficiency. One method to evaluate the overall performance of MRI is signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), which can be used to measure image quality and exam length. Metamaterials have become a particularly interesting approach in the academic setting given their flexibility in design and ability to boost magnetic fields. Through this National Science Foundation (NSF) STTR Phase I project, the feasibility for constructing a metamaterial-enhanced surface coil that demonstrates improvements in the SNR of MRI was investigated. To achieve this overall objective, work has been done to: 1) investigate the coupling between metamaterials and surface coils through simulation, 2) explore novel fabrication methods with large-scale manufacturing in mind, and 3) experimentally examine the SNR enhancement potential of an integrated metamaterial-enhanced surface coil.</p> <p>Throughout this NSF STTR Phase I project, major strides were taken toward establishing the feasibility of a metamaterial-enhanced surface coil. Continued development of such MRI surface coils toward significantly improved SNR is foreseen to ease the widespread clinical adoption of metamaterials. More broadly, such increases in SNR with these coils have the commercial potential to speed up MRI exams, increasing the number of patients who can receive timely and better-quality radiologic care.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Ryan&nbsp;Mcnaughton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) system and accessory manufacturers have continually sought improved performance, driven by a desire for better diagnostic accuracy and imaging efficiency. One method to evaluate the overall performance of MRI is signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), which can be used to measure image quality and exam length. Metamaterials have become a particularly interesting approach in the academic setting given their flexibility in design and ability to boost magnetic fields. Through this National Science Foundation (NSF) STTR Phase I project, the feasibility for constructing a metamaterial-enhanced surface coil that demonstrates improvements in the SNR of MRI was investigated. To achieve this overall objective, work has been done to: 1) investigate the coupling between metamaterials and surface coils through simulation, 2) explore novel fabrication methods with large-scale manufacturing in mind, and 3) experimentally examine the SNR enhancement potential of an integrated metamaterial-enhanced surface coil.  Throughout this NSF STTR Phase I project, major strides were taken toward establishing the feasibility of a metamaterial-enhanced surface coil. Continued development of such MRI surface coils toward significantly improved SNR is foreseen to ease the widespread clinical adoption of metamaterials. More broadly, such increases in SNR with these coils have the commercial potential to speed up MRI exams, increasing the number of patients who can receive timely and better-quality radiologic care.          Last Modified: 05/31/2023       Submitted by: Ryan Mcnaughton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
