<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Novel Cryodesalination System]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project allows energy efficiencies and novel methods of fresh water production. The high cost of conventional methods prevent construction of new desalination (converting salt water) and wastewater clean-up facilities. The proposed project lowers the high capital and operating costs of producing fresh water.  The proposed process is a platform technology with applications ranging from seawater desalination to purification of waste streams from a variety of industries, including petroleum, mining, fertilizer, and coal. The units can range in size from small mobile units on skids to massive high-volume infrastructure plants enabling economies of scale and construction of large plants, potentially at one-tenth the costs of present-day desalination plants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to prove and quantify the effectiveness of two major innovations: the crystallizer that controls crystal size and the ice-brine separation process which separates ice crystals from residual brine without mechanical equipment. The crystallizer R&amp;D includes calibrating and measuring internal circulation; charting internal circulation as a function of ice crystallization rate and pressure; studying ice formation and ice crystal salinity (purity) as a function of ice crystallization rate, internal circulation, pressure, residence time, and brine concentration (temperature); determining the effect of pressure and operating ranges to avoid hydrate formation; determining how hydrate formation is related to feed and/or reject brine concentrations; and determining the effect of varying residence time. The ice slurry R&amp;D includes investigating the maximum ice concentration in slurries that can be pumped without difficulty within the range of 15 – 25% ice concentration; and the effect of various temperatures on the flow characteristics of these slurries. Cryosol investigations include determining and graphing at what point and to what extent viscosity diluents are needed to maintain good slurry flow within the range of temperatures from 32F to the eutectic; and the identification and properties of effective non-toxic viscosity diluents.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2053267</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kent</FirstName>
<LastName>Dawson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kent Dawson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kent@cryodesalination.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000875856</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norbert</FirstName>
<LastName>Buchsbaum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Norbert N Buchsbaum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cryodesalination@comcast.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000646895</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/18/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CryoDesalination, LLC</Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>770961428</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137030597</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5159 JACKWOOD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QDEWAAR1U7K1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CRYODESALINATION LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CryoDesalination, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Conroe</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>773036403</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5111 North Frazier]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Water scarcity for human, industrial, and agricultural consumption is an important and significant problem of our time. Global population and per-capita water usage are increasing while fresh water supplies are dwindling. One of the largest hurdles in making seawater and industrial wastewater suitable for consumption is the high cost of building and operating desalination and wastewater clean-up facilities.</p> <p>CryoDesalinations technology is a better way to lower this burden and reduce the cost of desalination globally, increasing the accessibility of fresh water for people that need it.&nbsp;</p> <p>Freeze desalination was tested extensively in the 1950s and 1960s. However, this research did not find a viable method to separate ice from brine at scale. CryoDesalination has solved this problem using a smart and simple approach. During the NSF funded research, we verified that an immiscible edible oil with an intermediate density can be effectively used to separate forming ice from salty brine. We call this oil Cryosol (See Outcome Figure 1), and it enables several advantages:</p> <ol> <li>Straightforward physical separation of ice from brine&nbsp;</li> <li>Prevents excess brine from being captured in the forming ice, increasing efficiency</li> <li>Higher thermal efficiency than thermal desalination</li> <li>Favorable economies of scale compared to reverse osmosis</li> </ol> <p>This Phase I effort investigated and quantified the interaction of variables in batch systems. In this process, we proved the technology, developed a working design, and mitigated the most important risks associated with CryoDesalination. Specifically, we showed:</p> <ol> <li>A wide variety of brines, from seawater (3.7% salt) to industrial effluent (10% salt), can be desalinated by freezing. See Outcome Figure 2</li> <li>The optimal freezing and brine mixing dynamics with testing and Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD). See Outcome Figure 3</li> <li>How to select the appropriate Cryosol based on feed variables. See Outcome Figure 4</li> <li>How to mitigate hydrocarbon hydrates</li> <li>How our patented process allows for smarter and more effective separation of ice and brine in a flowing system</li> </ol> <p>A proposed Phase II effort will build on this progress to create a small-scale fully continuous desalination system that can be scaled directly to commercial scale, effectively de-risking the technology for large scale adoption.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Kent&nbsp;Dawson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216315087_Fig1.Cryosolallowsfortheeasyseparationofcleanicefrombrinewithoutbrineentrainment--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216315087_Fig1.Cryosolallowsfortheeasyseparationofcleanicefrombrinewithoutbrineentrainment--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cryosol"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216315087_Fig1.Cryosolallowsfortheeasyseparationofcleanicefrombrinewithoutbrineentrainment--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cryosol"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Outcome Figure 1. Cryosol allows for the easy separation of clean ice from brine without brine entrainment</div> <div class="imageCredit">CryoDesalination, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kent&nbsp;Dawson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cryosol</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216408880_Fig2.ManyBrinescanbedesalinatedwithCryoDesalination--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216408880_Fig2.ManyBrinescanbedesalinatedwithCryoDesalination--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Desalination"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216408880_Fig2.ManyBrinescanbedesalinatedwithCryoDesalination--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Desalination"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Outcome Figure 2. Many Brines can be desalinated with CryoDesalination</div> <div class="imageCredit">CryoDesalination, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kent&nbsp;Dawson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Desalination</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216490074_Fig3.Icevolumefractionatincreasingdistancesfromthemixingnozzle--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216490074_Fig3.Icevolumefractionatincreasingdistancesfromthemixingnozzle--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mixing efficiency"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216490074_Fig3.Icevolumefractionatincreasingdistancesfromthemixingnozzle--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mixing efficiency"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Outcome Figure 3. Ice volume fraction at increasing distances from the mixing nozzle</div> <div class="imageCredit">CryoDesalination, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kent&nbsp;Dawson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mixing efficiency</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216570463_Fig4.ViscosityvsTemperatureforfiveCryosolcandidates--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216570463_Fig4.ViscosityvsTemperatureforfiveCryosolcandidates--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cryosol viscosity"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2053267/2053267_10759570_1674216570463_Fig4.ViscosityvsTemperatureforfiveCryosolcandidates--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cryosol viscosity"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Outcome Figure 4. Viscosity vs Temperature for five Cryosol candidates</div> <div class="imageCredit">CryoDesalination, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kent&nbsp;Dawson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cryosol viscosity</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Water scarcity for human, industrial, and agricultural consumption is an important and significant problem of our time. Global population and per-capita water usage are increasing while fresh water supplies are dwindling. One of the largest hurdles in making seawater and industrial wastewater suitable for consumption is the high cost of building and operating desalination and wastewater clean-up facilities.  CryoDesalinations technology is a better way to lower this burden and reduce the cost of desalination globally, increasing the accessibility of fresh water for people that need it.   Freeze desalination was tested extensively in the 1950s and 1960s. However, this research did not find a viable method to separate ice from brine at scale. CryoDesalination has solved this problem using a smart and simple approach. During the NSF funded research, we verified that an immiscible edible oil with an intermediate density can be effectively used to separate forming ice from salty brine. We call this oil Cryosol (See Outcome Figure 1), and it enables several advantages:  Straightforward physical separation of ice from brine  Prevents excess brine from being captured in the forming ice, increasing efficiency Higher thermal efficiency than thermal desalination Favorable economies of scale compared to reverse osmosis   This Phase I effort investigated and quantified the interaction of variables in batch systems. In this process, we proved the technology, developed a working design, and mitigated the most important risks associated with CryoDesalination. Specifically, we showed:  A wide variety of brines, from seawater (3.7% salt) to industrial effluent (10% salt), can be desalinated by freezing. See Outcome Figure 2 The optimal freezing and brine mixing dynamics with testing and Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD). See Outcome Figure 3 How to select the appropriate Cryosol based on feed variables. See Outcome Figure 4 How to mitigate hydrocarbon hydrates How our patented process allows for smarter and more effective separation of ice and brine in a flowing system   A proposed Phase II effort will build on this progress to create a small-scale fully continuous desalination system that can be scaled directly to commercial scale, effectively de-risking the technology for large scale adoption.           Last Modified: 01/25/2023       Submitted by: Kent Dawson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
