<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Understanding the unprecedented anchovy response to warm-water conditions in the California Current]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Suchman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>csuchman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922092</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Like many species of small pelagic marine fish, recruitment and productivity of Northern Anchovy fluctuate by orders of magnitude among years. When abundant, the anchovy support a wide range of marine species, including marine mammals, seabirds and a diverse group of marine fishes. Anchovy, which previously thrived during periods of cool-water temperatures and strong coastal upwelling, are currently booming with abundances far in excess of any historical record, even though the California Current Ecosystem is experiencing an unprecedented marine heat wave. This unexpected occurrence challenges the most basic understanding of the mechanisms driving population dynamics in the species.  This project is investigating the effects of trophic relationships on population productivity by capitalizing on the immediate research opportunity afforded by the novel, yet ephemeral, state of a local marine heat wave. Findings from the work are being used to develop a mechanistic model of coastal pelagic fish population dynamics generally, and anchovy dynamics in particular. Funded field and lab work are supporting opportunities for undergraduate training and research, and are generating open-access data that serve the research and teaching/training communities into the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID project augments the scheduled Fall research cruises jointly run by the California Cooperative Oceanic Fisheries Investigation and the California Current Ecosystem Long-Term Ecological Research programs. Together, these programs conduct regional oceanographic surveys that include anchovy spawning grounds and larval nursery areas. The RAPID-augmented sampling is designed to test the emerging hypothesis that anchovy populations are trophodynamically mediated at the larval stage, whereby high recruitment results from increased trophic transfer efficiency from the base of the food web. Larval diets and prey selection analyses are being paired with amino acid compound-specific isotope analysis (δ15N) of the larvae and prey field to generate detailed information on larval trophic ecology. Larval diets and plankton community structure are being related to available data on upwelling and productivity to assess environmental and biological drivers to trophic transfer efficiency. Collectively, these analyses are revealing how food chain length is regulated at the larval level through prey selection, at the prey level through community composition, and at the base of the food chain via coastal upwelling and primary production. Furthermore, this project is establishing whether the current trophic level of anchovy larvae is equal to that of historic population booms and if this is the result of favorable feeding conditions throughout their habitat.  Findings from the study are generating a mechanistic understanding of the trophic underpinnings of small pelagic fish population productivity in coastal upwelling systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2053719</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brice</FirstName>
<LastName>Semmens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brice Semmens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bsemmens@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000646400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Landry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael R Landry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mlandry@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000066876</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920931500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8622 DISCOVERY WAY RM 116</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QJ8HMDK7MRM3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCSD Scripps Inst of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Dr. #0210]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1174</Code>
<Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1195</Code>
<Text>LONG TERM ECOLOGICAL RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Northern Anchovy is an important constituent of the marine food web, supporting numerous species of marine mammals, seabirds and a diverse group of marine fishes inhabiting the US west coast. During an extended period of unusually high sea surface temperatures that began with the 2014 warm-water anomaly, anchovy, previously thought to thrive only under high-upwelling cold-water conditions, boomed to a population size far exceeding historical records. Like many other small coastal pelagic fishes worldwide, anchovy exhibit massive boom and bust fluctuations in population size, but this recent event raised new questions as to what specific factors drive the fluctuations. We had linked anchovy booms and busts to changes in larval food chain length (FCL) that affect energy transfer efficiency from the food chain base to larvae, but the exact mechanisms behind FCL regulation were unknown. Fish are most vulnerable to starvation and predation during the larval stage, and survival is crucial to recruitment of young fish to the adult populations. The current project capitalized on persistent warm-water conditions in the Southern Californian Bight and high numbers of anchovy and other species spawning there to gain a better understanding of what, where and how changes in larval food chain length occur, how that relates to fitness, growth and survival, and other factors, such as maternal investment, that may be important for larval survival.</p> <p>Larval anchovy, abundant co-occuring species of larval rockfish and their plankton prey were sampled at multiple locations throughout the Southern Californian Bight in fall 2020, and winter and spring 2021. In addition, we also used larval anchovy and shortbelly rockfish (a commonly caught species) collected by the California Cooperative Oceanic Fisheries Investigations (CalCOFI) over the past 2 decades and larval anchovy size data from 1960 to 2005. We used microscopic and imaging techniques to identify fish larval, prey communities in the environment, diet and prey selection by the larvae. We also employed otolith analysis to measure larval otolith core size, a proxy for maternal investment, otolith growth ring widths to age and reconstruct the growth history of the larvae, and Compound Specific Isotopic Analysis of nitrogen isotopes in Amino Acids to determine FCL.</p> <p>We found that larval anchovy as well as rockfish are highly selective in their feeding, and mostly rely on specific copepod species and development stages, suggesting that they could be actively selecting for prey that result in a shorter more efficient food chain. In larval shortbelly rockfishes, the ingestion of these preferred prey resulted in higher body condition and faster growth. Shorter FCL led to significantly faster growth rate and a higher body fitness. Development of a larval size ratio index as a proxy for larval survival also revealed that during the historical time periods of short FCL to larval anchovy, the larval size ratio index was low, indicating high survival of young larvae which subsequently resulted in large adult population size. From these three tightly linked parameters, we proposed the &ldquo;Trophic Efficiency in Early Life (TEEL)&rdquo; Hypothesis for fisheries recruitment. High survival of larvae to recruit to the adult population depends on high energy transfer efficiency from the base of the food chain to the larvae. We also found that a larger otolith core size correlated with improved foraging of larval rockfish and higher survival and body fitness of both larval anchovy and rockfish, suggesting that maternal investment may be another important determinant of recruitment success.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The findings of this project have generated new understanding of the principal mechanisms driving growth and survival of young fishes and their recruitment to adult populations. This information along with the FCL and larval size ratio indexes has the potential to improve the assessment and short-term predictions of population sizes and inform management strategies of these species and possibly other species as well. In sum, our research suggests that the combination of being born large (maternal investment) and short FCL to preferred prey (trophic efficiency) are keystone factors that facilitate rapid growth and survival of very different fishes in the California Current. Temporal variability in these factors may apply as a general mechanism that drives the boom-bust dynamics of small pelagic species worldwide.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/22/2023<br>      Modified by: Brice&nbsp;Semmens</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Northern Anchovy is an important constituent of the marine food web, supporting numerous species of marine mammals, seabirds and a diverse group of marine fishes inhabiting the US west coast. During an extended period of unusually high sea surface temperatures that began with the 2014 warm-water anomaly, anchovy, previously thought to thrive only under high-upwelling cold-water conditions, boomed to a population size far exceeding historical records. Like many other small coastal pelagic fishes worldwide, anchovy exhibit massive boom and bust fluctuations in population size, but this recent event raised new questions as to what specific factors drive the fluctuations. We had linked anchovy booms and busts to changes in larval food chain length (FCL) that affect energy transfer efficiency from the food chain base to larvae, but the exact mechanisms behind FCL regulation were unknown. Fish are most vulnerable to starvation and predation during the larval stage, and survival is crucial to recruitment of young fish to the adult populations. The current project capitalized on persistent warm-water conditions in the Southern Californian Bight and high numbers of anchovy and other species spawning there to gain a better understanding of what, where and how changes in larval food chain length occur, how that relates to fitness, growth and survival, and other factors, such as maternal investment, that may be important for larval survival.  Larval anchovy, abundant co-occuring species of larval rockfish and their plankton prey were sampled at multiple locations throughout the Southern Californian Bight in fall 2020, and winter and spring 2021. In addition, we also used larval anchovy and shortbelly rockfish (a commonly caught species) collected by the California Cooperative Oceanic Fisheries Investigations (CalCOFI) over the past 2 decades and larval anchovy size data from 1960 to 2005. We used microscopic and imaging techniques to identify fish larval, prey communities in the environment, diet and prey selection by the larvae. We also employed otolith analysis to measure larval otolith core size, a proxy for maternal investment, otolith growth ring widths to age and reconstruct the growth history of the larvae, and Compound Specific Isotopic Analysis of nitrogen isotopes in Amino Acids to determine FCL.  We found that larval anchovy as well as rockfish are highly selective in their feeding, and mostly rely on specific copepod species and development stages, suggesting that they could be actively selecting for prey that result in a shorter more efficient food chain. In larval shortbelly rockfishes, the ingestion of these preferred prey resulted in higher body condition and faster growth. Shorter FCL led to significantly faster growth rate and a higher body fitness. Development of a larval size ratio index as a proxy for larval survival also revealed that during the historical time periods of short FCL to larval anchovy, the larval size ratio index was low, indicating high survival of young larvae which subsequently resulted in large adult population size. From these three tightly linked parameters, we proposed the "Trophic Efficiency in Early Life (TEEL)" Hypothesis for fisheries recruitment. High survival of larvae to recruit to the adult population depends on high energy transfer efficiency from the base of the food chain to the larvae. We also found that a larger otolith core size correlated with improved foraging of larval rockfish and higher survival and body fitness of both larval anchovy and rockfish, suggesting that maternal investment may be another important determinant of recruitment success.      The findings of this project have generated new understanding of the principal mechanisms driving growth and survival of young fishes and their recruitment to adult populations. This information along with the FCL and larval size ratio indexes has the potential to improve the assessment and short-term predictions of population sizes and inform management strategies of these species and possibly other species as well. In sum, our research suggests that the combination of being born large (maternal investment) and short FCL to preferred prey (trophic efficiency) are keystone factors that facilitate rapid growth and survival of very different fishes in the California Current. Temporal variability in these factors may apply as a general mechanism that drives the boom-bust dynamics of small pelagic species worldwide.       Last Modified: 03/22/2023       Submitted by: Brice Semmens]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
