<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Sustainable textile manufacturing through protein engineering]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255003.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255003</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will demonstrate the promise of transforming proteins found in agricultural waste into high-performance, cost-effective and environmentally friendly cotton, silk and polyester-like fibers.  Textile production negatively impacts the environment and wastewater.  Structural proteins found in agricultural waste are a substitute to natural silk, cotton, and theoretically polyester. The proposed project will advance a new, tough, cost-effective, environmentally friendly, protein-based textile fiber. The proposed textile will be both recyclable and biodegradable. Protein-based fibers will transform the $981 B global textile industry and enable new use of billions of pounds of agricultural waste.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will advance a technology to maintain protein primary structure (backbone chemistry) for synthetic textile development.  The challenge is to simultaneously restore the protein secondary and tertiary structure responsible for the excellent balance of mechanical and aesthetic properties inherent in natural plant and animal sourced fibers. The proposed process integrates protein molecular biology with novel, ecologically sound fiber formation engineering. Advanced manufacturing will be used to recreate fibers in a closed-loop process recycling chemicals and water without harmful byproducts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2053091</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Simardev</FirstName>
<LastName>Gulati</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Simardev Gulati</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sim@dropelfabrics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000835110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BARLEY &amp; BRITCHES INC.</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100184878</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5162637006</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>530 FASHION AVE # M1</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PMRZTZEFM4M8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BARLEY &amp; BRITCHES INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[DROPEL FABRICS]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100184878</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255003</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-bc864910-7fff-d8e2-f10f-c2391379434b"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project validated proprietary technology to transform waste poultry&nbsp;</span>feather keratin into scalable, durable, luxruious and cost-effective textile fibers. Specifically, we have validated that our proprietary, wet spinning process produces a fiber with the secondary structure of natural keratin and we have validated our proprietary &ldquo;melt spinning&rdquo; process for poultry feather keratin based on the addition of nitrogen containing low molar mass compounds. A cost- effective source of poultry feather keratin has been identified, allowing for future scale-up initiatives. Detailed plans for the Process and Product Development laboratory and initial plans for a pilot scale (100kg/month) are in place.</p> <p dir="ltr">Potential customers have been identified with interest in evaluating waste poultry feather keratin textile fibers for a variety of&nbsp;textile applications. Initial lifetime audit calculations suggest that with the technolog,&nbsp; waste poultryfeather keratin can be transformed into a value added textile product with reduced carbon footprint compared to current textile fibers. The commercialization of waste keratin into cost- effective textile fibers will provide a new source of textiles for the growing world population with an environmentally friendly textile product consistent with the circular economy. The commercialization of keratin fibers in the United States will also result in significant job creation and GDP growth.</p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Simardev&nbsp;Gulati</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The project validated proprietary technology to transform waste poultry feather keratin into scalable, durable, luxruious and cost-effective textile fibers. Specifically, we have validated that our proprietary, wet spinning process produces a fiber with the secondary structure of natural keratin and we have validated our proprietary "melt spinning" process for poultry feather keratin based on the addition of nitrogen containing low molar mass compounds. A cost- effective source of poultry feather keratin has been identified, allowing for future scale-up initiatives. Detailed plans for the Process and Product Development laboratory and initial plans for a pilot scale (100kg/month) are in place. Potential customers have been identified with interest in evaluating waste poultry feather keratin textile fibers for a variety of textile applications. Initial lifetime audit calculations suggest that with the technolog,  waste poultryfeather keratin can be transformed into a value added textile product with reduced carbon footprint compared to current textile fibers. The commercialization of waste keratin into cost- effective textile fibers will provide a new source of textiles for the growing world population with an environmentally friendly textile product consistent with the circular economy. The commercialization of keratin fibers in the United States will also result in significant job creation and GDP growth.               Last Modified: 05/05/2023       Submitted by: Simardev Gulati]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
