<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER: Chemistry Perspectives to Design Novel Superconductors]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>651501.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>77589</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschwenz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924771</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PART 1:   NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Superconductivity, though first discovered more than a century ago, is still plagued by questions and challenges.  Superconductors have zero electrical resistance and strongly repel magnetic fields when electricity flows through them and therefore have applications for uses such as grids that can transmit power without energy loss, ultra-fast levitating trains that ride frictionless magnets instead of rails, and quantum computing devices. There is a demand for innovative approaches to the design and synthesis of new superconducting materials. This project, supported by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry program within the Division of Materials Research and the Established Program to Support Competitive Research (EPSCoR), combines experimental investigation and theoretical assessment to reveal fundamental chemical principles to design new superconducting materials. The scientific significance of the research is to open a new chemical perspective towards superconductivity that focuses on the role of pairs of atoms of particular elements to accelerate the search for new superconductors. The proposed outreach activities and educational plan emphasize solid-state materials-related outreach activities including the development of dually communication-intensive certified and service-learning certified undergraduate courses and a vibrant research program for women and underrepresented minority students in the state of Louisiana.  These activities will expand the research capability of the state and foster the training of next-generation materials scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PART 2:   TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses chemical strategies to probe the role of two new critical charge-transfer pairs of elements (Pd-P and Pt-P) in superconductivity.  The PI and her group use methods for solid-state materials discovery and physical properties characterization, targeting families of compounds selected in order to be able to probe the role of breaking or forming bonds between these specific pairs of elements.  Together with the experimental effort, theoretical determination of electronic structures and electron-phonon coupling provide feedback toward further synthetic efforts.  This approach advances knowledge about a comprehensive set of properties: structural influences on electronic and magnetic structures, electron-electron and electron-phonon correlations, magnetism, spin-orbit coupling effects, and their interplay in superconductors. The educational plan will focus on developing and establishing service-learning pedagogies for solid-state materials in the state of Louisiana. This gives university students experiential opportunities to learn in real-world contexts and develop skills of community engagement while providing outreach demonstrations relating to superconductivity and other properties to K-12 schools.  This project is supported by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry program within the Division of Materials Research and the Established Program to Support Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2053287</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weiwei</FirstName>
<LastName>Xie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weiwei Xie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xieweiwe@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000746057</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 RUTGERS PLZ</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscatawy</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[33 Knightsbridge Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>054Y</Code>
<Text>GVF - Global Venture Fund</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~77589</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This two-year program is a materials design and synthesis program aimed at discovering new superconductors by translating our understanding of superconductivity physics into chemical requirements. One of the most important features shared by the two families of superconductors is that they are layered compounds with critical charge-transfer pairs (Cu-O and Fe-As). The &ldquo;critical pair&rdquo; is a pair of atoms in the periodic table between which there is a delicate charge-transfer balance between covalent and ionic bonding. It is conjectured that the superconductivity can be induced to systems with critical charge-transfer pairs by small perturbation such as chemical doping. We proposed to investigate new critical charge-transfer pairs in layered structural families, 115-type AT<sub>5</sub>Pn (A=transition metals and rare-earth elements; Pn= P, As, Sb and Se) and 122-type AT<sub>2</sub>M<sub>2</sub> (A=alkali and alkaline earth metals; M= B, Ge, Sn, Pn). The detailed goals of the proposal are understanding the factors that stabilize the metastable phases by combining exploratory/target syntheses and pressure-dependent structure determinations with electronic structure theory and establishing relationships among structures, bonding interactions, and superconductivity. The project also seeks to understand the interplay of superconductivity and magnetism, superconductivity and topology in complex materials to the rational design of novel quantum superconducting materials. These studies yield and will continue to discover important insights into the design and synthesis of novel quantum materials and provide the basis for fundamental insights into the physical behavior of electron systems over a wide range of electron-electron and electron-phonon correlations. We discovered several novel superconductors, superconducting quantum materials, and intermetallics with unusual structures and electronic and magnetic features.</p> <p>The outreach activities included the development of a solid-state materials-related outreach activities including the development of dually Communication-Intensive certified and Service-Learning certified undergraduate courses and a vibrant research program for women and underrepresented minority students. The undergraduate students&rsquo; activities included the development of confidence by in-person interaction and class support after the pandemic.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Weiwei&nbsp;Xie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This two-year program is a materials design and synthesis program aimed at discovering new superconductors by translating our understanding of superconductivity physics into chemical requirements. One of the most important features shared by the two families of superconductors is that they are layered compounds with critical charge-transfer pairs (Cu-O and Fe-As). The "critical pair" is a pair of atoms in the periodic table between which there is a delicate charge-transfer balance between covalent and ionic bonding. It is conjectured that the superconductivity can be induced to systems with critical charge-transfer pairs by small perturbation such as chemical doping. We proposed to investigate new critical charge-transfer pairs in layered structural families, 115-type AT5Pn (A=transition metals and rare-earth elements; Pn= P, As, Sb and Se) and 122-type AT2M2 (A=alkali and alkaline earth metals; M= B, Ge, Sn, Pn). The detailed goals of the proposal are understanding the factors that stabilize the metastable phases by combining exploratory/target syntheses and pressure-dependent structure determinations with electronic structure theory and establishing relationships among structures, bonding interactions, and superconductivity. The project also seeks to understand the interplay of superconductivity and magnetism, superconductivity and topology in complex materials to the rational design of novel quantum superconducting materials. These studies yield and will continue to discover important insights into the design and synthesis of novel quantum materials and provide the basis for fundamental insights into the physical behavior of electron systems over a wide range of electron-electron and electron-phonon correlations. We discovered several novel superconductors, superconducting quantum materials, and intermetallics with unusual structures and electronic and magnetic features.  The outreach activities included the development of a solid-state materials-related outreach activities including the development of dually Communication-Intensive certified and Service-Learning certified undergraduate courses and a vibrant research program for women and underrepresented minority students. The undergraduate students’ activities included the development of confidence by in-person interaction and class support after the pandemic.       Last Modified: 02/25/2023       Submitted by: Weiwei Xie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
