<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Fundamental Investigations in Femtosecond Laser-based Additive Manufacturing with Functional Nanomaterials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12668.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12668</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Wells</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awells@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With the coming era of the Internet-of-Things (IoT), there is an increasing need for miniaturized smart devices, such as smart sands, tags, and wearable/implantable devices, for various biomedical and environmental monitoring applications. Many critical components in these devices, such as sensors, antennas, inter-connects and batteries are not compatible with conventional Integrated Circuits (IC) processes used in the semiconductor industry. In addition, many devices need to be customized for their specific target applications, which could require three-dimensional nanostructures, heterogeneous materials integration, miniaturized form factor, and specified sensitivity, power density and life times. It is difficult for conventional semiconductor manufacturing foundries to accommodate these customized specifications due to the lack of flexibility in process and material choices. Micro and nanoscale additive manufacturing has the potential to meet such requirements. However, a technical breakthrough is still needed in this area to enable additive manufacturing of functional components with nanoscale resolution, quality and reliability commensurate with IC fabricated devices. This award supports fundamental research to form the knowledge base for development of nanoscale additive manufacturing (Nano-AM) processes for direct manufacturing of nano-devices. Multiple disciplines are involved in this research including nanomanufacturing, laser-nanomaterial interaction, surface science, and multiscale transport phenomena. Results from this research will enhance the U.S. competence in advanced manufacturing industry by providing paradigm-changing manufacturing technique in the era of IoT. The integration of the research results into curriculum development, undergraduate and minority students research opportunities and hands-on projects for K-12 students will enhance the students' knowledge and foster innovation in advanced manufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Current nanoscale additive manufacturing is limited by the lack of capability to fabricate 3D nonpolymer functional devices. To overcome this limit, this research employs non-polymer (metal, semiconductor and dielectric) nanomaterials as building blocks and aims at understanding and exploiting unique behaviors of these nanomaterials under ultrafast laser excitation to enable 3D Nano-AM processes. Firstly, fundamental mechanisms leading to femtosecond laser induced ionization and surface modification of nanomaterials will be explored. Secondly, the correlations between laser excitation (ionization and modification) and induced nanomaterial assembly, deposition and sintering behaviors will be established. Multiscale modeling and simulations (Ab initio, classical Molecular Dynamics and Brownian Dynamics) will be performed to understand experimental results over different temporal and spatial scales. Finally, a physics-based model relating nanomaterials properties, laser excitation conditions with the morphology and properties of manufactured nanostructures will be developed.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2054104</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heng</FirstName>
<LastName>Pan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heng Pan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hpan@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000653742</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778433124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3124 TAMU</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>081E</Code>
<Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~12668</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Additive manufacturing (AM) has revolutionized the conventional manufacturing technologies by providing freedom of fabrication of arbitrarily complex three-dimensional (3D) structures.&nbsp; 3D printing of micro/nano structures are important because of their diverse applications, especially in electronics, optics and medical fields. Today, most of the commercially available metal AM processes are at macroscale and no established method is available for direct printing true 3D structures with sub-micron feature size without involving organic additives. Metal micro/nanofabrication is of high interest in printable electronics, microelectromechanical systems, nanophotonics and biomedical devices. Massive amount of research on 3D metal printing focus on features &gt;10 &micro;m, such as inkjet printing, aerosol jet printing, micro selective laser sintering, and laser chemical vapor deposition, or 1-10 &micro;m, such as direct ink writing and laser induced forward transfer. Several works with sub-&micro;m features have been reported, including electrohydrodynamic printing, laser electrophoretic deposition, and localized electroplating, which all require conductive or semi-conductive substrates. Focused electron/ion beam induced deposition could reach tens of nm resolution at a cost of SEM/FIB equipment.</p> <p>In this project, we enable sub-micron 3D printing of metal using femtosecond laser to induce highly localized, non-thermal ligand transformation and self-fusion of nanocrystals (Figure 1). This process does not require organic additives or designed photosensitive ligands and is applicable to common ligands (such as oleylamine, a versatile ligand widely used in encapsulating metal, semiconductor and ceramic nanoparticles). Furthermore, it is shown this process can print various 2.5D (Figure 2) and true 3D (Figure 3) metal structures containing sub-micron features. To provide insight in the new manufacturing process, we use femtosecond laser two-pulse correlation and <em>in-situ</em> optical transmission probing to investigate the non-equilibrium heating of nanocrystals and transient sintering dynamics.It is found that electron coupling plays an important role in the laser nanocrystal sintering process. The ultrafast (sub-10ps) and non-equilibrium process facilitates sintering in dry (spin-coated NCs) and wet (solvent suspended NCs) environments (Figure 4). The nonlinear dependence of sintering rate on laser fluence was exploited to print sub-diffraction-limited features in nanocrystal suspension. The smallest feature printed is ~200nm, which is ~1/5 of the laser wavelength. These findings provide a new perspective toward nanomanufacturing development based on probing and engineering ultrafast transport phenomena in functional nanocrystals.</p> <p>The new micro/nano additive manufacturing equipment and processes enabled by this project allow direct printing of true 3D structures with multiple functional materials (metal and semiconductors). With the proliferation of smart devices and the coming era of the Internet-of-Things, manufacturing industries are facing a paradigm change. This innovation in additive manufacturing will produce high performance functional micro/nano devices that can be hybridized with Integrated Circuits (IC) chips. This is expected to play an important role in re-shaping manufacturing platforms and supply chains for future smart devices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Heng&nbsp;Pan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672462463208_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672462463208_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672462463208_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Illustration of the laser 3D metal printing process and experimental configuration of laser 3D metal printing process.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Heng Pan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Heng&nbsp;Pan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672462850083_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672462850083_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672462850083_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SEM image of pillar array (2.5D structures).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Heng Pan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Heng&nbsp;Pan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672463043517_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672463043517_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672463043517_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SEM image of printed pillars tilted with various angles and hierarchical structures.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Heng Pan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Heng&nbsp;Pan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672463266091_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672463266091_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054104/2054104_10446003_1672463266091_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Experimental configuration for two-pulse correlation study. The transient nanocrystal sintering process as probed by in-situ optical transmission in two-pulse correlation study.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Heng Pan</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Heng&nbsp;Pan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Additive manufacturing (AM) has revolutionized the conventional manufacturing technologies by providing freedom of fabrication of arbitrarily complex three-dimensional (3D) structures.  3D printing of micro/nano structures are important because of their diverse applications, especially in electronics, optics and medical fields. Today, most of the commercially available metal AM processes are at macroscale and no established method is available for direct printing true 3D structures with sub-micron feature size without involving organic additives. Metal micro/nanofabrication is of high interest in printable electronics, microelectromechanical systems, nanophotonics and biomedical devices. Massive amount of research on 3D metal printing focus on features &gt;10 &micro;m, such as inkjet printing, aerosol jet printing, micro selective laser sintering, and laser chemical vapor deposition, or 1-10 &micro;m, such as direct ink writing and laser induced forward transfer. Several works with sub-&micro;m features have been reported, including electrohydrodynamic printing, laser electrophoretic deposition, and localized electroplating, which all require conductive or semi-conductive substrates. Focused electron/ion beam induced deposition could reach tens of nm resolution at a cost of SEM/FIB equipment.  In this project, we enable sub-micron 3D printing of metal using femtosecond laser to induce highly localized, non-thermal ligand transformation and self-fusion of nanocrystals (Figure 1). This process does not require organic additives or designed photosensitive ligands and is applicable to common ligands (such as oleylamine, a versatile ligand widely used in encapsulating metal, semiconductor and ceramic nanoparticles). Furthermore, it is shown this process can print various 2.5D (Figure 2) and true 3D (Figure 3) metal structures containing sub-micron features. To provide insight in the new manufacturing process, we use femtosecond laser two-pulse correlation and in-situ optical transmission probing to investigate the non-equilibrium heating of nanocrystals and transient sintering dynamics.It is found that electron coupling plays an important role in the laser nanocrystal sintering process. The ultrafast (sub-10ps) and non-equilibrium process facilitates sintering in dry (spin-coated NCs) and wet (solvent suspended NCs) environments (Figure 4). The nonlinear dependence of sintering rate on laser fluence was exploited to print sub-diffraction-limited features in nanocrystal suspension. The smallest feature printed is ~200nm, which is ~1/5 of the laser wavelength. These findings provide a new perspective toward nanomanufacturing development based on probing and engineering ultrafast transport phenomena in functional nanocrystals.  The new micro/nano additive manufacturing equipment and processes enabled by this project allow direct printing of true 3D structures with multiple functional materials (metal and semiconductors). With the proliferation of smart devices and the coming era of the Internet-of-Things, manufacturing industries are facing a paradigm change. This innovation in additive manufacturing will produce high performance functional micro/nano devices that can be hybridized with Integrated Circuits (IC) chips. This is expected to play an important role in re-shaping manufacturing platforms and supply chains for future smart devices.             Last Modified: 01/12/2023       Submitted by: Heng Pan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
