<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Global Sustainability Scholars for Sustainable Oceans: building a network of transdisciplinary scientists and practitioners that represent humanity’s future.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1312490.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1312490</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Uhle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>muhle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Humanity faces profound challenges in the 21st century. From a rapidly rising population, a warming climate, increased demand for food, fiber, and water, and a rapid loss of biodiversity and ecosystem services, we face environmental problems that are more pervasive and serious than at any time in our history.  The global ocean plays a critical role in the Earth system affecting atmospheric, geochemical, ecological, and social systems in a multitude of interconnected ways.  To predict changes, understand their impacts on natural and social systems, and develop approaches that allow us to adapt to and mitigate the impacts, requires more integrative approaches to the study of ocean systems, and this, in turn, will require large-scale cooperation across disciplinary, cultural, and national boundaries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Accordingly, the next generation of sustainability leaders will require a broad set of skills to engage in inter- and trans-disciplinary teams to solve the complex environmental issues that face humanity.  This project seeks to develop the next generation of international trans-disciplinary sustainability science leaders through a collaborative fellowship program that connects undergraduates, graduate students and post-doctoral researchers with today's trans-disciplinary sustainability science leaders.  Using a cohort model, the participants work with international, transdisciplinary research teams on ocean sustainability projects funded by the Belmont Forum, over the course of several field seasons.  Through these research opportunities and training experiences, the program seeks to provide the participants with trans-cultural, trans-disciplinary, and trans-national cooperative opportunities which will be essential in generating and applying knowledge to actions that speed the transition toward a more globally sustainable future. The program seeks to help the participants be nimble and fluent across research disciplines, and to develop collaborative leadership, communication, and negotiation skills.  The project will provide opportunities for students and researchers from underrepresented groups to engage in transdisciplinary, team-oriented, international science with direct relevance to some of the most challenging issues in ocean sustainability.  Engaging over several consecutive field seasons, will further build community that is likely to last well beyond the lifetime of the project and help generate the diverse workforce of the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/27/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2054521</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kirsten</FirstName>
<LastName>Rowell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kirsten Rowell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kirsten.rowell@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000069830</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/27/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nnenia</FirstName>
<LastName>Campbell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nnenia M Campbell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nnenia@billandersonfund.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000748983</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/27/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 MARINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Regents of the University of Colorado]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7313</Code>
<Text>Intl Global Change Res &amp; Coord</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1679</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7313</Code>
<Text>REGIONAL INST FOR GLOBAL CHANG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~1035132</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~277358</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
