<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: An in situ Closure Study of Mixed Phase Clouds at Storm Peak]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/31/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>342319.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>342319</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yu Gu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ygu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928796</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Clouds are commonly differentiated by the precipitation that reaches the surface, either rain or snow. This means they are often thought of as being liquid water, also called warm clouds, or ice, also called cold clouds. Those clouds that contain liquid water droplets and ice crystals at the same time are called mixed phase clouds. Mixed phase clouds are currently poorly understood because of the complicated mixture. Our lack of understanding of clouds, particularly those that are mixed in phase, limits our ability to understand precipitation, the atmosphere chemistry and climate. This project will determine the particles on which the droplets and ice crystals in mixed phase clouds form by deploying a new inlet and both warm and cold cloud chambers at Storm Peak Laboratory. Storm Peak is a high altitude site located in the Rocky Mountains in north-central Colorado that is among only a handful of sites worldwide that offers scientific laboratories where mixed phase clouds exist for long time periods. Using this new inlet, the research team will carry out two-season long observational studies of droplet and ice crystals within mixed phase clouds. This project will allow a resolution of the question of which atmospheric particles make droplets, which make ice crystals, and which do not effectively make either.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A graduate student will work on this project full time, thereby being trained in this important area of atmospheric science. A post-doctoral fellow will also work on this project part-time, increasing their research experience in this area. The collected data will be archived and presented to the atmospheric sciences community. This will include both papers and presentations, with a focus on providing data to help improve models that include precipitation, climate and air quality. Beyond the scientific community, a documentary of the project at Storm Peak will be made in partnership with Science for the Public, a WGBH-Boston television and multimedia production. This will emphasize one of Science for the Public's objective areas, adult science, technology, engineering and math education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2054847</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Cziczo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel J Cziczo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[djcziczo@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000616057</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE STE 1900</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7790</Code>
<Text>LARS SPECIAL PROGRAMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~342317</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This outlines the outcomes of the NSF award entitled "Collaborative Research: An in situ Closure Study of Mixed Phase Clouds at Storm Peak"&nbsp;</p> <p>This project improved our understanding of Mixed Phase Clouds (MPCs),&nbsp;where both droplets and ice can exist,&nbsp;since they are of critical importance in understanding climate and precipitation and how they could change under different emission scenarios in the future.&nbsp;</p> <p>Project goals were successfully completed. We note PI Cziczo moved institutions during the grant period which resulted in some personnel changes. An 18 month no cost extensions was requested due to an inability to perform the required field work during the pandemic. Despite these challenges all work was ultimately completed although final papers remain in the preparation and submission stages.</p> <p>During Year 1 of the project (2018-2019), the team, then at MIT, designed the cloud phase-separating inlet, based on the SPIDER prototype, for characterization of mixed phase clouds at Storm Peak Laboratory (SPL). The design and fabrication work was performed in the lab at MIT from spring to fall of 2018.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>During Year 2 a 3-week period of MPC measurements was conducted during January/February 2019 at Storm Peak Laboratory near Steamboat Springs, Colorado. The team successfully supported all field operations, including extensive ancillary measurements of trace gases, and aerosol and cloud microphysics. The SPIDER inlet was used to measure and quantify cloud drop and ice residuals. These residuals were compared to water content and cloud element measurements at SPL.&nbsp;Via a partnership with the National Center of Atmospheric Research&nbsp; water vapor isotopic analyzers were added by Dr. Adriana Bailey: one targeting ice crystals and the other targeting interstitial vapor.&nbsp;&nbsp;Simultaneously, the Storm Peak Laboratory team had a water vapor isotopic analyzer for the measurement of ambient vapor.&nbsp;This represented the first proof-of-concept measurements of isotope ratios to infer the microphysical conditions that affected the formation and growth of the ice crystals observed.&nbsp;</p> <p>The field campaign planned for Year 3 (2020 and 2021) was delayed by the COVID-19 pandemic and conducted during Year 4 under a No Cost Extension. Work was minimized in Year 3 to preserve funding while data analysis and paper writing continued:&nbsp;</p> <p>Koolik et al.: A phase separation inlet for droplets, ice residuals, and interstitial aerosol particles, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 15, 3213?3222, https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-15-3213-2022, 2022.</p> <p>Also during Year 3, Dr. Hallar and Dr. Cziczo worked closely with Handix Scientific Inc. to conduct the first long-term deployment of continuous measurement of ice nucleating particles in the U.S.&nbsp;&nbsp;Measurement began in October 2020 and ended on January 2021. &nbsp;This data has served to provide a deeper understanding of the characteristics of ice nucleating particles at Storm Peak Lab. This was an excellent test of the new technology, and resulted in the following paper currently under review:&nbsp;</p> <p>Hodshireet al.: A High-Resolution Record of Ice Nuclei Concentrations Between &minus;20 to &minus;30 ?C for Fall and Winter at Storm Peak Laboratory with the autonomous Continuous Flow Diffusion Chamber Ice Activation Spectrometer, Atmos. Meas. Tech. Discuss. [preprint], https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-2022-216, in review, 2022.</p> <p>During Year 4 (2021-2022), the 2<sup>nd</sup>&nbsp;field deployment successfully took place in January, 2022. &nbsp;A new partnership was started during Year 4 with the Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT). Dr. Larissa Lacher participated in the field study by deploying a Portable Ice Nucleation Experiment (PINE) to support the closure experiment. The KIT PINE provided a continuous ice nucleation dataset from October 2021 ? July 2022. KIT also facilitated the loan of a PALAS Cloud Droplet Analyzer&nbsp;to complement Storm Peak Laboratory's facility instruments during the deployment.&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, the Storm Peak Laboratory team supported Dr. Naruki Hiranuma and his team from West Texas A&amp;M University to conduct complementary measurements during the 2022 field campaign. The group collected total aerosol particles and cloud residuals directly sampled from mixed-phase clouds by means of a custom-made field-deployed pumped counterflow virtual impactor.</p> <p>This project also tasked Dr. Hallar's team with extensively evaluating the Cloud Condensation Nuclei (CCN) concentration data collected at Storm Peak Laboratory. &nbsp;As shown in the following paper under review, it was found that new particle formation significantly impacts the number concentration of CCN in the Spring and Winter at Storm Peak Laboratory:</p> <p>Hirshornet al.: Seasonal Significance of New Particle Formation Impacts on Cloud Condensation Nuclei at a Mountaintop Location, Atmos. Chem. Phys. Discuss. [preprint], https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2022-338, in review, 2022.</p> <p>Numerous graduate students and postdoctoral researchers from MIT, Purdue University, and University of Utah were provided field training via this project and are listed under the personnel. Outreach activities were also produced in partnership with both Science for the Public and Superheroes of Science.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Cziczo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054847/2054847_10539576_1670512496575_Datafromdeployment--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054847/2054847_10539576_1670512496575_Datafromdeployment--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Atmospheric conditions during deployment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054847/2054847_10539576_1670512496575_Datafromdeployment--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Atmospheric conditions during deployment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Atmospheric conditions during proof of concept deployment</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lesly Franco</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Cziczo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Atmospheric conditions during deployment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054847/2054847_10539576_1670512566176_Teammembersduringdeployment--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054847/2054847_10539576_1670512566176_Teammembersduringdeployment--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Team members during deployment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2054847/2054847_10539576_1670512566176_Teammembersduringdeployment--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Team members during deployment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Team members from KIT and Purdue during deployment</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dan Cziczo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Cziczo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Team members during deployment</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This outlines the outcomes of the NSF award entitled "Collaborative Research: An in situ Closure Study of Mixed Phase Clouds at Storm Peak"   This project improved our understanding of Mixed Phase Clouds (MPCs), where both droplets and ice can exist, since they are of critical importance in understanding climate and precipitation and how they could change under different emission scenarios in the future.   Project goals were successfully completed. We note PI Cziczo moved institutions during the grant period which resulted in some personnel changes. An 18 month no cost extensions was requested due to an inability to perform the required field work during the pandemic. Despite these challenges all work was ultimately completed although final papers remain in the preparation and submission stages.  During Year 1 of the project (2018-2019), the team, then at MIT, designed the cloud phase-separating inlet, based on the SPIDER prototype, for characterization of mixed phase clouds at Storm Peak Laboratory (SPL). The design and fabrication work was performed in the lab at MIT from spring to fall of 2018.    During Year 2 a 3-week period of MPC measurements was conducted during January/February 2019 at Storm Peak Laboratory near Steamboat Springs, Colorado. The team successfully supported all field operations, including extensive ancillary measurements of trace gases, and aerosol and cloud microphysics. The SPIDER inlet was used to measure and quantify cloud drop and ice residuals. These residuals were compared to water content and cloud element measurements at SPL. Via a partnership with the National Center of Atmospheric Research  water vapor isotopic analyzers were added by Dr. Adriana Bailey: one targeting ice crystals and the other targeting interstitial vapor.  Simultaneously, the Storm Peak Laboratory team had a water vapor isotopic analyzer for the measurement of ambient vapor. This represented the first proof-of-concept measurements of isotope ratios to infer the microphysical conditions that affected the formation and growth of the ice crystals observed.   The field campaign planned for Year 3 (2020 and 2021) was delayed by the COVID-19 pandemic and conducted during Year 4 under a No Cost Extension. Work was minimized in Year 3 to preserve funding while data analysis and paper writing continued:   Koolik et al.: A phase separation inlet for droplets, ice residuals, and interstitial aerosol particles, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 15, 3213?3222, https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-15-3213-2022, 2022.  Also during Year 3, Dr. Hallar and Dr. Cziczo worked closely with Handix Scientific Inc. to conduct the first long-term deployment of continuous measurement of ice nucleating particles in the U.S.  Measurement began in October 2020 and ended on January 2021.  This data has served to provide a deeper understanding of the characteristics of ice nucleating particles at Storm Peak Lab. This was an excellent test of the new technology, and resulted in the following paper currently under review:   Hodshireet al.: A High-Resolution Record of Ice Nuclei Concentrations Between &minus;20 to &minus;30 ?C for Fall and Winter at Storm Peak Laboratory with the autonomous Continuous Flow Diffusion Chamber Ice Activation Spectrometer, Atmos. Meas. Tech. Discuss. [preprint], https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-2022-216, in review, 2022.  During Year 4 (2021-2022), the 2nd field deployment successfully took place in January, 2022.  A new partnership was started during Year 4 with the Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT). Dr. Larissa Lacher participated in the field study by deploying a Portable Ice Nucleation Experiment (PINE) to support the closure experiment. The KIT PINE provided a continuous ice nucleation dataset from October 2021 ? July 2022. KIT also facilitated the loan of a PALAS Cloud Droplet Analyzer to complement Storm Peak Laboratory's facility instruments during the deployment.   Additionally, the Storm Peak Laboratory team supported Dr. Naruki Hiranuma and his team from West Texas A&amp;M University to conduct complementary measurements during the 2022 field campaign. The group collected total aerosol particles and cloud residuals directly sampled from mixed-phase clouds by means of a custom-made field-deployed pumped counterflow virtual impactor.  This project also tasked Dr. Hallar's team with extensively evaluating the Cloud Condensation Nuclei (CCN) concentration data collected at Storm Peak Laboratory.  As shown in the following paper under review, it was found that new particle formation significantly impacts the number concentration of CCN in the Spring and Winter at Storm Peak Laboratory:  Hirshornet al.: Seasonal Significance of New Particle Formation Impacts on Cloud Condensation Nuclei at a Mountaintop Location, Atmos. Chem. Phys. Discuss. [preprint], https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2022-338, in review, 2022.  Numerous graduate students and postdoctoral researchers from MIT, Purdue University, and University of Utah were provided field training via this project and are listed under the personnel. Outreach activities were also produced in partnership with both Science for the Public and Superheroes of Science.          Last Modified: 12/08/2022       Submitted by: Daniel J Cziczo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
