<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Waiting to Exhale:  Quantifying Tropical Storm-Induced Increased Flux of Coastal Wetland Carbon into the Atmosphere?]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100937.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100937</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henrietta Edmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hedmonds@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927427</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In the summer and fall of 2020, the coastal bays of Louisiana have experienced impacts from a number of tropical storms/hurricanes in close procession. Tropical storm Marco, Hurricanes Laura, Sally and Beta made their closest approaches to Barataria Bay from 81 km for Marco, up to 379 km for Beta. Storm erosion can lead to carbon from coastal soils being released to the atmosphere as carbon dioxide (CO2). Scientists rarely have the opportunity to assess the impact of tropical storms on the conversion of wetland soil carbon to CO2 release to the atmosphere, because they don’t have detailed measurements from before the storms to compare with post-storm data. This project has an opportunity to benefit from an existing NSF grant with four years of extensive measurements. RAPID-response funding will support intensive sampling of Barataria Bay in the immediate aftermath of the 2020 storms, and up to a year afterwards. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite no direct strikes to the coastal basin, marsh edge erosion rates were up to 60 times higher than the 4-year long-term average. This is already an important finding since most measurements focus on coastlines with direct strikes but clearly, substantial wetland erosion occurs from tropical storms imparting wind fields driving wave energy at substantial distances. Consequently, a particularly active tropical storm season has led to significant carbon-rich wetland soil being dumped into the shallow, aerobic waters of the Barataria Bay in a relatively short period of time. The primary questions to be addressed by this project are whether and how accelerated erosion from the 2020 storm season will lead to a significant increase in CO2 outgassing from the bay to the atmosphere, and for how long the effects will persist. The team of investigators will continue to measure marsh edge erosion over the next year correlated to twice a month water sampling of bay surface waters for determination of dissolved inorganic and organic carbon, and dissolved CO2. Sampling will be conducted along transects running from close proximity to the wetland erosion stations out in the open bay. Air-sea CO2 flux will be estimated using a model and correlated to the wetland erosion rates. The team will compare the storm event-induced “bay respiration” rate with that of next year. This RAPID project will yield several important outcomes: 1) Determination of the increase and temporal impact of wetland carbon loss to the atmosphere from a number of significant storms, similar to what is expected for the future under a changing climate; 2) Understanding if the organic C breakdown to CO2 will increase coastal acidification within the coastal bay.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2054935</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John R White</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jrwhite@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000091404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zuo</FirstName>
<LastName>Xue</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zuo Xue</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zxue@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000692905</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 HIMES HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECQEYCHRNKJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1389</Code>
<Text>CARBON CYCLE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~100937</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project took advantage of the busy hurricane season in 2020 for the Gulf of Mexico to determine how the passage of hurricanes changes the carbon flux from coastal waters and coastal wetlands.&nbsp; While most research investigate the direct impact of hurricanes, we examined what happens when the hurricane is further away but still generates a wind field of 20-30 mph at some distance away.&nbsp; We found the erosion rates of the coastal wetlands were, on average, 60 times higher from the daily average when a far away storm increased wind wave activity.&nbsp;&nbsp; This is an important consideration because these wetlands are storing lots of carbon in the soils and if far away storms can still cause erosion, then the carbon dioxide is released to the atmosphere.&nbsp; We also observed and modeled how carbon dioxide release increases from coastal waters when a hurricane passes by.&nbsp; There are two processes at work when that happens.&nbsp; The first is the water is stirred up, allowing carbon dioxide at depth to be released to the air or in the case of Hurricane Laura (2020) the phytoplankton growth was weakened, so instead of the carbon dioxide being taken up by these plants, it was released to the atmosphere.&nbsp; This research showed that for the coastal waters, there can be a short term release of carbon dioxide to the atmosphere due to hurricane passage but that for coastal wetlands, up to 800 years of stored soil carbon can be release to the water, with the vast majority released to the atmosphere.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2023<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;R&nbsp;White</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2054935/2054935_10708422_1688575063567_Hurricanepaths--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2054935/2054935_10708422_1688575063567_Hurricanepaths--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hurricane paths"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2054935/2054935_10708422_1688575063567_Hurricanepaths--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hurricane paths"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The tracks of far field hurricanes and the close approach storm Zeta to our project area in 2020</div> <div class="imageCredit">George Xue</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;R&nbsp;White</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hurricane paths</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project took advantage of the busy hurricane season in 2020 for the Gulf of Mexico to determine how the passage of hurricanes changes the carbon flux from coastal waters and coastal wetlands.  While most research investigate the direct impact of hurricanes, we examined what happens when the hurricane is further away but still generates a wind field of 20-30 mph at some distance away.  We found the erosion rates of the coastal wetlands were, on average, 60 times higher from the daily average when a far away storm increased wind wave activity.   This is an important consideration because these wetlands are storing lots of carbon in the soils and if far away storms can still cause erosion, then the carbon dioxide is released to the atmosphere.  We also observed and modeled how carbon dioxide release increases from coastal waters when a hurricane passes by.  There are two processes at work when that happens.  The first is the water is stirred up, allowing carbon dioxide at depth to be released to the air or in the case of Hurricane Laura (2020) the phytoplankton growth was weakened, so instead of the carbon dioxide being taken up by these plants, it was released to the atmosphere.  This research showed that for the coastal waters, there can be a short term release of carbon dioxide to the atmosphere due to hurricane passage but that for coastal wetlands, up to 800 years of stored soil carbon can be release to the water, with the vast majority released to the atmosphere.          Last Modified: 07/05/2023       Submitted by: John R White]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
