<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II: Sustainable Packaging Foam]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1715999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is the reduction in single use plastics that contribute to landfill waste and ocean plastic pollution by replacing these plastics in packaging with a fully biodegradable and naturally sourced alternative. Increasing consumer demand for more sustainable solutions as well as the rapid growth of ecommerce shipping has created an urgent industry need for companies to replace traditional materials with sustainable packaging. This project develops a bio-benign foam that can be produced at scale with drop-in compatible manufacturing processes to create superior biodegradable packaging products at similar cost to traditional expanded polystyrene products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project will scale the production processes of a chitin-based foam to be used as protective packaging. Chitin is a polysaccharide derived from shrimp shell waste. The project fully develop a scalable extrusion process that creates high quality foam and is well-suited to scale for mass production at volumes required to service the packaging industry. With this project, the extrusion process developed can be implemented with supply chain partners to show a fully scalable sustainable packaging material that can meet the increasing demands of the industry. The goals are to achieve high volume production with partners and create protective packaging with the same mechanical performance and density as expanded polystyrene.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2054360</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Felts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Felts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john@cruzfoam.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000749945</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cruz Foam, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>SANTA CRUZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>950605756</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9259892695</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2851 MISSION ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LPCSKCUXLKG3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CRUZ FOAM INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HLQ4ADDZ31S6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cruz Foam, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950605756</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2851 Mission St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~1008000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~707999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>This SBIR phase II award has yielded significant intellectual merit through the development of a novel biodegradable foam specifically designed for packaging applications. The foam possesses tunable mechanical properties, enabling it to mimic the characteristics of expanded polyethylene and expanded polystyrene, which are the leading packaging foams in the industry. Its range of densities makes it suitable for packaging delicate items such as glass, as well as heavier objects like appliances.</p> <p>To achieve these desirable properties, an extensive research effort was undertaken to explore various foam compositions and evaluate the impact of each component within the formulation. Furthermore, the production process of this foam was optimized by adapting existing equipment, such as twin-screw or compounding extruders, which can generate foam at a rate of up to 2000 pounds per hour. This level of production output is comparable to that of current plastic materials, ensuring scalability and commercial viability.</p> <p>Moreover, in addition to the foam's processing optimization, several packaging designs were explored utilizing this innovative material. These include hybrid corrugated/foam packaging for appliances, as well as paper/foam packaging for cold chain and e-commerce applications. By investigating these alternative packaging designs, the project further demonstrates its commitment to innovation and versatility in addressing packaging challenges across various sectors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>The broader impacts of this research are significant, particularly in relation to the environmental and societal consequences associated with single-use plastics. The ever-increasing volume of plastic waste, much of which ends up in landfills or the ocean, poses a severe threat to the environment. These plastics take hundreds of years to degrade, releasing microplastics that harm various forms of life. With the rapid growth of e-commerce and home delivery, the use of protective packaging has surged, exacerbating the plastic waste problem.</p> <p>However, the biodegradable nature of the developed foam, coupled with its recyclability when combined with paper products, offers a sustainable solution. By composting or recycling the foam alongside paper materials, the environmental impact of single-use packaging can be dramatically reduced. This breakthrough has the potential to contribute to a significant shift away from environmentally damaging plastic packaging materials.</p> <p>Furthermore, the project's utilization of existing manufacturing equipment enables the production of the biodegradable foam within the continental United States. By manufacturing in established factories, this innovation generates employment opportunities and contributes to the national economy. The project's emphasis on local production further enhances its positive societal impact.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2023<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Felts</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  This SBIR phase II award has yielded significant intellectual merit through the development of a novel biodegradable foam specifically designed for packaging applications. The foam possesses tunable mechanical properties, enabling it to mimic the characteristics of expanded polyethylene and expanded polystyrene, which are the leading packaging foams in the industry. Its range of densities makes it suitable for packaging delicate items such as glass, as well as heavier objects like appliances.  To achieve these desirable properties, an extensive research effort was undertaken to explore various foam compositions and evaluate the impact of each component within the formulation. Furthermore, the production process of this foam was optimized by adapting existing equipment, such as twin-screw or compounding extruders, which can generate foam at a rate of up to 2000 pounds per hour. This level of production output is comparable to that of current plastic materials, ensuring scalability and commercial viability.  Moreover, in addition to the foam's processing optimization, several packaging designs were explored utilizing this innovative material. These include hybrid corrugated/foam packaging for appliances, as well as paper/foam packaging for cold chain and e-commerce applications. By investigating these alternative packaging designs, the project further demonstrates its commitment to innovation and versatility in addressing packaging challenges across various sectors.     Broader Impacts:  The broader impacts of this research are significant, particularly in relation to the environmental and societal consequences associated with single-use plastics. The ever-increasing volume of plastic waste, much of which ends up in landfills or the ocean, poses a severe threat to the environment. These plastics take hundreds of years to degrade, releasing microplastics that harm various forms of life. With the rapid growth of e-commerce and home delivery, the use of protective packaging has surged, exacerbating the plastic waste problem.  However, the biodegradable nature of the developed foam, coupled with its recyclability when combined with paper products, offers a sustainable solution. By composting or recycling the foam alongside paper materials, the environmental impact of single-use packaging can be dramatically reduced. This breakthrough has the potential to contribute to a significant shift away from environmentally damaging plastic packaging materials.  Furthermore, the project's utilization of existing manufacturing equipment enables the production of the biodegradable foam within the continental United States. By manufacturing in established factories, this innovation generates employment opportunities and contributes to the national economy. The project's emphasis on local production further enhances its positive societal impact.          Last Modified: 08/01/2023       Submitted by: John Felts]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
