<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[International Workshop on Operator Theory and Its Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Constanze Liaw</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cliaw@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928042</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The funds will provide travel support for up to twenty junior US based scientists in operator theory, electrical engineering and physics to attend the International Workshop on Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA), which will be held at Chapman University, Orange, CA during August 9 - 13, 2021. An important goal is the active participation of young mathematicians, such as graduate students, post-docs, and other junior level positions. This goal will be achieved by encouraging every junior participant to give a contributed talk and by providing space for informal discussions and avenues for future collaborations. All invited speakers will be asked to ensure that part of their talks be accessible to young researchers. Due to its yearly international presence, IWOTA facilitates the enlargement of mathematics networks from all around the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Operator Theory lies at the intersection of several fields such as analysis, quantum mechanics, theoretical physics, probability, stochastic processes, signal processing, machine learning, and many others. As quantum physics can be described via applied operator theory the two special sessions on quantum physics and on super-oscillations are at the forefront of one of the biggest challenges of the 21st century: quantum computing. The theory of stochastic processes and operator theory have numerous intersections, which require deep tools of operator theory to explore. Stochastic processes and their derivatives (usually generalized stochastic processes) may be studied using the theory of Gelfand triples, obtained by applying the Bochner-Minlos theorem to a positive definite function on a Frechet nuclear space. Replacing the Fock space by the free Fock space, one arrives at the non-commutative setting. In a similar vein, replacing the complex numbers by the Grassmann algebra or by a ternary algebra one gets new connections with super mathematics and manifolds. Four of the special sessions focus on this circle of ideas. Recent research in bicomplex, ternary, and quaternionic analysis use operator theory techniques to relate the intrinsic analytic structure and the many types of operators that arise and obtain realization formulas in each case. Applicability of some techniques in a more general hypercomplex setting provides even more applications to physics and digital signal processing. Ternary algebras are known to be a promising candidate for the algebraic confinement model for the problem of observability of three quarks/anti-quarks in Quantum Field Theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2055270</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mihaela</FirstName>
<LastName>Vajiac</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mihaela B Vajiac</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbvajiac@chapman.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000839152</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Alpay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel A Alpay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alpay@chapman.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000839153</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Chapman University</Name>
<CityName>ORANGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>928661005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7146287383</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>40</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA40</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EN9DMTETW3N1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHAPMAN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Chapman University]]></Name>
<CityName>Orange</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>928661005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>40</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA40</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Operator Theory lies at the intersection of several fields such as analysis, quantum mechanics, theoretical physics, probability, stochastic processes, signal processing, machine learning, and many others. The International Workshop of Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA 2021) brought together mathematicians working in a variety of fields where applications of operator theory are a common denominator. It is worth noting that 2021 marked the first year when IWOTA was held on the West Coast of the United States since its inception in 1981 in Santa Monica, CA. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p class="Default">The co-PIs, Alpay and Vajiac, received support for providing travel funds for up to twenty junior and scientists from under-represented mathematical communities, who do not have support from NSF or other sources. The funds allowed them to not only provide travel for this International Workshop on Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA Chapman University, Orange, August 9 - 13, 2021), but also, after additional approval and extension of funds timeline, for an additional Workshop under a subset of the same themes held during May-June 2022.&nbsp; <strong>&nbsp;</strong>The PI and co-PI had also received a Chapman University On-Campus Conference Award that helped defray some of the costs for both conferences, for all participants, such as conference dinners, coffee breaks, etc.</p> <p class="Default">The first goal was to fund underrepresented communities of mathematicians in the field to the IWOTA Chapman University, Orange, August 9 - 13, 2021. A modest registration fee was charged to all IWOTA 2021 participants. Using NSF funds, the PI and coPI sponsored all registration fees for the members of the funded communities.</p> <p class="Default">Here is a synopsis of the topics of the Special Sessions organized:</p> <ol> <li>Applications of Operator Theory in Quantum Physics&nbsp; </li> <li>Fourier Analysis and Applications (folded in Section 6) </li> <li>Hilbert Spaces of Analytic Functions and Applications&nbsp; </li> <li>Infinite Dimensional Analysis and Stochastic Processes </li> <li>Laplacian Eigenfunctions ? Counts, Morphologies and Statistics </li> <li>Linear Systems, Fourier Analysis, and Applications</li> <li>Operator Theory and Interpolation in Several Complex Variables </li> <li>Operators and Hypercomplex Analysis </li> <li>Operator Theory on reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces </li> <li>Pseudo-differential Operators </li> <li>Spectral Theory and Differential Operators </li> <li>Theory of Superoscillations </li> <li>General Session for Contributed Papers</li> </ol> <p>The objectives of these major activities were the dissemination and presentation of cutting-edge results in Operator Theory and Applications. For both events there were many mathematicians that attended in person, allowing for a collegial working atmosphere. Both the in person and online events converged to forge many collaborations in the fields covered.&nbsp; The IWOTA Workshop held over 155 talks in 13 parallel sessions, in addition to the 10 plenary and 10 semi-plenary ones and brought together mathematicians and engineers who work in functional analysis and its application to related areas.</p> <p class="Default">The remaining funds were used to organize a small IWOTA satellite workshop during the period May 28th-June 4th, 2022, titled ?Workshop on Operator Theory with an eye on Linear Systems and Hypercomplex Analysis. The structure was as follows: May 28-29 and June 3-4 there were two intensive mini-courses organized for each of the two days, one in the morning and one in the afternoon, up to a total of four speakers, all researchers from under-represented categories. From May 30th to June 2nd there were four days of regular talks by the participants and intense collaboration. No registration fee was charged for the subsequent satellite workshop. The remaining NSF funds together with other funds we secured from our institution were used to support travel expenses for the same underrepresented categories of participants either minicourse speakers or regular speakers.</p> <p class="Default">The supported four mini-course speakers from underrepresented mathematical communities were Professors Isabelle Chalendar from University of Lyon, Paula Cerejeiras from University of Aveiro, Irene Sabadini, from Politecnico di Milano, and Kasso Okoudjou, from Tufts University. One of the co-PIs, Professor Daniel Alpay, was also a mini-course speaker, with no support from the grant, therefore no conflicts of interest arose.</p> <p>The topics of the minicourses of the satellite workshop were:</p> <ol> <li>Hypercomplex operator theory presented by Prof.      Paula Cerejeiras, (University of Aveiro, Portugal) </li> <li>A theory of orthogonal polynomial on the      Sierpinski gasket presented by Prof. Kasso Okoudjou, (Tufts University,      USA) </li> <li>Semigroups of weighted composition operators on      spaces of holomorphic functions presented by Prof. Isabelle Chalendar,      (University of Lyon I, France) </li> <li>Functional calculi on the S-spectrum in the      quaternionic and in the hypercomplex setting presented by Prof. Irene      Sabadini, (Politecnico di Milan, Italy) </li> <li>Infinite Dimensional Analysis presented by Prof.      Daniel Alpay (Chapman University). </li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Conference related activities, from presented talks, to conversations with experts in the field during the breaks (both in person and on Zoom), greatly contributed to the increase in research skills and experience of undergraduate and graduate students, post-docs, as well as mathematicians from underrepresented communities. For more details, please see the conference webpages.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Conference Webpage:</p> <p><a href="https://www.chapman.edu/scst/conferences-and-events/iwota-2021/index.aspx">https://www.chapman.edu/scst/conferences-and-events/iwota-2021/index.aspx</a></p> <p>Satellite Conference Webpage:</p> <p><a href="https://www1.chapman.edu/~mbvajiac/conferences/2022Conference.html">https://www1.chapman.edu/~mbvajiac/conferences/2022Conference.html</a></p> <p>Plenary and semi-plenary IWOTA 2021 talks are now online under our Schmid College of Science and Technology YouTube channel:</p> <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLXlinOq24a9Q44rLeVTjdEpuAao4Gjyif">https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLXlinOq24a9Q44rLeVTjdEpuAao4Gjyif</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Mihaela&nbsp;B&nbsp;Vajiac</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Operator Theory lies at the intersection of several fields such as analysis, quantum mechanics, theoretical physics, probability, stochastic processes, signal processing, machine learning, and many others. The International Workshop of Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA 2021) brought together mathematicians working in a variety of fields where applications of operator theory are a common denominator. It is worth noting that 2021 marked the first year when IWOTA was held on the West Coast of the United States since its inception in 1981 in Santa Monica, CA.   The co-PIs, Alpay and Vajiac, received support for providing travel funds for up to twenty junior and scientists from under-represented mathematical communities, who do not have support from NSF or other sources. The funds allowed them to not only provide travel for this International Workshop on Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA Chapman University, Orange, August 9 - 13, 2021), but also, after additional approval and extension of funds timeline, for an additional Workshop under a subset of the same themes held during May-June 2022.   The PI and co-PI had also received a Chapman University On-Campus Conference Award that helped defray some of the costs for both conferences, for all participants, such as conference dinners, coffee breaks, etc. The first goal was to fund underrepresented communities of mathematicians in the field to the IWOTA Chapman University, Orange, August 9 - 13, 2021. A modest registration fee was charged to all IWOTA 2021 participants. Using NSF funds, the PI and coPI sponsored all registration fees for the members of the funded communities. Here is a synopsis of the topics of the Special Sessions organized:  Applications of Operator Theory in Quantum Physics   Fourier Analysis and Applications (folded in Section 6)  Hilbert Spaces of Analytic Functions and Applications   Infinite Dimensional Analysis and Stochastic Processes  Laplacian Eigenfunctions ? Counts, Morphologies and Statistics  Linear Systems, Fourier Analysis, and Applications Operator Theory and Interpolation in Several Complex Variables  Operators and Hypercomplex Analysis  Operator Theory on reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces  Pseudo-differential Operators  Spectral Theory and Differential Operators  Theory of Superoscillations  General Session for Contributed Papers   The objectives of these major activities were the dissemination and presentation of cutting-edge results in Operator Theory and Applications. For both events there were many mathematicians that attended in person, allowing for a collegial working atmosphere. Both the in person and online events converged to forge many collaborations in the fields covered.  The IWOTA Workshop held over 155 talks in 13 parallel sessions, in addition to the 10 plenary and 10 semi-plenary ones and brought together mathematicians and engineers who work in functional analysis and its application to related areas. The remaining funds were used to organize a small IWOTA satellite workshop during the period May 28th-June 4th, 2022, titled ?Workshop on Operator Theory with an eye on Linear Systems and Hypercomplex Analysis. The structure was as follows: May 28-29 and June 3-4 there were two intensive mini-courses organized for each of the two days, one in the morning and one in the afternoon, up to a total of four speakers, all researchers from under-represented categories. From May 30th to June 2nd there were four days of regular talks by the participants and intense collaboration. No registration fee was charged for the subsequent satellite workshop. The remaining NSF funds together with other funds we secured from our institution were used to support travel expenses for the same underrepresented categories of participants either minicourse speakers or regular speakers. The supported four mini-course speakers from underrepresented mathematical communities were Professors Isabelle Chalendar from University of Lyon, Paula Cerejeiras from University of Aveiro, Irene Sabadini, from Politecnico di Milano, and Kasso Okoudjou, from Tufts University. One of the co-PIs, Professor Daniel Alpay, was also a mini-course speaker, with no support from the grant, therefore no conflicts of interest arose.  The topics of the minicourses of the satellite workshop were:  Hypercomplex operator theory presented by Prof.      Paula Cerejeiras, (University of Aveiro, Portugal)  A theory of orthogonal polynomial on the      Sierpinski gasket presented by Prof. Kasso Okoudjou, (Tufts University,      USA)  Semigroups of weighted composition operators on      spaces of holomorphic functions presented by Prof. Isabelle Chalendar,      (University of Lyon I, France)  Functional calculi on the S-spectrum in the      quaternionic and in the hypercomplex setting presented by Prof. Irene      Sabadini, (Politecnico di Milan, Italy)  Infinite Dimensional Analysis presented by Prof.      Daniel Alpay (Chapman University).       Conference related activities, from presented talks, to conversations with experts in the field during the breaks (both in person and on Zoom), greatly contributed to the increase in research skills and experience of undergraduate and graduate students, post-docs, as well as mathematicians from underrepresented communities. For more details, please see the conference webpages.     Conference Webpage:  https://www.chapman.edu/scst/conferences-and-events/iwota-2021/index.aspx  Satellite Conference Webpage:  https://www1.chapman.edu/~mbvajiac/conferences/2022Conference.html  Plenary and semi-plenary IWOTA 2021 talks are now online under our Schmid College of Science and Technology YouTube channel:  https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLXlinOq24a9Q44rLeVTjdEpuAao4Gjyif          Last Modified: 11/29/2022       Submitted by: Mihaela B Vajiac]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
