<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Multiplexed paper-based test for rapid diagnosis of early-stage Lyme Disease]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercialization potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a low-cost rapid diagnostic tool with the ability to measure multiple health markers in a single test. Development of this platform may benefit the healthcare system by improving the accessibility of diagnostic and prognostic testing that requires a panel of measurements. Specifically, there is potential for an early-stage Lyme disease (LD) diagnostic. Approximately 300,000 people contract LD each year, incurring a $1.3 billion cost to the medical system. Unfortunately, much of the societal and economic costs of LD stem from misdiagnosis due to the low sensitivity of the current Centers for Disease Control (CDC)-recommended testing protocol, which is typically &lt;50% for the early-stage of disease, a time when many patients seek care. Therefore, the commercialization of an accurate and rapid test may provide a low-cost yet effective tool for identifying early-stage infection at the point-of-care, leading to faster and more effective treatment. The results from this potential I-Corps project also may benefit the diagnostics and medical community by demonstrating the value of a data-driven approach to multiplexed rapid testing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a point-of-care diagnostic assay for early-stage Lyme disease (LD). Previously, the design and validation of a low-cost, paper-based vertical flow assay (VFA) was completed. Unlike standard rapid testing formats, the proposed VFA technology enables the point-of-care measurement (from patient blood) of a large panel of antibodies specific to the early-stage LD infection. A data-driven diagnostic algorithm is then used to infer a LD diagnosis from the panel of measurements, enabling sensitive and specific testing of suspected early-stage Lyme patients across a diverse population with varying immune responses.  An initial peer-reviewed clinical study of the prototype assay and diagnostic algorithm reported sensitivity and specificity of 87.5% and 96.7%, respectively, when compared to a rigorous clinical gold standard using all early-stage LD samples. These initial technical results show potential for effective early-stage LD diagnosis at the point-of-care, enabling faster and more effective treatment that could mitigate debilitating late-stage symptoms and associated costs to the healthcare system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2055749</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aydogan</FirstName>
<LastName>Ozcan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aydogan Ozcan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ozcan@ee.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000488625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/26/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[68-119 Engineering IV Building,]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><dl class="clearing"><dd> <div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>The NSF I-Corps team investigated the  potential product-market fit of an innovative diagnostic test developed  at UCLA and the PATHS-UP Center, an NSF-sponsored Engineering Research  Center (ERC). The rapid testing platform uniquely supports up to 100  independent simultaneous assay reactions within a compact plastic  cassette and leverages a compact reader working with advanced  calibration algorithms to accurately report measurement results of key  clinical panels. Over the course of the I-Corps program, the team  investigated a potential application of this technology for Lyme Disease  testing in the primary care or urgent care setting.</p> <p>Working in the I-Corps Winter Cohort, the team identified three related  customer segments; primary care doctors in private practice, testing  purchasing boards for hospital systems, and directors of urgent care  testing. Furthermore, as Lyme Disease is only endemic in the Northeast  and Midwest, these customer segments were further segmented due to  region. During the I-Corps project, the team interviewed over 110 potential  customers within these segments along with influencers and end-users,  with interviews primarily focused in the Northeastern and Midwestern  United States.</p> <p>Under the I-Corps instruction, the team tested several hypothetical  value propositions and challenged initial assumptions regarding  product-market fit of this potential rapid Lyme test. Through numerous  interviews with primary care physicians, the team created a working workflow  map of the Lyme diagnostic odyssey,  which underscored paint-points and inefficiencies of the current  clinical state-of-the-art. The team importantly learned that a majority (&gt;60%)  of physicians interviewed in endemic regions do not rely or wait on  blood testing as a decision point for providing antibiotic treatment.  Although a rapid diagnostic  tool would be helpful in the decision-making process, it would not  necessarily enable faster treatment for patients already presenting with  clinical symptoms and/or a patient history suggesting Lyme Disease. &nbsp;Another major takeaway was that private practice clinics, unlike the in the urgent care  setting, do not generate revenue from in-house testing. Therefore,  adoption by this customer segment is driven primarily by patient demand  and/or changes to physician guidelines along with ease of reimbursement  through insurance. Additionally, because most of the private practice  clinics indicated during interviews that they have unilateral  decision-making precedents for using new tests, private practice  physicians could be potential early adopters of a new rapid diagnostic.</p> <p>Through these interviews, the team was also able to identify the potential  early adopters with the most urgent unmet need as Family doctors (both  Primary care physicians, and Advanced Nurse Practitioners) who operated  in rural areas with high-tick exposure and lack of frequent access to  centralized testing. These customer archetypes consistently spoke to a  critical need for a new diagnostic tool that could guide antibiotic  treatment decisions among a patient population that has limited access  to testing sites, yet high tick exposure and high anxiety about Lyme  disease and other tick-borne illnesses.</p> <p>These findings were captured in the Team&rsquo;s final &lsquo;Lesson&rsquo;s Learned&rsquo;  Presentation during the final I-Corps session, where it was concluded  that additional customer discovery interviews should be conducted to  determine other commercially-viable applications of the core technology.  The veterinary market for tick-borne diagnostics along with the at-home  allergy testing market were identified as potential areas of impact,  and additional interviews were conducted with customer segments in both  markets.</p> </div> </dd></dl><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2022<br>      Modified by: Aydogan&nbsp;Ozcan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The NSF I-Corps team investigated the  potential product-market fit of an innovative diagnostic test developed  at UCLA and the PATHS-UP Center, an NSF-sponsored Engineering Research  Center (ERC). The rapid testing platform uniquely supports up to 100  independent simultaneous assay reactions within a compact plastic  cassette and leverages a compact reader working with advanced  calibration algorithms to accurately report measurement results of key  clinical panels. Over the course of the I-Corps program, the team  investigated a potential application of this technology for Lyme Disease  testing in the primary care or urgent care setting.  Working in the I-Corps Winter Cohort, the team identified three related  customer segments; primary care doctors in private practice, testing  purchasing boards for hospital systems, and directors of urgent care  testing. Furthermore, as Lyme Disease is only endemic in the Northeast  and Midwest, these customer segments were further segmented due to  region. During the I-Corps project, the team interviewed over 110 potential  customers within these segments along with influencers and end-users,  with interviews primarily focused in the Northeastern and Midwestern  United States.  Under the I-Corps instruction, the team tested several hypothetical  value propositions and challenged initial assumptions regarding  product-market fit of this potential rapid Lyme test. Through numerous  interviews with primary care physicians, the team created a working workflow  map of the Lyme diagnostic odyssey,  which underscored paint-points and inefficiencies of the current  clinical state-of-the-art. The team importantly learned that a majority (&gt;60%)  of physicians interviewed in endemic regions do not rely or wait on  blood testing as a decision point for providing antibiotic treatment.  Although a rapid diagnostic  tool would be helpful in the decision-making process, it would not  necessarily enable faster treatment for patients already presenting with  clinical symptoms and/or a patient history suggesting Lyme Disease.  Another major takeaway was that private practice clinics, unlike the in the urgent care  setting, do not generate revenue from in-house testing. Therefore,  adoption by this customer segment is driven primarily by patient demand  and/or changes to physician guidelines along with ease of reimbursement  through insurance. Additionally, because most of the private practice  clinics indicated during interviews that they have unilateral  decision-making precedents for using new tests, private practice  physicians could be potential early adopters of a new rapid diagnostic.  Through these interviews, the team was also able to identify the potential  early adopters with the most urgent unmet need as Family doctors (both  Primary care physicians, and Advanced Nurse Practitioners) who operated  in rural areas with high-tick exposure and lack of frequent access to  centralized testing. These customer archetypes consistently spoke to a  critical need for a new diagnostic tool that could guide antibiotic  treatment decisions among a patient population that has limited access  to testing sites, yet high tick exposure and high anxiety about Lyme  disease and other tick-borne illnesses.  These findings were captured in the Team’s final ‘Lesson’s Learned’  Presentation during the final I-Corps session, where it was concluded  that additional customer discovery interviews should be conducted to  determine other commercially-viable applications of the core technology.  The veterinary market for tick-borne diagnostics along with the at-home  allergy testing market were identified as potential areas of impact,  and additional interviews were conducted with customer segments in both  markets.         Last Modified: 07/10/2022       Submitted by: Aydogan Ozcan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
